(Scott) Hello.
I'm Ridley Scott
and I'm gonna be talking about Alien,
which was the second film of my
career, which followed The Duellists.
I made this film in the year 1978,
which was released in 1979.
Uh, the title sequence
I invited a very well-known
graphic designer, in fact, designers
Steve Frankfurt and Richard Greenberg
to come into the...
To help me
where we really were only talking about
the poster and...
And presswork.
But when I saw their proposal,
I then asked them if they would come in
to actually get involved
in the title sequences.
Because I always felt title sequences
somehow never echo the artwork
on the poster work.
And my only brief to them was
I kind of wanted a hieroglyphic
that would come up at the beginning.
Because I always wanted
to infer or suggest
that this alien could have been a...
From a sophisticated society.
Obviously not comprehendible by us.
But I think the more sophisticated
we made them,
the more frightening they would be.
And so they came up with what I think
is really one of the best title sequences
I've seen in years
and still have seen in years
since the great Saul Bass.
So...
The film was always going to start
in a rather somber, low-key fashion.
And I always remember
having this argument with the...
Some of my colleagues
at that particular time
including the studio,
where they kept saying:
"But nothing happens for 45 minutes."
And I said "Well, that's the whole point."
Because once it starts to happen,
I think we should have them...
And I think while it's for the...
If nothing happens
in the first 45 minutes,
it's revealing the world
that these workers in space
function in.
And it's very interesting today, in 1 999,
we're now talking about deep-mining
ideas in space.
Which, of course, as part of
the description of the Nostromo
is in fact involved in just that,
mining in deep space.
So the title sequence continues
to unfold
revealing what is the Nostromo,
which suggests some kind of freighter,
aircraft carrier, refinery,
where we gradually come
to what would be regarded
as the living quarters.
And I always wanted
to pull off this idea
of that kind of crazy bird in the middle
of the kitchen
which is dipping into water.
Because I was gonna use that later,
just prior to the ex--
The Nostromo exploding.
I'll explain that later.
Yeah. We begin really with morning
on this ship.
Whatever morning means
in this no-time and no--
No time in space.
But we are witnessing
a spaceship waking up.
Or, in fact, be woken up
by its central drive computer,
which we call Mother.
Kubrick had already found a great name
for his computer,
which was called HAL.
I couldn't think of anything
but to say "mum" or "mother."
And the sinister idea of having
the screens reflected in the faces
of what were essentially
emergency helmets,
which are always in position
on the back of two seats,
seemed to be a great way
of opening the film.
I came up with that idea
when I actually saw the set
coming together.
And so the addition of the helmets
talking to each other was late in the day.
But I think it worked pretty well.
Hypersleep, on long stretches
and probably used as a hospital
when they're all up and about.
I always thought Jerry's music
here was absolutely -
to use a hackneyed word - poetic.
And when I mixed it,
it always brought a lump to my throat
(chuckles)
on this cue right here.
So there, we're looking at seven babies
all slumbering, unsuspecting.
I love this piece of score here.
It's fantastic.
Jerry is one of those musicians
who really watches the actors
and reflects what's going on
with the performance.
To be totally realistic, I always wanted
all the crew to be stark-naked.
Of course, they would be. if they
were lying in any form of hypersleep,
they would be naked.
But for obvious reasons,
I couldn't do that.
Particularly this first shot.
Because there was
a particularly extraordinary view.
And at one stage, it was--
In the discussion,
I said "Well, the women may as
well be, you know, topless."
Because that's what it is.
I wanted to have a total sense
of reality and rawness
to this whole film.
Which because the realer
and truer you get
then I think the scarier it gets later.
But I lost that argument
for obvious reasons and so...
I think I remember now.
I did two versions.
And was told I can't use--
I've gotta use the covered-up version.
It's a very nice segue
into them all being up.
And in this mix here,
we're obviously meeting all the characters.
But I wanted it to be,
in fact, normal early morning chatter.
Bearing in mind, they've probably been
asleep for 18 months.
And so that's where they're eating
rather uninteresting-looking food
because all the food would actually
have to be the first food to enter--
First real food to enter their bodies
in months.
And this scene also, of course,
is introducing the characters,
the below decks,
which are Harry Dean Stanton
and Yaphet Kotto,
already complaining about their deal.
And we never know
whether that's serious
between who's saying what.
So on the real mix, which was--
Even on the six-track Dolby,
it was quite loud and quite aggressive.
That was intentional.
And then you have the peace
in the chamber
where the captain, Tom Skerritt,
wants to find out
why they've been woken up.
Obviously, the sets are designed
for total claustrophobia,
with low ceilings and sealed corridors
and sealed chambers.
And they were all pretty well four-sided,
the ceilings,
and it was quite a kind of task or challenge
for the lighting cameraman
who, I think, I believe until recently,
has never done another feature film,
but was a great colleague of mine
where we've done many television
commercials together,
called Derek Vanlint.
And I still think that
when you see this in DVD,
it will recapture
what the original print was like.
And I think Derek
did an absolutely wonderful job.
Then we have a nice connection
with Earth
with Sigourney's reference
to Antarctic or Antarctica.
So they're getting close. Probably,
uh, many million miles, but still close.
What I thought about this crew
in the way they were characterized
is that we were always told
just enough about them.
So we knew classically who they were,
who the troublemakers were,
who the politicians were.
There was already a class system
with below deck and upper deck.
Jerry Goldsmith was a musician
who is kind of a formidable musician
that I approached to see
if he would actually take this onboard.
And he was immediately enthusiastic
about the whole notion,
the whole genre and the whole, you
know, description of the atmosphere
that I had to verbalize to him
at that point.
And I still think, for me,
this is one of the best scores
I've ever been involved with.
It was a real contribution
to the sense of foreboding,
particularly at the beginning of the film.
With the fear, at one point
in the editing process, did not happen--
Nothing happened for 45 minutes.
But I think
Jerry's music sustains the tension.
So that when something
does start to happen,
I think, hopefully,
I think it was successful.
The audience was so sprung-loaded
that the rest was easy. Lt was rock 'n' roll.
Yeah. The casting process was...
What I've now discovered,
like all my films, took a long time.
I select very carefully.
Where, eventually,
it's a gut reaction to saying:
"It's him" or "It's her."
It's a combination of various things.
Obviously, acting capability.
But also it's a physical thing.
And then you're mixing,
putting all these people together.
And so the process
took quite a lot of time.
Because from a director's angle,
I think, that if you cast right
you've got so many other problems
when you're actually
in the process of filming
to turn left, another to right,
the other up, the other down."
So he was doing
this incredibly basic lash-up.
But I think the end result is just...
Still stands up there. It's really good.
We shot and got in close
on the Nostromo.
I cheated like hell
because I was giving it atmosphere.
I guess they may have gas,
if this would be gas.
It wouldn't be atmosphere.
It might be gaseous.
Here we go. There's a bump.
So that's the camera wobbling
and the actors complying
with the wobble.
So I was yanking the camera
all over the place.
I think this is the first time
we get into wobbly cameras
so this precursors rock videos.
(chuckles)
The graphic design here
I always thought was great
because it wasn't over-designed.
If you're in a cockpit now
of a very sophisticated fighter,
it's amazing how basic they are.
And I didn't wanna go into overkill.
I wanted it just to feel raw and real.
All this is just the camera...
As the Nostromo sinks, it's just
a dolly craning up in a smoke room.
So none of this is CGI.
It's all just literally shot.
It always bothered me
that the lights underneath
we couldn't get it in a straight line.
And that drove me crazy,
but eventually we had to shoot.
(laughing]
That model there is only four feet long.
But I think that's pretty big.
I always thought the exhausts
were dodgy.
So the exhausts are getting blown
by the propellers.
I'm trying to get the sense of movement
of the air around it or the gas around it.
But I guess you can buy it.
That leg is about a foot across, so...
Now the fire here was--
Because we were on a pretty
tight schedule on this film, I think
total schedule was about 12 weeks.
So this fire had to be shot in a day.
It was a real scramble.
But with sound effects
and shooting into lights
and of course, the actors,
I think we conveyed the sense
of chaos. And I love this cut.
Straight out of it into "Let's face the music,
and see what kind of trouble we're in."
Part of the reality was actually,
you know,
in handheld camera shooting the lights
and things like that,
which I'd been doing a lot of
in commercials.
And I was always an operator.
So I just find operating
is the best job on the floor.
And, you know, if you got your eye
on the viewfinder you know you've got it.
Now we have video assist
and therefore, it's less necessary
but I still love the process of operating.
You can invent while you're doing it.
And I was always told in the early days
"Actors don't like it if you operate."
Well, this is not true, I've discovered.
In fact, there seems to be
a stronger camaraderie
and a closer contact
because they feel that you're
really, really watching them.
And the connection is very strong
when you're operating.
Again, a great cut from
this deafening roar,
which on six-track Dolby is deafening,
to almost an ear-popping,
air-conditioned silence.
When you're looking...
When you come into the cockpit
and she's...
And Veronica is reflectively looking out
at this unfriendly planet,
it's almost as if she knows something.
You feel that she is sensing
that this is not gonna be a good trip.
I love Tom Skerritt's laid-back quality.
When he could play this as a noisy,
you know, aggressive, macho pilot.
But in fact, he's...
He's actually almost like Chuck Yeager.
(chuckles)
Very interesting alphanumerics,
gobbledygook
we put on a green and yellow screen
rather than black.
And all this stuff here, where they...
You've gotta have LAN Holm
as the geologist
speculating on the mysterious
chemistry of the planet.
Great stuff. Great acting.
There's a little shot
where we see the scale of the nose
and we see her walk across
in the window.
The first sign here
that Ian isn't necessarily
what you think he is.
Is he arthritic, or is it something else?
Or is it years in space have got
to his joints?
So that was a little...
That was a little suggestion by him
which I thought was great.
I said "What a great idea."
So there you have an actor really thinking
through the whole idea
and getting in to the notion
of the realities
of science fact and not science fiction.
I love this cockpit.
Somehow it's very fascist.
This shot here, actually, is three children
made in miniature spacesuits that we--
Who were my two sons
and the cameraman's son.
I had small costumes made for them
so the landing legs look bigger.
So if that was an adult,
those legs would look half the size.
But they're children, overcramped.
This was shot direct link down below
and a camera up on the monitor.
And I'm blowing vermiculite
through the air, which hurt like hell.
So I had to wear goggles
and breathing mask
because vermiculite is basically
chipped up teeny bits of plastic.
The idea of making the hero a heroine,
I think, was a master stroke
because we truly expect Sigourney
probably to be the first one to go.
And of course, the story is different.
We had a whole armory of CO2
because, of course, any scientist
would look at this and say:
"What the hell
have they got CO2 there for?"
But I just liked it.
So here we use CO2 for the first time.
And he switches it off.
Just a great dramatic end to the scene.
Sigourney was great
because she has such
with fresh meat
which was the lacework you see
there, called Nottingham lace
which is basically the skin
from the stomach of a cow
which when they pull it off
in the slaughterhouse
you have this beautiful
filigree of lace
which is lining the stomach.
So we laid that over the top.
And then the thing that snaps up
and hits him in the face
is an intestine of a sheep
which has all been steamed clean
and immaculate.
Just put an air line on it, it just went:
I used to have rubber gloves on,
a white coat
and I had to dress it for every shot.
I felt like a surgeon.
And then the air line went on and, bang,
and it, you know, works.
I guess if you spend
a lot of time together in space
the camaraderie
will gradually disappear
and each person will become isolated
with their own thoughts
and their own memories
of where they've been
and where they're going to.
And therefore,
all of the characters are designed
as not really being comrades.
There's a kind of cold relationship
amongst all of them.
And an interesting point
is that at the end of the film
Sigourney does
the extraordinary thing
of going back for a cat.
Well, maybe her only real relationship
on the spaceship is the cat.
So Sigourney, here, you see an officer
wanting to go by the book
even countermanding
the wishes of her captain.
So she's now taking over
and she's being right to do so.
If only they'd just stayed with it,
there would've been no problem.
This always spooked
the audience totally.
The very simple thing that
the tail of the facehugger
tightens on the man's neck.
That's my favorite reaction in the movie.
(laughs)
"My God." And there it is.
Now, that's just a rubber tail
with a bit of liner, we just pulled it tight.
This particular set here
where Ron Cobb had done a lot of
visuals of the interior of the Nostromo
and I would say, this is one
of the most realistic and beautifuI
pieces of technology I've seen,
you know.
Well, you know, I think the best
technology ever presented probably
was in 2001, Stanley Kubrick.
And so it was very difficult
because Stanley had done that
and it was and still is
one of my favorite films.
If I had to say, what are your 20 favorite
films, that would have to be in there.
And therefore, it was tricky not to get
influenced by what he had done
and, of course, what he had done,
I think A, had worked closely
with finding out what NASA
speculative designs were or would be.
So when you think about 2001
and you look at what's happening
today, he's still ahead of the game.
And so we have to avoid that at all cost
but inevitably, it's fair to say
I was very much influenced by 2001.
Boy, that's effective.
I forgot how effective that was.
Now that's just polystyrene
on a fairly potent acid
and it sure goes through there fast,
but it looks like...
I thought it was a great,
subtle way of saying
that this thing is indestructible
and has gone through metal.
Burnt through a boot.
It's interesting to note here
that the full realization
that there might be trouble here
is that you get a sense
that they are beginning to work
together for the first time
rather than being aggressive
with each other
and unreceptive.
Bit of Irving the Explainer.
(Dallas) Here's your pen back.
(Scott) Nice humorous moment.
(laughs)
And, of course, Harry's up next.
Here we are in the engine room.
I liked a lot of the Sizzle Rocks,
which I used for lightning.
So it's introducing a lot of familiar stuff
but in unfamiliar surroundings,
like the CO2.
The technology of the spacecraft
doesn't stand too close scrutiny. Heh.
I made this hand-held because
of the slight movement
which again, you're wanting
to make an audience uneasy.
They know it's in there somewhere
and they don't know what to expect.
Because even when a film comes out
and people get the heat from the movie
and they wanna see it,
they still don't know
where it's gonna happen,
so this could be the scene.
It scares the hell out of them.
But I think we now had
enough tension going.
I was trying to work out a shock
on that day and we couldn't, so...
That's a cheap shock.
(laughs)
But it worked.
And I always felt this was a bit artificial
that nothing really happened
and yet on reflection, actually,
it was good
because there was worse to come.
It's worth mentioning the soundman
on this, Jimmy Shields.
You'll notice that light even has a sound,
right?
So if you listen to the track
you'll hear all these kinds of weird
and wonderful, very subtle sounds.
In fact, I did,
I think four, five films with Jimmy.
He's still going strong.
That's the corner you expect
and then it drops.
That's-- That's as good
as we could do on the day.
And all we could do
is have the propman drop it.
So you're convinced that something's
gonna happen to LAN here.
Of course it's not.
Good shot.
Now, the interior of this thing,
we made a rubber case
and the inside of it there
is all shellfish.
They are, on the surface there,
they are oysters, clams.
So there's oysters and clams, all fresh.
Hence, yeah, every morning
we'd have a bucket of oysters and clams.
I'd just put them in with tweezers
and just dress it.
(chuckles)
But it kind of looks real, but is real.
I like the three heads in this.
I like Dallas' stare.
Absolutely staring in silence at it.
And we hit the breakfast scene before
they're gonna go back into hypersleep.
In fact, they'd probably be eating food
in special preparation.
So that once they're in the hypersleep,
they would,
to be graphic, secrete or lose the food
to become a liquid form.
This is a good scene
to hear Jimmy Shields' sound effects.
You can hear a hum
which rises and falls,
which is always there.
Something is always there,
which makes you uneasy.
Because the sounds were almost organic.
Jimmy used a lot of organic sounds.
Okay, here's the famous scene.
I think most of that food in there
was muesli.
A little look from Ian there
as the kind of doctor on the board.
He's still watching him closely because
obviously he doesn't believe it's gone away.
Dirty joke from Yaphet.
(laughs)
Here it goes.
Well, I didn't ever show them what
would come out. They never saw that.
And we did all this in one take.
But with five or was it four cameras?
With all the air lines prepared.
So once he's on the table,
it's all preset to go.
So all this is kind of one camera.
And he starts to thrash.
It's all hand-held. And then you go to...
He starts to spasm.
Boom. That's an air line inside his chest,
inside his vest.
Now he's going into a spasm frenzy.
Wow, that's pretty good.
(laughing)
That's pretty heavy.
Listen to the sounds.
It's a baby.
It's a boy.
And I had to have a little railway track
across the table to get rid of it.
for such eventualities.
And therefore they're having to use
and adapt materials
and lash up weapons
including flamethrowers
to hunt and protect this thing.
Of course, at this moment
they think it's tiny.
But with this exotic biomechanoid,
he's growing as they speak.
(Ash) Micro changes in air density.
(Scott) Good answer.
(chuckles)
Dallas is always very cool.
Yaphet, who's always great,
is the troublemaker onboard the ship.
And the day that Yaphet had to die,
he said "I'm not gonna die."
The cat was the only witness.
I think Veronica
starts to evoke a more fragile
human spirit who's now terrified.
And she's got the first sense
of the reality of the situation
that they're really in trouble.
So this is suggesting
they saw something.
It was better not to see it.
And Ash saying "Kane's son"
is very interesting.
Because the whole notion of this,
you know,
was taken off a certain type of insect
that will find a host for its eggs.
And then in that host,
which could be another insect,
a grub, preferably,
it will bury its eggs and then, of course,
the eggs will grow and consume the host.
So that's the logic of it all.
So then we get repetition
of the same set.
So there we get a sense
of a whole complex.
Of course, this is where
the sound mix is great
because you give a sense
of the cavernous
interiors of all these tubes.
A lot of reverb on Dallas' voice.
Again, we keep shooting
the same ladder and the same tube.
It's an exercise in using the same set
many times.
The first time I see Dallas
bothered in the film.
This is where he starts to feel
that he's in trouble.
There you get a panicked reaction.
It's an interesting scene here,
because somehow
Tom really makes the audience
feel put in the same situation.
And we know he's gonna die.
Now it's inevitable.
And you get a sense of his feeling
of panic as well, which is wonderful.
And Ash waits for the inevitable.
Oddly enough, that was a sequence
that we weren't really prepared for
because we didn't really have
what I thought was enough of a set.
But again,
when you're forced to be inventive...
Yeah, you know, the best comes out of it.
It works very well.
We had a scene in between this
which was a scene
between Sigourney comforting
a terrorized Veronica,
who was really the first member
of the crew
to begin to lose it.
And also, it's a very important scene
because this is where Sigourney
now is in charge.
She's next in command.
She's taken over from Dallas.
And also, it's a proving scene
for Sigourney
because you have Ash,
you have Yaphet Kotto,
who are obviously wondering
whether they can trust her judgment.
I remember shooting this
and I remember talking to Yaphet
and saying to Yaphet,
which is a little unfair,
to wind up Sigourney.
And keep interrupting her.
And it was really great because
she established her authority.
(laughs)
So I think you have a very good
takeover here by Sigourney.
I filled the Nostromo with all these toys
from the various gift shops
around the universe
wherever they'd stopped off.
And that's what these little toys were.
I always figure that wherever you go,
there will be gift shops.
So that's where...
That's how the Hawaiian shirt appeared.
That's how the dipping bird appeared.
That's the toys.
I guess this is the closest thing
to seeing a robot have sex.
I need to have some show of strength,
which was simple, but violent.
And I think here comes
one of the really great ideas in the film
which is having this character onboard
that you had no idea what he was.
And here, it's to be revealed.
And it also makes sense.
If you have interests,
financial interest like this,
you gotta have something onboard
to make sure that you are protected.
So he's like a walking transmitter.
You hear the death of Ash
and the winding down the...
Whatever is driving him.
It's Jimmy Shields' great sounds.
A lot with this stuff
we had to make up on the day, virtually.
So we couldn't work out how to kill Ash.
Great voice.
Yeah, we worked on that forever,
trying to find out what would
the voice be of this dying robot.
It almost has a Doppler effect.
Spooky.
This was a speech about--
A really doomy speech
about the indestructibility of it
and the perfection of what they had,
what they were against.
And this was a scene
that was written during photography.
We were never happy
about the dialogue that we had.
And I think David had to work on this
incessantly
as we were headed
towards the actual day.
I think we came up with the words
that morning. Or David did.
(Ash) I admire its purity.
A survivor,
unclouded
(Scott) "Unclouded."
(Ash) by conscience, remorse,
or delusions of morality.
(Scott) Kind of a great speech.
(Ash)
I can't lie to you about your chances, but...
(Scott) Mm. Great. That's a pretty tough
piece of information at that point.
(laughs)
So now we're in a really,
I think, terrifying situation.
Because big, tough Yaphet
had suddenly got these two women
as part of his defense group.
So, boy, he must have been feeling
really vulnerable.
There's so much you do
which you keep simple
you know, the head on the table,
you could have gone crazy
with all kinds of stuff underneath it.
I think most of the audience were
convinced that the cat had an alien,
the next alien inside it.
There's even low-key light levels,
it's very tricky.
Because we're pretty well wide open
on spherical.
Oh, I'm sorry. Anamorphic.
And it's sort of
a little bit of out of focus there.
It just shows how few takes I was doing.
At this point,
I was running against the gun.
Great keynote.
You got a great cue coming in.
And, of course, here
I wanted to promote the idea
that Sigourney was next.
Which is a pretty obvious thing
to be doing at this point.
You wanna put her in direct jeopardy.
And I was always concerned
about would the audience think:
"Why the hell is she going back
for the cat?"
But nobody seemed to question it.
Shows we've got a bunch
of animal lovers out there.
She touched the seat button.
That's what made the seat fly forward.
A cheap thrill.
But that's what this kind of genre needs
is you've gotta keep coming up
with original ways of keeping,
sustaining the tension.
And that cat...
That cry of the cat,
again, was laid in deliberately
to promote the idea that
"Was the cat impregnated?"
I wanted the alien to have a certain
kind of fascination and delicacy,
like this massive toy coming towards her,
which was mesmerizing.
And I put this music up for her,
which seemed to help her.
So, in fact, when I got into the Nostromo
and into the shuttle also at the end,
I lined the side of the set
with 15-inch speakers
and I played Tomita
in the shuttle, absolutely full bore.
So rather than a silent set
and me shouting "Action!"
and Sigourney rushing around
in silence,
I said "Do you want some assistance?"
She said "Yeah."
I said "Listen to this." Bumm.
And I had The Planets by Tomita.
And she liked that.
Because then it helped her...
It just helped her to have
that massive orchestration around
and it was--
We had it right up. Yeah.
And, of course,
making Sigourney a very lonely figure.
She can hear the death
rather than see the death
of the other two.
Her death is heard.
And it's probably more frightening
by hearing it rather than seeing it.
That was a tough session
in the looping stage
trying to get that kind of scream.
I think what we managed to do
in the film here
is always put the audience in the place
of the individual about to die.
So I think we somehow
touched on something
which makes the audience very
vulnerable to what's occurring
which, I think,
is why it's particularly frightening.
So the invention
of how do you blow up a refinery
is, you know, tricky
and should be complex.
But, also, it's enormously frustrating.
It almost meant at this point
to be kind of almost humorous.
Here you are trying to read
an instruction book
at the time when you're
about to meet your maker.
And there's one of the fuses
that I've got in the office
which Nicky gave to me
at the end of the movie.
I've got this column.
Nothing could be done by mistake here.
This has gotta be very deliberate.
So in a way, it's like a one-sided,
one-man way
of being able to set off
an atomic bomb.
There she hits the corridor.
Now she's gonna come back
and switch off the power.
But she's passed the point of no return.
This is one of our big miniatures,
the engine room.
When you get this played full bore,
it's pretty intense actually.
And interesting to see that, I think
it's the last 17 minutes of the film,
there is no dialogue except for
utterances of Sigourney to herself.
Now you've got the emergency thing
really kicking in.
You get this going six-track Dolby,
big sound,
it's a great mix.
And now she's gotta go all the way back.
And they always wanted to cut this down.
And I said no.
You know, you've gotta show...
That flapping door there,
there was actually a guy standing there
trying to hide the light.
And they wanted to cut it out.
I said "No, leave it in."
There's actually a guy there.
In fact, it's kind of silly
because with an explosion like that
there would be nothing left.
But why it explodes three times,
it's just better.
Three's always better.
There you go. I knew there was three.
And a firestorm.
A bit dodgy, but kind of good.
Considering it's just artwork.
That was, I think, actually,
that was a little bit of slit-scan.
Great cue.
Here's the cue.
Now you know you're in trouble.
(Ripley) I got you...
(Scott) "Got you, you son of a bitch."
(Ripley) ..you son of a bitch.
(Scott) Now you know you're in trouble.
I think the music now, as dialogue,
is telling you it's not over.
Hit it a little bit. There.
So now we're tense again.
I love that cut to the cat.
This little squeal of the cat.
And you think, you're convinced
it has to be the cat, I think, correct?
Cos don't forget,
we've invested in earlier shots
of the cat wandering off by itself
and then the alien looking down
in the box.
In fact, now, looking at this,
I would almost put the box...
Put the cat in it
before I go into the cockpit.
So then you think,
A, the alien's in the cockpit,
B, what did it do the cat?
Is that satisfaction or is it threat?
I wanted these hypersleeps to be,
eventually, for the end of the film...
I wanted her to be Sleeping Beauty.
Now, when you lose the music,
funnily enough, it gets more tense.
And the actual sound effects gets,
I think, even more scary.
So you wonder what the hell is going on.
They kept saying
"There's no sex in this movie."
I said "Well, you don't need any.
But there's a good opportunity here
to have a little bit of, you know,
hinted-at sexuality."
And Sigourney is certainly the person
to project that.
And, like, in these films,
what's interesting?
And now, I think about it
but then nobody else does.
She just lets...
She just lost six colleagues.
And she's going into mode of
"How do I get out of here?" All right?
"How do I put myself into a position
where I'm gonna reach Earth?
And maybe the network
will pick me up."
And nobody ever raised that question.
I do, but I thought
"Well, if it's not broke..."
You know, "If it's not broken,
don't fix it."
Otherwise, you're gonna have
a serious psychological blitz
as she, you know, collapses mentally
because she's lost six colleagues.
Oddly enough,
there's a sensuality to this whole scene.
Partly the silence.
It's subtly sexual, right?
Or is it just me?
(chuckles)
This is a tough shoot.
Inside a tiny, teeny cupboard.
And it's even tougher. How the hell
do you get the helmet to go on one...?
And Nickie just did it.
We just put the helmet on as it hit,
the lights went on inside the helmet.
And you just make a sound of an airlock
and you got the helmet on.
Economy.
There it is, watch.
Simple.
Beautiful helmets. Now, we used
the same suits as the planet
and all we did was recycle
and spray them white.
Tried to think of something
other than a laser gun
or, you know, of a weapon.
I thought a harpoon.
So they're saying "A harpoon?
What would she use a harpoon for?"
I said "Docking?"
"And like a safety thing
in case something..."
It's like a safety--
Piece of a safety equipment.
So I thought because a harpoon
is more lethal somehow and more...
You know, a gun is too easy.
You know, this is Sigourney's idea.
She kept saying "I wanna sing
'You Are My Lucky Star."'
I'd like to keep myself concentrating.
And not thinking about the worst
that could possibly happen.
So we did it on the day and then there
was this big rush to get the clearance on it.
I love the lighting in here
because it's very harsh in a way,
but beautiful.
And shooting this
with the strobes going,
you're getting a, obviously,
stroboscopic effect on the alien.
So he's kind of jumping.
Because I think in the strobe,
you're losing some frames.
It's an illusion but I think it helped.
I love that as you see him slither out
from the wall.
Once it's humanoid, it's spooky.
They say you don't see enough of the alien,
I think you see plenty of the alien.
And besides, he is humanoid.
Because if the alien
had originally jumped on the cat,
then the alien
would've been a version of the cat.
And so on.
All these things
would've been done now CGI.
But they're tough to do physically,
you know?
This is all physical.
So Roy Scammell was the stuntman
who fell on elastic
and then got pulled back up.
There's the water effect
of the engines going on,
which I thought
was particularly successful.
Particularly there, that's like...
They say "What is that?"
And I say "Well, you know,
it's a plasma engine, of course."
(chuckles)
Then you cut him loose and let him drop.
And he just clipped me, nearly knocked
me out when they dropped him.
And this shot,
oddly enough, was spherical.
We had to do it for a technical reason,
but I left it spherical
so you have a distortion
on the body of the lens.
There, particularly. That's beautiful.
Love these repetitions.
And this is Howard Hanson music.
And one of the reasons
it really works beautifully,
apart from going with the voice,
goes into a hold in a second.
Beautiful.
Here.
I love that holding pattern.
Interesting, after a film like that,
you end it on virtual silence.
The production designer on this
was Michael Seymour,
an old colleague of mine
from television commercials.
And who the...
Who had invited two young art directors
at that particular point to assist him.
Roger Christian assisted him
with the look of and the construction
of the spaceship Nostromo.
And Roger Christian is now a director
and has been for a number of years.
And Les Dilley was in charge
of everything to do with the alien.
And therefore,
he would carry out Giger's drawings.
Remarkable drawings.
And transfer that--
Translate those drawings
into these giant sets
which, in itself, is a task.
There's a big leap
between a drawing and a set.
Where it looks real and looks,
I should say, viscerally real
rather than just like a rendition
of a drawing.
It can easily fall apart
between the art
and the final construction.
Yeah, I mean, it was a...
I think I'd been pretty well used to
a lot of filmmaking at this point
through advertising
and then a film like The Duellists.
So I knew the best.
I knew I needed the best.
Because I'm very demanding
and at the same time,
I think I'm easy to work with.
And the whole thing, you know, when you
put a good bunch of people together,
it becomes all very inspirational.
And I think above all things, if it's not fun,
you shouldn't be doing it, you know.
So I love the process
of filmmaking and
thank God
I'm able to continue making movies.
(chuckles)
[ENGLISH - US - SDH - COMMENTARY