Hello, I'm Mortimer Young of
Forever Young Film Preservation.
First, I want to thank all of
you who sent cards and letters
expressing concern
after our plant explosion
outside of Wilmington,
Delaware, June of last year.
Forever Young Films will no longer employ
non-union labor, I can tell you that.
No casualties, no serious damage
outside of the loss of one
Albanian coming-of-age film,
Smityu Joransik,
or Smityu Finds a Pebble,
destroyed before it could be
transferred to videotape.
We're posting the original script to
our Web site, wwwforeveryoungfilms.net,
in the original Albanian.
Visit us if you can
download Sutterlin text.
That aside, thanks to the
Wilmington Fire Department,
who worked so heroically to save the
entire Ma and Pa Kettle catalog,
and a personal thanks to emergency
room doctor Nate Eisenberg.
I had no idea what prolonged
exposure to plant fumes
had been doing
to my cerebral cortex.
Where was I?
This evening's title,
The Grand Lebowski,
is one of our
greatest success stories.
Probably a title
few of you are familiar with,
it was originally produced
in the late '90s
by obscure PolyGram Films,
and slipped beneath the waves critically
and commercially on its first release.
It then washed hither and yon
in the corporate paroxysms
that shook filmdom during the
catastrophic period of Synergy,
a period which saw Hollywood
awash with money
from Japanese electronic giants,
a large Canadian liquor concern,
and the French sewage processing
conglomerate Vivendi.
Prints of the film had been languishing
in a state of almost criminal neglect.
Here, for instance,
is the hilarious toe scene
from an unrestored
copy of the film.
Now, so far we have what appears to me
to be a series of victimless crimes.
What about the toe?
Forget about the fucking toe!
Forever Young fieldworkers fanned
out in search of undamaged reels.
Our international tip line
yielded a virtually pristine
Italian-language print
from the palazzo
of a Lombard collector.
After our technicians
bathed this print
in our patented
progressive alkalide solution
and then subjected it
to a sonic jiggle bath,
look what emerged.
(SPEAKING IN ITALIAN)
Glorious, isn't it?
Now all that was left to be done
was reassemble the original cast
in the Forever Young studios
to dub the movie
back into English.
Only John Goodman
was unavailable.
His voice was recreated by
master impressionist David Frye.
Now, so far we have what appears to me
to be a series of victimless crimes.
What about the toe?
Forget about the fucking toe!
Wonderful.
"Forget about
the fucking toe!"
By the way, did you know that in Italy
this film was released as Mr. Marijuana
and was quite a success?
Well, we hope you enjoy
The Grand Lebowski,
restored, rejuvenated
and still smoking.
Until we see you again, this
is Mortimer Young. Good night.