(BIG CITY PLAYING)
(MAN SINGING)
And keep your retirement
And your so-called social security
Big city, turn me loose
and set me free...
I'm Jerry Lundegaard.
You're Jerry Lundegaard?
Yeah.
Shep Proudfoot said...
CARL: Shep said you'd be here at 7:30.
What gives, man?
Shep said 8:30.
We've been sitting here an hour.
He's peed three times already.
I'm sure sorry.
Shep told me 8:30.
It was a mix-up, I guess.
You got the car?
Yeah. You bet.
It's out in the lot there,
brand-new, burnt umber Cierra.
Yeah, okay.
Well, sit down, then.
I'm Carl Showalter.
This is my associate, Gaear Grimsrud.
Yeah. How you doing?
So, we all set on this thing, then?
Sure, Jerry. We're all set.
Why wouldn't we be?
Yeah, no, I'm sure you are.
Shep vouched for you and all.
I got every confidence
here in you fellas.
I guess that's it, then.
Here are the keys.
CARL: No, that's not it, Jerry.
Huh?
The new vehicle plus $40,000.
Yeah, but the deal was the car first,
then the 40,000,
like as if it was the ransom.
I thought Shep told you.
Shep didn't tell us much, Jerry.
Well, okay...
Except that you were
gonna be here at 7:30.
Yeah, well, that was a mix-up, then.
Yeah, you already said that.
Yeah, but it's not a
whole pay-in-advance deal.
See, I give you a brand-new
vehicle in advance, and then...
I'm not gonna debate you, Jerry.
Okay.
I'm not gonna sit here and debate.
I will say this, though.
What Shep told us didn't
make a whole lot of sense.
Oh, no. It's real sound.
It's all worked out.
You want your own wife kidnapped.
Yeah.
You...
My point is,
you pay the ransom,
what, 80,000 bucks?
I mean, you give us half the
ransom, 40,000, you keep half.
It's like robbing Peter to pay Paul.
It doesn't make any sense.
Okay, see,
it's not me paying the ransom.
The thing is,
my wife, she's wealthy.
Her dad, he's real well-off.
Now, I'm in a bit of trouble.
CARL: What kind of
trouble you in, Jerry?
(STAMMERING) Well, that's...
I'm not gonna get into...
See, I just need the money.
Now, her dad, he's real well-off.
So, why don't you just
ask him for the money?
Or your fucking wife, you know?
Or your fucking wife, Jerry?
Well...
It's all part of this...
They don't know I need it, see?
Okay, so there's that.
And even if they did, I wouldn't get it,
so there's that on top, then.
See, these are personal matters.
Personal matters?
Yeah, personal matters
that needn't...
Okay, Jerry.
You're tasking us to perform
this mission, but you won't...
You won't...
Fuck it.
Let's take a look at that Cierra.
Hon?
Hi, hon!
Welcome back!
How was Fargo?
Yeah, real good.
Dad's here.
(CHATTERING ON TV)
MAN ON TV: ...leads the Badgers in
goal production with five this year.
How you doing, Wade?
Yeah, pretty good.
What you watching there?
Gophers.
Who they playing?
Ooh!
(GROANS)
(CROWD CHEERING)
Is he staying for supper, then?
Yeah. I think so.
- Dad?
- WADE: What?
Are you staying for supper?
WADE: Yeah.
May I be excused?
You done there?
Uh-huh.
I'm going out.
- Where are you going?
- Just out.
Just McDonald's.
- Back at 9:30.
- Okay.
He just ate.
He didn't finish.
Going to McDonald's
instead of finishing here.
He sees his friends there.
It's okay.
It's okay, McDonald's?
What do you think they do there?
They don't drink milk
shakes, I assure you.
It's okay, Dad.
Wade, have you had
a chance to think about
that deal I was talking about,
those 40 acres there, in Wayzata?
You told me about it.
Yeah, you said you'd
have to think about it.
I understand.
It's a lot of money.
It's a heck of a lot. What did you
say you were gonna put there?
A lot. It's a...
I know it's a lot.
I mean a parking lot.
Well, 750,000 is a lot.
Yeah, well, it's a chunk, but...
I had a couple lots, late 50s.
Lost a lot of money.
- A lot of money.
- Yeah, but the difference...
I thought you were gonna
show it to Stan Grossman.
He passes on this stuff before
it gets kicked up to me.
Well, Stan'll say, "No dice."
That's why you pay him.
I'm asking you here, Wade.
This could work out real good
for me and Jean and Scotty.
Jean and Scotty never have to worry.
Where is Pancakes House?
What?
We stop at Pancakes House.
What are you, nuts?
We had pancakes for breakfast.
Gotta go to a place
where I can get a shot
and a beer and a steak, maybe.
Not more fucking pancakes.
Come on.
Oh, come on, man.
Okay. Here's an idea.
We can stop outside of Brainerd.
I know a place there where we can get laid.
What do you think?
I'm fucking hungry now, you know.
Yeah, yeah, Jesus.
I'm saying we can stop, get pancakes,
and then we'll get laid, all right?
WOMAN ON PA: Lou Diamond, line one.
MAN: We sat right here in this room
and went over this and over this.
Yeah, but that TruCoat...
I sat right here and said I
didn't want any TruCoat.
Yeah, but I'm saying that TruCoat.
You don't get it,
you get oxidation problems.
It'll cost you a heck of
a lot more than $500.
You're sitting there.
You're talking in circles.
You're talking like we
didn't go over this already.
Yeah, but this TruCoat...
We had a deal here for 19,500.
You sat there and darned
if you didn't tell me
you'd get me this car,
these options,
without the sealant, for 19,500.
All right, I'm not saying I didn't.
You called me
20 minutes ago and said
you had it ready to make delivery.
You says, "Come on down and get it."
And here you are, and you're
wasting my time and my wife's time,
and I'm paying 19,500
for this vehicle here.
All right.
I'll talk to my boss.
See, they install that
TruCoat at the factory.
There's nothing we can do,
but I'll talk to my boss.
These guys here.
These guys.
It's always the same.
It's always more.
(CHATTERING ON TV)
You going to the Gophers on Sunday?
Oh, you betcha.
You wouldn't have an extra ticket?
You kidding?
Well,
he never done this before,
but seeing as it's special
circumstances and all,
he says I can knock
$100 off that TruCoat.
100?
You lied to me, Mr. Lundegaard.
You're a bald-faced liar.
WOMAN: Bucky, please.
A fucking liar.
Bucky, please.
Where's my goddamn checkbook?
Let's get this over with.
Where is it?
(WOMEN MOANING)
(THE TONIGHT SHOW THEME PLAYING)
ED MCMAHON: From Hollywood,
The Tonight Show, starring...
I am talking about your potential.
Mmm-hmm.
You're not a C student.
Yeah.
Yet you're getting C grades.
It's that disparity there that
concerns your dad and me.
Uh-huh.
You know what a disparity is?
Yeah!
Okay! Well, that's why we...
We don't want you
going out for hockey.
Oh, man!
Come on. What's the big deal?
It's just an hour...
(PHONE RINGING)
Hold on.
SCOTTY: What's the big deal?
Hello?
- WADE: Yeah, hiya, hon.
- Oh, hi, Dad.
Is Jerry around?
Yeah. Hon!
Yeah, he's here.
Yeah, I'll catch him for you.
- Hon!
- JERRY: Yeah?
- It's Dad.
- Okay.
Look, Dad, there's no fucking way...
Scotty!
Hey, let's watch
that language there.
How you doing there, Wade?
What's going on there?
Nothing, Wade.
How you doing there?
Stan Grossman
looked at your proposal.
He says it's pretty sweet.
No kidding?
Might be interested.
No kidding? I'd need the
cash pretty quick there,
in order to close the deal.
Come by at 2:30.
We'll talk about it.
If your numbers are right,
Stan says it's pretty sweet.
- Stan, you know, Grossman.
- Yeah.
2:30.
Yeah. Okay.
(ROCK MUSIC PLAYING ON RADIO)
Say, Shep, how you doing there?
Say, you know those two fellas
you put me in touch
with up there in Fargo?
I put you in touch with Grimsrud.
Yeah, well, he had a buddy there.
- He...
- Then I don't vouch for him.
Well, that's okay.
I vouch for Grimsrud.
Who's his buddy?
Carl something.
Never heard of him.
Don't vouch for him.
Well, that's okay. He's a buddy
of the guy you vouched for,
so I'm not worried.
I just...
I was wondering, see, I got
to get in touch with him.
See, this deal I needed him
for, I may not need it anymore.
- Something's happening, see.
- Call him up.
Yeah, well, see, I did that, and
I haven't been able to get him,
so I thought maybe you'd know an
alternate number, or what have you.
Nope.
Okay. Well...
Real good, then.
(ROCK MUSIC PLAYING ON CAR RADIO)
(GRIMSRUD COUGHS)
Can you crack a fucking
window open, man?
You know, it's proven
that secondhand smoke is...
You know, a cancer agent.
Hey, look at that.
Twin Cities.
That's the IDS Building,
the big glass one.
Tallest skyscraper in the Midwest
after the Sears in Chicago,
or John Hancock building, whatever.
You ever been to Minneapolis?
No.
Would it kill you to say something?
I did.
"No." That's the first thing you've
said in the last four hours.
That's a...
That's a fountain
of conversation, man.
That's a geyser.
I mean, whoa, daddy.
Stand back, man.
Shit.
I'm sitting here driving.
I'm doing all the driving, man,
whole fucking way
from Brainerd, driving.
Just trying to chat.
You know, keep our spirits up,
fight the boredom of the road,
and you can't say one fucking thing
just in the way of conversation?
Oh, fuck it. I don't
have to talk either, man.
See how you like it.
Just total fucking silence.
Two could play at
that game, smart guy.
We'll just see how you like it.
Total silence.
Mr. Lundegaard, this is
Reilly Diefenbach from GMAC.
How are you this morning?
Real good.
How you doing?
Pretty good, Mr. Lundegaard.
You're damn hard
to get on the phone.
It's pretty darn busy here,
but that's the way we like it.
Well, that's for sure.
Now, I just need on these last,
these financing documents
that you sent us,
I can't read the serial
numbers of the vehicles.
Yeah, but I already got the...
It's okay.
The loans are in place.
I already got the...
What? The...
Yeah, the 320,000.
You got the money last month.
Yeah, so we're all set, then.
Yeah, but the vehicles
that you're borrowing on,
I just can't read the serial
numbers on your application.
Maybe if you could just read...
Yeah, but the deal's already done.
I already got the money.
Yes, but if we have an audit here,
I just have to know
that these vehicles
you're financing with this money,
that they really exist.
Yeah, well, they exist, all right.
(CHUCKLING)
I'm sure they do,
but I can't read the serial numbers
here, so if you could read me...
Yeah, but... See...
I don't have them in front of me.
Why don't I just
fax you over a copy?
No, well, no, fax is no good.
That's what I have,
and I can't read the darn thing.
Yeah, okay. I'll have my girl
send you a copy, then.
Okay, because if I can't correlate
this note with the specific vehicles,
then I got to call back that money.
Yeah, how much money was that?
320,000.
I got to correlate that money
with the cars it's being lent on.
Yeah. Okay, no problem.
I'll just fax that right over.
No, no, no. Fax...
I mean, send it over.
I'll shoot it right over to you, then.
Okay, okay. Fine.
Okay. Real good, then.
- We're back with Katie Carlson.
- Hi.
Now, before we get going here,
we just want to remind all
of our viewers at home
that this March, for the
second year in a row,
Katie and I, along
with Twin City Travel,
will be leading a two-week
riverboat trip down the Nile.
It's a terrific time.
I know you've heard about it.
We want all of you to come with,
and that's the truth.
(BOTH LAUGHING)
Okay, now, for those of
you that just joined us,
Katie here, this morning,
is going to show us
how to make Holidazzle
eggs ourselves, at home.
- Now, Katie, I gotta admit...
- What?
I was a little bit surprised
when I first picked this up.
Right.
This is an empty egg.
(LAUGHS)
That's right, Dale.
Well, how do you get the egg...
- There was an egg in here, right?
- Yeah.
Okay, well, I don't... How do you...
I mean, you don't have
an empty chicken somewhere
that lays empty eggs?
No, no.
I guarantee, this was
an honest-to-goodness...
(SCREAMS)
(SCREAMING)
(GRUNTING)
Unguent.
What?
I need unguent.
No.
(WHIMPERING)
(CRYING) No...
(POUNDING ON DOOR)
(CARL GROANING)
CARL: You want to do it?
GRIMSRUD: Push.
(WATER DRIPPING)
(JEAN SCREAMING)
How are you, Stan?
How you doing, Wade?
Good to see you again, Jerry.
If these numbers are right,
this looks pretty sweet.
Those numbers are right, all right.
Believe me.
WADE: This is doable.
Congratulations, Jer.
Yeah, thanks, Stan.
Well, it's a pretty...
What kind of finder's fee
were you looking for?
Huh?
The financials are pretty thorough,
so the only thing
we don't know is your fee.
My fee?
Wade, what the heck
are you talking about?
WADE: Stan and I are okay.
- Yeah.
- We're good to load in.
Yeah.
But we never talked about your
fee for bringing it to us.
No, but, Wade, see,
I was bringing you this deal
for you to loan me
the money to put in.
It's my deal here, see.
Jerry, we thought you were
bringing us an investment.
Yeah. Right.
You're saying...
What are you saying?
You're saying
we put in all the money,
and you collect when it pays off.
(BOTH CHUCKLING)
(STUTTERING)
No, no. See... But I'd...
I'd pay you back the
principal and interest.
Heck, I'd go one over prime?
We're not a bank, Jerry.
If I wanted bank
interest on 750,000,
I'd go to Midwest Federal,
talk to old Bill Diehl.
- He's at North Star.
- He's at...
No, no. See, I...
I don't need a finder's fee.
I need...
Finder's fee is, what, 10%?
Heck, that's not gonna do it for me.
I need the principal.
Well, Jerry, we're not gonna
just give you $750,000.
What the heck were you thinking?
If I'm only getting bank interest,
I want complete security.
Heck, FDIC.
I don't see nothing like that here.
Yeah, but I...
Okay. I...
I guarantee you your money back.
I'm not talking about
your damn word, Jerry.
Jeez!
What the heck are you...
We're not a bank, Jerry.
Well, look. I don't want
to cut you out of the loop,
but this here's a good deal.
I assume, if you're not interested,
you won't mind if we
move on it independently.
(CAR DOOR BEEPING)
Damn it!
(GRUNTS)
Hon?
I got the groceries!
Yeah, Wade, hi.
It's Jerry. I...
Wade, it's Jerry.
I don't know what to do. It's Jean.
I don't know what to do.
It's my wife.
It's Jean.
Yeah, Wade, I...
It's Jerry. I...
Wade, it's Jerry.
I... We gotta talk.
It's something...
Jeez. It's terrible.
Yeah, Wade Gustafson, please.
(JEAN WHIMPERING)
Shut the fuck up,
or I'll throw you back
into the trunk, you know.
Jesus, that's more than
I've heard you say all week.
(SIREN BLARING)
Shit.
Oh, the tags.
All right, it's just the tags.
I never put my tags on the car.
All right, don't worry.
I'll take care of this.
(JEAN WHIMPERING SOFTLY)
All right, just keep it
still back there, lady,
or else we're gonna have to,
you know, to shoot you.
Hey, I'll take care of this.
How can I help you, Officer?
This is a new car, then, sir?
It certainly is, Officer.
Still got that smell.
You're required to
display temporary tags,
either in the plate area or taped
to the inside of the back window.
Certainly.
Can I see your license
and registration, please?
Certainly.
Yeah, I was gonna tape up those...
The tag.
You know, to be in full
compliance, but it must have...
It must have slipped my mind.
So maybe the best
thing to do would be
to take care of that
right here in Brainerd.
What's this, sir?
My license and registration.
Yeah, I want to be in compliance.
I was just thinking we could
take care of it right here,
in Brainerd.
Put that back in
your pocket, please,
and step out of the
car, please, sir.
(JEAN WHIMPERING)
(GROANS)
(JEAN WHIMPERING LOUDLY)
Shut the fuck up.
Whoa.
Whoa, daddy.
You'll take care of it.
You are smooth, smooth, you know?
Oh, daddy.
Just clear him off the road.
Yeah.
(GRUNTING)
(TIRES SQUEALING)
(WHIMPERING)
(TIRES SCREECHING)
JEAN: No!
(GROANS)
(CAR DOOR BEEPING)
(SNORING)
(PHONE RINGING)
Oh, jeez.
Hi. It's Marge.
(MAN CHATTERING)
Oh, my. Where?
Yeah?
Oh, jeez.
Okay. There in a jiff.
Real good, then.
(NORM MOANING)
You can sleep.
It's early yet.
Got to go?
Yeah.
I'll fix you some eggs.
It's okay, hon.
I gotta run.
You got to eat a breakfast, Marge.
I'll fix you some eggs.
Hon, you can sleep.
You gotta eat a breakfast.
(CLEARING THROAT)
I'll fix you some eggs.
Norm.
Thanks, hon.
Time to shove off.
Love you, Margie.
Love you, hon.
Hon?
Yeah?
Prowler needs a jump.
(DISPATCHER CHATTERING ON RADIO)
Hiya, Lou.
(WHOOPS)
What you got there?
Margie, thought you might
need a little warm-up.
Thanks a bunch.
So what's the deal now?
Gary says triple homicide?
Yeah, looks pretty bad.
Two of them are over here.
Where is everybody?
Well, it's cold, Margie.
Watch your step, Margie.
Jeez. So...
(EXCLAIMS) Jeez!
Here's the second one!
It's in the head and the hand there.
I guess that's a defensive wound.
Oh, yeah?
Where's the state trooper?
Back there a good piece,
in the ditch next to his prowler.
Okay.
So we got a trooper
pulls someone over.
We got a shooting.
These folks drive by.
There's a high-speed pursuit, ends here,
and then this execution-type deal.
Yeah.
I'd be very surprised if our
suspect was from Brainerd.
Yeah.
And I'll tell you what.
From his footprint,
he looks like a big fella.
You see something down there, Chief?
No. I just think I'm gonna barf.
Jeez.
You okay, Margie?
Yeah. I'm fine.
It's just morning sickness.
Well, that passed.
Yeah?
Yeah. Now I'm hungry again.
You have breakfast yet, Margie?
Oh, yeah.
Norm made some eggs.
Yeah?
Well...
What now, do you think?
Let's go take a look at that trooper.
There's different footprints here, Lou.
LOU: Yeah?
Yeah. This guy's smaller than his buddy.
Oh, yeah?
MARGE: For Pete's sake.
How's it look, Marge?
Well, he's got his
gun on his hip there,
and he looks like a nice enough guy.
It's a real shame.
LOU: Yeah.
Didn't monkey with
his car there, did you?
No way.
Well, somebody shut his lights.
I guess the little guy sat in there
waiting for his buddy to come back.
Yeah, it would have been cold out here.
Heck, yeah.
You think is Dave open yet?
Dave?
You don't think he's mixed up in...
Oh, no, no. I just want to
get Norm some night crawlers.
Did you look in his citation book?
Yeah. Last vehicle he wrote in
was a tan Cierra at 2:18 a.m.
Under plate number he put "DLR."
I figure they stopped him or shot him
before he could finish
filling out the tag number.
So, I got the State looking for a
Cierra with a tag starting "DLR."
They don't got no match yet.
I'm not sure that
I agree with you 100%
on your police work there, Lou.
- Yeah?
- Yeah.
I think that vehicle there
probably had dealer plates.
"DLR."
Oh.
Jeez.
Say, Lou,
did you hear the one about the guy
who couldn't afford personalized plates,
so he went and changed
his name to J3L-2404?
Yeah. That's a good one.
Look, all's I know is, you got a
problem, you call a professional.
No. They said no cops.
They were darn clear on that, Wade.
They said, "You call your cops,
and we're gonna shoot..."
Of course they're gonna say that.
Where's my protection?
They got Jean here.
If I give these sons
of bitches $1 million,
where's my guarantee
they're gonna let her go?
Well, they...
$1 million is a lot of damn money.
- Yeah, but...
- There they are. They got my daughter.
Think this thing through here, Wade.
You give them what they want,
why won't they let her go?
You got to listen to
me on this one, Wade.
Heck, you don't know.
You're just whistling Dixie here.
I'm saying the cops,
they can advise us on this.
I'm saying call a professional.
No. No cops.
That's final.
This is my deal here, Wade.
Yeah.
Jean is my wife here.
I gotta tell you, Wade,
I'm leaning to Jerry's viewpoint here.
Well...
We got to protect Jean. These...
We're not holding
any cards here, Wade.
They got them all.
So they call the shots.
You're darn tooting.
Oh, damn it.
I'm telling you.
Well, why don't we...
Stan, I'm thinking we should
offer them a half a million.
Now, come on here!
No way, Wade.
No way.
We're not horse-trading here, Wade.
Yeah.
We gotta just bite the
bullet on this thing.
Yeah.
So, well, what's the
next step here, Jerry?
They're gonna call me up and
give me instructions for a drop.
I'm supposed to have the
money ready tomorrow.
Damn it!
How was everything today?
Yeah. Real good, now.
How you doing?
Okay.
Now, we'll get the money together.
Don't worry about it, Jerry.
Now, do you want anyone at
home with you till they call?
No, I...
They don't...
They were just supposed
to be dealing with me.
- They were real clear.
- Yeah.
You know,
they said no one listening in.
They'll be watching.
You know, maybe it's all bull,
but like you said, Stan,
they're calling the shots.
Okay.
Now, is Scotty gonna be all right?
Yeah. Jeez. Scotty.
Yeah. I'll go talk to him.
(HORN HONKING)
(KNOCKING AT DOOR)
How you doing there, Scotty?
Dad...
What are they doing?
What do you think
they're doing with Mom?
It's okay, Scotty.
They're not gonna
wanna hurt her any.
These men, they just want money.
Yeah, well, what if
something goes wrong, Dad?
No, no. Nothing's going wrong here.
Granddad and I, we're, we're making
sure this gets handled right.
I really think we should
call the cops here.
No. No. No one can
know about this thing.
We gotta play ball with these guys.
You ask Stan Grossman,
he'll tell you the same thing.
Yeah. But, Dad...
We're gonna get Mom back for
you, but we gotta play ball.
You know?
That's the deal here.
So if Lorraine calls, or Sylvia,
you just say Mom's down in
Florida, with Pearl and Marty.
That's the best we can do here.
No!
(MUFFLED SCREAMING)
(CARL LAUGHING)
No!
Oh, God.
(CRYING)
Lunchtime.
Thanks, Margaret.
Hi. Hey.
Willy. Carol.
Janie, two more of those
Skin So Soft, please.
Sure thing.
Hiya, hon.
NORM: I brought you
some lunch, Margie.
What are those?
Night crawlers?
Yeah.
Oh, thanks, hon.
You bet.
Thanks for lunch.
Yeah.
Looks pretty good.
What do we got here, Arby's?
How's the painting going?
Pretty good.
Found out the Hautmans are
entering a painting this year.
Hon, you're better than them.
They're real good.
They're good, Norm,
but you're better than them.
You think so?
Hey, you got Arby's all over me.
(KNOCK AT DOOR)
Hiya, Norm.
How's the painting going?
NORM: Not too bad.
You know.
How we doing on that vehicle?
Well, no motels registered
any tan Cierra last night,
but the night before,
two men checked into the Blue Ox,
registering a Cierra and
leaving the tag space blank.
Jeez, that's a good lead.
LOU: Yeah.
Blue Ox, that's that truckers'
joint out there on I-35?
Yeah. Owner was on the desk then.
Said these two had company.
Oh, yeah?
Yeah.
GIRL 1: Yeah, we both did.
She went to college, too.
GIRL 2: I went to Normandale
for about a year and a half.
Yeah, that's where we met.
But I dropped out, though.
Yeah.
She dropped.
So where you girls from?
- Chaska.
- Le Sueur.
But I went to high school
in White Bear Lake.
Go Bears.
Okay. I want you to tell me
what these fellows looked like.
Well, the little guy, he
was kind of funny-looking.
In what way?
I don't know.
Just funny-looking.
Can you be any more specific?
I couldn't really say.
He wasn't circumcised.
Was he funny-looking
apart from that?
Yeah.
So, you were having sex
with the little fella, then.
Uh-huh.
Is there anything else
you can tell me about him?
No. Like I say,
he was funny-looking.
More than most people, even.
What about the other fella?
He was a little older.
You know, he looked
like the Marlboro Man.
- Oh, yeah?
- Yeah.
But maybe I'm saying that, you know,
'cause he smoked a lot of Marlboros.
You know, like a
subconscious type of thing.
Oh, yeah, that can happen.
Yeah.
Hey, they said they were
going to the Twin Cities.
- Oh, yeah?
- Yeah!
Yeah, is that useful to you?
You betcha. Yeah.
- Yeah.
CARL: Come on!
(POUNDING)
Goddamn it!
Jesus Christ.
Fucking shitbox.
Been here for days.
Damn it.
Nothing to do.
Fucking TV doesn't even...
Damn it, come on! Plug me in, man.
Give me a fucking signal.
Goddamn it!
Unbelievable! Come on!
God...
Fuck!
Come on, plug me into
the ozone, baby! Come on!
Come on!
Fuck! Fuck!
MAN: The bark beetle
carries the worm to its nest
where it will feed its young
for up to six months.
In the spring, the larvae hatch,
and the cycle begins again.
Well...
I'm turning in, Norm.
Oh, yeah?
Here it is, throwing
off the larval envelope.
(PHONE RINGING)
Hello?
MIKE: Yeah.
Is this Marge?
Yeah.
Margie Olmstead?
Yeah. Who's this?
This is Mike Yanagita!
You know, Mike Yanagita.
Remember me?
Mike Yanagita?
Yeah!
Well, yeah!
Course I remember you.
How are you doing?
What time is it?
Oh, jeez.
It's 10:45.
I hope I didn't wake you.
No. That's okay.
Yeah, I'm down in the Twin Cities,
and I was just watching on TV about
these shootings up in Brainerd.
And I saw you on the news there.
Yeah.
I thought, "Jeez, is
that Margie Olmstead?"
I can't believe it.
Yeah, that's me.
Well, how the heck are you?
Okay. You know.
Okay.
- Yeah?
- Yeah.
How you doing?
Pretty good.
Well, heck.
It's been such a long time, Mike.
It's great to hear from you.
Yeah, you got your...
This is loaded here.
This has your independent...
Your front-wheel drive,
rack-and-pinion steering,
antilock brakes, alarm, radar,
and I can give it to you
with a heck of a sealant.
This TruCoat stuff,
it'll keep the salt off.
Yeah, I don't need
no sealant, though.
Yeah.
You don't need that.
Now, were you thinking
of financing here?
You ought to be aware of this
GMAC plan they have now.
It's really super.
MAN: Got a call for you, Jerry.
Yeah, okay.
(BEEPING)
Jerry Lundegaard.
CARL: All right, Jerry,
you got the phone to yourself?
Well, yeah.
You know who this is?
Well, yeah, I got an idea.
How's that Cierra
working out for you?
Circumstances have changed, Jerry.
Well...
What do you mean?
Things have changed. Circumstances,
Jerry, beyond the acts of God.
Force majeure.
What the...
How's Jean?
Who's Jean?
My wife. What the...
She's all right, but there's
three people up in Brainerd
who aren't so okay,
I'll tell you that.
What the heck are you talking about?
Let's just finish this deal up here.
Blood has been shed, Jerry.
What the heck do you mean?
Three people in Brainerd.
Oh, jeez.
That's right, and we need more money.
What the heck are you talking about?
What do you fellas
got yourself mixed up in?
We need more money...
This was supposed to be
a no-rough-stuff type deal.
Don't ever interrupt me, Jerry!
Just shut the fuck up!
Well, I'm sorry, but I just, I...
I'm not gonna debate you, Jerry.
I'm not gonna debate!
We now want the entire 80,000.
Oh, for Christ's sake here.
Blood has been shed.
We've incurred risk, Jerry.
I'm coming into town tomorrow.
You have the money ready.
Now, we had a deal here.
A deal's a deal.
Is it, Jerry?
You ask those three poor souls up
in Brainerd if a deal's a deal.
Go ahead, ask them!
The heck do you mean?
"The heck do you mean?"
I'll see you tomorrow.
(PHONE BEEPING)
Yeah?
REILLY: Jerome Lundegaard?
Yeah.
This is Reilly Diefenbach at GMAC.
Sir, I've not received those
vehicle IDs you promised.
Yeah. I...
Those are in the mail.
That very well may be.
I must inform you, however,
that absent the receipt of those
numbers by tomorrow afternoon,
I will have to refer this
matter to our legal department.
Yeah.
- My patience is at an end.
- Yeah.
- Good day, sir.
Hi, Norm.
How you doing, Margie?
How's the fricassee?
Pretty darn good.
You want some?
Oh, no. I got...
Hey, Norm, I thought you was going
ice fishing up at Mille Lacs.
Yeah. After lunch.
MARGE: What you got there?
The numbers you asked for.
Calls made from the lobby
pay phone at the Blue Ox.
Two to Minneapolis that night.
First one's a trucking company
and second one's
a private residence,
a Shep Proudfoot.
A what?
Shep Proudfoot.
That's a name.
Yeah.
Okay. Yeah.
Think I'll take a drive
down there, then.
Oh, yeah?
Twin Cities.
(WADE GROANING)
Damn it, I want to be
a part of this thing.
No. Wade, they were real clear.
They said they'd call
tomorrow with instructions,
and it's gotta be
delivered by me alone.
It's my money, I'll deliver it.
What do they care?
Wade's got a point, there.
I'll handle the call
if you want, Jerry.
No, no. See, they...
No. See, they only deal with me.
You feel this nervousness
on the phone there.
They're very... These
guys are dangerous.
All the more reason.
I don't want you...
With all due respect, Jerry,
I don't want you mucking this up.
What the heck do you mean?
They want my money,
they can deal with me.
Otherwise,
I'm going to a professional.
- No, see...
- There's $1 million here.
No. See...
Look, Jerry, you're not
selling me a damn car!
It's my show here.
That's that!
It's the way we'd prefer
to handle it, Jerry.
Hi. How you doing?
Real good. How are you
doing today, ma'am?
I'm doing really
super there. Thanks.
I'm Mrs. Gunderson.
I have a reservation.
Yep. You sure do, Mrs. Gunderson.
Is there a phone
down here, you think?
Detective Sibert?
Yeah, this is Marge Gunderson
from up Brainerd. We spoke.
Yeah. Well, actually,
I'm in town here.
I had to do a few things
in the Twin Cities,
so I thought I'd check in with you
about that USFI search
on Shep Proudfoot.
Oh, yeah?
Well, maybe I'll go visit
with him if I have...
No. I can find that.
Yeah. Well, thanks a bunch.
Say, say, would you happen to know
a good place for lunch
in the downtown area?
The Radisson.
Oh, yeah?
Is it reasonable?
Hi. How you doing?
Yeah. I decided not to park here.
Well, what do you mean?
You decided not to park here?
Yeah, I just came in and I
decided not to park here, so...
But...
Well, I'm sorry, sir...
Yeah, I decided not to... I...
You know, I'm not...
I decided not to take the
trip, as it turns out, so...
Well, I'm sorry, sir,
we still got to charge you the $4.
I just pulled in here.
I just fucking pulled in here.
Well, but...
See, there's a minimum charge of $4.
Long-term parking
charges by the day.
(HORN HONKING)
(SIGHS)
I guess you think you're, you
know, like an authority figure.
That stupid fucking
uniform, huh, buddy?
King clip-on tie there.
Big fucking man, huh?
You know, these are the
limits of your life, man.
Ruler of your
little fucking gate here.
Here. There's your $4,
you pathetic piece of shit.
Where's Shep?
Talking to a cop.
Cop?
Said she was a cop.
MARGE: So do you remember
getting a call Wednesday night?
Nope.
You do reside there
at 1425 Freemont Terrace?
Yep.
Anyone else residing there?
No.
Well, Mr. Proudfoot, this call
came in past 3:00 in the morning.
It's just hard for me to believe
you don't remember anyone calling.
Now, I know you've
had some problems.
Struggling with the narcotics,
some other entanglements,
currently on parole.
So?
Well, associating with criminals,
if you're the one they talked to,
that right there would be
a violation of your parole.
Would end you up back in Stillwater.
Now, I saw some rough
stuff on your priors,
but nothing in the
nature of a homicide.
I know you don't want to be an
accessory to something like that.
So, you think you might remember
who those folks were who called you?
(KNOCK AT DOOR)
Mr. Lundegaard?
Yeah.
Could I take just a
minute of your time here?
What is it all about?
Do you mind if I sit down?
Carrying quite a load here.
You're the owner here,
Mr. Lundegaard?
No. I...
Executive Sales Manager.
Well, you can help me.
My name's Marge Gunderson.
My father-in-law, he's the owner.
Uh-huh.
Well, I'm a police officer
from up Brainerd,
investigating some malfeasance.
And I was just wondering if
you'd had any new vehicles
stolen off the lot
in the past couple of weeks.
Specifically a tan Cutlass Cierra.
Mr. Lundegaard.
Brainerd.
Yeah, yeah.
Home of Paul Bunyan,
Babe, the Blue Ox.
Yeah, you know,
we got that big statue up there.
So, you haven't had any
vehicles go missing, then?
Nope. No, ma'am.
Okey-dokey.
Thanks a bunch.
I'll let you get back
to your paperwork, then.
- MAN: Service.
- Yeah, get me Shep.
He's not here right now.
What the heck do you mean?
He stepped out.
- Where'd he go? It's only...
- I'll get you Artie.
No. I don't need a mechanic.
I need a...
(STUTTERS)
Jeez. I gotta talk
to a friend of his,
(STUTTERS) so...
Have him...
What?
Oh, jeez.
(JAZZ MUSIC PLAYING)
Mike?
Marge?
Jeez! Oh, you look great!
Yeah. So do you.
Easy there. Easy...
Easy there. Easy there.
You do, too.
I'm expecting now.
I see that.
That's great.
What can I get you?
Just a Diet Coke, please.
WAITRESS: Great.
This is a nice place.
Yeah. You know, it's the
Radisson, so it's pretty good.
Yeah.
So...
You're living in Edina, then?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
A couple of years now.
It's actually Eden Prairie.
That school district.
So, Chief Gunderson, then!
So, you went and married
Norm son-of-a-Gunderson.
Oh, yeah.
Long time ago.
Great, great.
So, what brings you down?
Are you down here on that homicide,
if you're allowed, you
know, to discuss that?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
But there's not a heck
of a lot to discuss.
Okay.
Well, what about you, Mike?
Are you married?
You got kids?
Yeah, yeah. Well...
I was married.
I was married to...
You mind if I sit over here?
I was married to Linda Cooksey.
No. Why don't you sit over there?
I prefer that.
Okay.
Sorry.
No, no. Just so I can see you.
Don't have to turn my neck.
Sure, sure. I understand.
I didn't mean to...
No, no. That's fine.
Yeah, sorry. Sorry.
So, I was married to Linda Cooksey.
You remember Linda.
She was a year behind us.
Yeah. I think I remember her.
Yeah! She...
Oh, yeah!
So, it didn't work out, huh?
And then I've been working for
Honeywell for a few years now.
Well, they're a good outfit.
Yeah, if you're an engineer,
yeah, you could do a lot worse.
But it's not...
It's nothing like your achievement.
Well, it sounds like
you're doing really super.
It's not that...
It's not that things
didn't work out. It's...
Linda had leukemia, you know.
She was...
She passed away.
No.
It was tough.
There you go.
It was long...
She fought real hard, Marge.
You know...
So, what can you say?
Better times, huh?
Better times.
And then I saw you on the TV
and I remembered, you know?
I always liked you.
Well, I always liked you...
I always liked you so much.
So, Mike, should we get together
another time, you think?
No! I...
I'm sorry. It's...
You know,
I shouldn't have done this.
I shouldn't.
I thought we'd have
a really terrific time.
It's okay, Mike.
You were such a super lady.
And then...
I've been so lonely.
(SOFTLY)
It's okay, Mike.
(AUDIENCE APPLAUDING)
JOSE: Here's a song I dedicate to
all the ladies out here tonight.
Goes like this.
(SINGING)
Let's find each other tonight
Everything will be all right
Don't hesitate now
Let's find each other tonight
So...
Are you from around here?
Just in town on business.
Just in and out.
Just a little of the old in-and-out.
What do you do?
I...
You been to the
Celebrity Room before?
With other clients?
I don't think so.
It's nice.
Yeah, well, depends on the artist.
You know, Jose Feliciano,
you got no complaints.
Waiter!
What is he, deaf?
So...
How long you work
for the escort service?
I don't know.
A few months.
Find that work interesting, do you?
What are you talking about?
Right.
Come on.
I'm hearing bells.
All right.
Where were you?
(DOOR OPENS)
(GASPS)
(WOMAN SCREAMING)
Shep, what the hell are you doing?
I'm banging that girl.
Fucking asshole.
Get the fuck out of here.
Put me back in Stillwater,
you little fucking shithead.
Get the fuck out of here.
(POUNDING AT DOOR)
MAN: Yo!
Cut that shit out, man.
Trying to get some
goddamn sleep here.
Come on, brother...
Fuck you!
Fuck you.
Animals!
(WOMAN SCREAMING)
Stay away from me, man.
Hey, smoke a fucking peace pipe!
Don't you dare fucking hit me!
(CHOKING)
Fucking little weasel!
- Fuck you, man.
- Stop it!
You fucking, motherfucking,
son-of-a-bitching, fucking cock!
Jesus Christ!
You fucking shitbag motherfucker!
(PHONE RINGING)
JERRY: Yeah?
All right, Jerry,
I'm through fucking around.
You got the fucking money?
Yeah, I got the money, but...
Don't you fucking but me, Jerry.
I want you to put this money in the
Dayton Radisson parking ramp, top level,
30 minutes, Jerry,
we wrap this thing up.
Okay. But...
Hey, you're there in 30
minutes or I find you, Jerry,
and I shoot you and I
shoot your fucking wife,
and I shoot all your
little fucking children
and I shoot them all in the back of
their little fucking heads. You got it?
Okay, now,
you stay away from Scotty, now.
Got it?
Okay. Real good, then.
SCOTTY: Dad.
It's okay, Scotty.
Where you going?
I'll be back in a minute.
If Stan calls, you just
tell him I went to Embers.
Okay.
Here's your damn money.
Now, where's my daughter?
Yeah.
You goddamn punk!
Who the fuck are you?
I got your damn money.
Now, where's my daughter?
I am through fucking around!
Drop that fucking briefcase!
Where's my daughter?
Fuck you, man!
Where's Jerry?
I gave simple fucking instructions.
Where's my damn daughter?
No Jean, no money.
Drop that fucking money!
No Jean, no money!
Is this a fucking joke here?
Oh, jeez.
You happy now, asshole?
What's with you people?
You fucking imbeciles!
You fucking shot me!
(SCREAMING)
(GROANING)
May I have your ticket, please?
Open the fucking gate!
Oh, jeez.
SCOTTY: Dad?
Yeah?
Stan Grossman called.
Yeah. Okay.
Twice.
Okay.
Is everything okay?
Yeah.
Are you calling Stan?
Well, I'm...
I'm going to bed now.
MOHRA: How you doing?
- Mr. Mohra?
- Yeah?
Officer Olson.
Yeah. Righto.
Well...
So I'm tending bar down there at
Ecklund and Swedlin's last Tuesday,
and this little guy's drinking,
and he says, "Where can
a guy find some action?
"I'm going crazy out
there at the lake."
And I says, "What kind of action?"
And he says, "Woman action.
What do I look like?"
And I says, "Well,
what do I look like?
"I don't arrange
that kind of thing."
And he says, "But I'm going
crazy out there at the lake."
And I says, "Yeah, but this
ain't that kind of place."
He says, "Oh, so I get it. So you think
I'm some kind of jerk for asking."
Only he don't use the word "jerk."
- I understand.
- Then he calls me a jerk,
says the last guy thought
he's a jerk is dead now.
So, I don't say nothing.
He says, "What do you
think about that?"
And I says, "Well, that don't sound
like too good a deal for him, then."
You got that right.
Yeah, he says, "Yeah,
that guy's dead,
"and I don't mean of old age."
And then he says, "Jeez, I'm going
crazy out there at the lake."
White Bear Lake?
Yeah, well, at Ecklund and Swedlin,
that's closer to Moose Lake.
So I made that assumption.
Sure.
Anyway, he's drinking at the bar,
so I don't think
a whole great deal of it,
but then Mrs. Mohra, she heard
about the homicides down here
and thought I should
call it in, so I called it in.
End of story.
Well, what'd this guy
look like, anyways?
Oh, he's a...
Little guy, kind of funny-looking.
In what way?
Just in a general kind of way.
Okay. Well, thanks a
bunch, Mr. Mohra.
You're right.
It's probably nothing,
but thanks for calling her in.
Sure.
Looks like she's gonna
turn cold tomorrow.
Oh, yeah.
Got a front coming in.
Yeah.
You got that right.
Jesus Christ.
(GRUNTS)
Valerie, I'm leaving this
morning, back up to Brainerd.
Well, I'm sorry I won't see you.
But you think he's all right?
I saw him last night and...
What did he say?
Well, it's nothing specific he said.
It just seemed like it all hit
him really hard, his wife dying.
- His wife?
- Linda.
- Who?
- Linda Cooksey.
No. No, no.
They weren't...
He was bothering Linda for about...
For a good year.
Really pestering her,
wouldn't leave her alone.
So...
He didn't...
He never...
No! No, they never married.
Mike's had psychiatric problems.
Oh, my.
Yeah, he's been struggling.
He's living with his parents now.
Oh, jeez.
Linda's fine.
You should call her.
Jeez. Well...
Jeez.
That's a surprise.
Hello!
Mr. Lundegaard, sorry to bother you again.
Can I come in?
(STUTTERING) Yeah... No.
I'm kind of busy here.
I understand.
I'll keep it real short, then.
I'm on my way out of town,
but I was wondering...
Do you mind if I sit down?
Carrying a bit of a load here.
No, I...
Yeah, it's this vehicle
I asked about yesterday.
I was just wondering...
Yeah, like I told you, we haven't
had any vehicles go missing.
Okay. Are you sure?
'Cause I mean, how do you know?
Because, see,
the crime I'm investigating,
the perpetrators were driving
a car with dealer plates,
and they called
someone who works here,
so it'd be quite a
coincidence if they weren't,
you know, connected.
Yeah, I see.
So, how do you...
Have you done any kind
of inventory recently?
The car's not from our lot, ma'am.
But how do you know that
for sure without doing a...
Well, I would know.
I'm the Executive Sales Manager.
Yeah, but I understand...
We run a pretty tight ship here.
I know, but...
Well, how do
they establish that, sir?
I mean, are the cars counted daily,
or what kind of a routine here?
Ma'am, I answered your question.
I'm sorry, sir?
I answered the darn...
(STUTTERING) I'm cooperating
here, and there's no...
Sir, you have no call
to get snippy with me.
I'm just doing my job here.
I'm...
I'm not...
I'm not arguing here.
I'm cooperating, and there's no...
We're doing all we can.
Sir, could I talk to Mr. Gustafson?
Mr. Lundegaard.
Well, heck! If you wanna...
If you wanna play games here,
I'm working with you
on this thing here, but...
Okay! I'll do a damn lot count!
Sir, right now?
Yeah! Right now.
You're darn tooting!
If it's so damned important to you.
Well, I'm sorry, sir.
What the Christ! Jeez!
WOMAN ON PA: Bob Elcorona, line two.
(EXCLAIMS)
For Pete's sake.
For Pete's sake,
he's fleeing the interview.
He's fleeing the interview!
How do I get an outside line here?
All right.
Yeah.
Detective Sibert, please.
MAN: I told you it was over,
and I thought I made myself very clear.
WOMAN: Oh, you did.
You made yourself perfectly clear.
But something's come up.
What?
Well, it's something kind of small,
but it might be a big problem.
I'm pregnant.
I've had a doctor's test,
I've got the certificate,
and there's no doubt about it,
I'm gonna have your baby.
Now, look here.
I can explain this.
See, Robin was...
ls a student of mine.
You should see the other guy.
No, no, no.
It wasn't anything like that.
You don't understand!
I read that letter that she wrote.
I think I understand all there is...
CARL: What happened to her?
She started shrieking, you know.
Jeez.
Well, I got the money.
All of it, all 80 grand.
That's 40 for you, 40 for me.
That's it, then.
(KEYS JINGLING)
You can have my truck.
I'm taking the Cierra.
We split that.
How the fuck do you split
a fucking car, you dummy?
With a fucking chain saw?
One of us pays the other for half.
Hold on.
No fucking way.
Did you fucking notice this?
I got fucking shot!
I got fucking shot in the face!
I went and got the fucking money!
I got shot fucking picking it up!
I've been up for 36 fucking hours!
I'm taking that fucking car!
That fuck is mine,
you fucking asshole.
You know, I've been listening to
your fucking bullshit all week!
Are we square?
Yeah, you fucking mute!
And if you see your friend,
Shep Proudfoot,
tell him I'm gonna
nail his fucking ass.
MAN ON TV: I'll call you...
Later.
(SCREAMING)
LOU ON RADIO: His wife. This guy says
she was kidnapped last Wednesday.
The day of our homicides.
Yeah.
And this guy was who?
Lundegaard's
father-in-law's accountant.
Gustafson's accountant.
Yeah.
But we still
haven't found Gustafson?
...looking...
Sorry. Didn't copy, Lou.
Still missing.
We're looking.
Copy.
And Lundegaard, too?
Yeah.
Where are you, Margie?
I'm almost back.
I'm taking a drive
around Moose Lake.
Gary's loudmouth.
Yeah, the loudmouth.
So the whole state has it, huh?
Gustafson and Lundegaard?
Yeah.
It's over the wire.
It's everywhere.
They'll find them.
Copy.
Yeah, we got a lead on this...
There's the car!
Whose car?
My car! My car!
Tan Cierra! Tan Cierra!
Okay. Careful, Margie.
I'll send a couple cars.
(MACHINE WHIRRING)
Police!
Hands up!
(GUN FIRES)
(GROANING)
So that was Mrs. Lundegaard
on the floor in there.
And I guess that was your
accomplice in the wood chipper.
And those three people in Brainerd.
And for what?
For a little bit of money.
There's more to life than
a little money, you know?
Don't you know that?
And here you are.
And it's a beautiful day.
(SIREN WAILING)
Well...
I just don't understand it.
Mr. Anderson?
JERRY: Who?
Mr. Anderson, is this your
burgundy '98 out here?
Just a sec.
Could you open the door, please?
Yeah, yeah, just a sec.
Just a sec.
- COP: Dale!
- JERRY: My leg!
No!
(JERRY SCREAMING)
(GROANING)
(SIGHS)
(CHATTERING ON TV)
They announced it.
They announced it?
Yeah.
So?
Three-cent stamp.
Your mallard?
Yeah.
That's terrific.
It's just a three-cent.
It's terrific.
Hautman's blue-winged
teal got the 29-cent.
People don't much
use the three-cent.
Oh, for Pete's...
Of course they do.
Whenever they raise the postage,
people need the little stamps.
Yeah?
When they're stuck with
a bunch of the old ones.
Yeah.
I guess.
That's terrific.
I'm so proud of you, Norm.
Heck, Norm, you know,
we're doing pretty good.
I love you, Margie.
I love you, Norm.
Two more months.