What?
I said I want to tell you my story.
What the hell?
What's with the way
you fucking talk?
Who the fuck are you?
My name is...
Oh Dae-su.
Why did you hit on
someone else's girlfriend?
Hold on.
Did I hit on her?
- Mr. Oh Dae-su!
- Did I hit on her?
Fuck!
Okay! I got it.
Just a minute.
Okay! Okay!
Fuck.
Mr. Oh Dae-su
please sit down.
He is totally drunk.
I hit on her?
Hey, let me piss first.
I didn't hit on anyone!
- You son of a bitch!
- This guy is a real headache.
- Asshole!
- Mr. Oh Dae-su!
Sit down.
I'm very sorry.
- I gotta piss bad.
- Great.
- Cute, huh?
- Yeah, yeah. Sit down.
Today is
my daughter's birthday.
I got her
a birthday present.
Snatches of clouds
float in the sky.
Ah, great.
A pleasure boat
floats on the river.
My name
Oh Dae-su, means...
..."Just get by the day quietly."
That's why I'm Oh Dae-su.
But, shit...
Why can't I get by this day quietly...
Let me go! Huh!
- Shut the hell up!
- Let me go!
Let go of me!
That guy really needs
some prison time.
- Get away from me!
- Hey, get him!
I'll make sure he doesn't get drunk
and cause trouble again.
Have a nice day
Officer.
He's usually a nice guy, but...
Let's go.
I'll come visit you soon.
No need.
Don't come back.
That's up to me
you assholes.
Hey!
My sweet pea, it's daddy.
Daddy got you a present.
I'll be home soon with your gift
so wait a bit longer.
Let me talk to her.
- Good girl, good.
- Give me the phone.
Sweet pea, Joo-hwan
wants to talk to you.
You know Joo-hwan, right?
Hold on.
Hi, sweetie.
It's me, Joo-hwan.
So today's your birthday?
Happy birthday.
I'll treat you
to something nice tomorrow.
Hello?
Oh, Ja-hyun, I'm sorry.
I know it's very late.
Dae-su is on his way now.
I'm sorry.
Yes? Hold on.
Dae-su, it's your wife.
Dae-su!
Oh Dae-su!
I really had enough!
Stop fooling around and let's go already.
Dae-su!
Sir, sir.
Wait, come here.
Come talk to me.
I won't ask you to let me go.
Just tell me why I'm here, okay?
I should know the reason at least.
Shit, I've been locked up here
for two months already.
Sir, wait, come here.
What is this place?
Sir, just tell me how long
I have to stay in here.
Just tell me that, huh?
Sir!
Fuck you!
Come here, you asshole!
Son of a bitch.
I saw your face, asshole.
You're dead when I get out.
Come here, asshole.
I'm sorry. I won't curse.
Just tell me.
One month, two, or three?
Hey, where are you going?
Just tell me how long
you son of a bitch!
I said tell me how long
you asshole!
You son of a bitch!
Fucking assholes!
If they had told me
it was going to be 15 years...
...could it have been
easier to endure?
Or could it have not?
"Laugh, and the world laughs with you.
Weep, and you weep alone."
When the melody plays
gas comes out.
When the gas comes
I fall asleep.
I found out later
that it's the same Valium gas...
...Russian soldiers
used on the Chechen terrorists.
When I wake up
my hair has been cut.
I don't like the style really.
But they change my clothes
and clean the place up.
Kind bastards.
One, two...
...three.
It's too spicy...
I don't want spinach...
You eat it...
I won't eat spinach...
Kim Ja-hyun's body was found
deeply stabbed in the neck.
The brutality of the murder
with no valuables missing...
...led the police to suspect that
the motive was personal grudge.
Her husband who disappeared a year ago
is now on the wanted list.
According to neighbors
the missing husband, Oh Dae-su...
...drank often, causing trouble
with his wife and the neighbors.
Blood found at the scene
matched Oh Dae-su's...
...ana' fresh fingerprints were fauna'
from a cup at the crime scene...
...proving that Oh Dae-su recently
visited his wife, according to the police.
A missing family album, the only
stolen item also backs their theories.
After three years...
...many wrinkles
have formed on his face.
- That is around $61000
- For a Sushi knife .7
"Right always prevails"
if you stand aimlessly
ata phone booth on a rainy day...
- .-and meet a man whose face
is hidden under a purple umbrella...
...I'd suggest that you get close to the TV.
- "A listening device?"
The television is both
a clock and a calendar.
It's your school
home, church...
...friend...
...and lover.
But...
Countless nights may pass...
...but my heart is turned to you.
Though I may shed my sad tears...
...it's still your face that I miss.
But...
...my lover's song..
...is too short.
This morning around 7:50
the Sungsoo Bridge...
...in Seoul suddenly
collapsed in the middle...
I wrote about all the people
I fought, tormented, and hurt.
This was bath my prison journal...
...and autobiography
of my evil deeds.
I thought I had lived
an average life...
...but I've sinned so much.
All I could think about
at that moment was...
...the poor guy next door is eating
with only one chopstick.
But...
Who locked me up here?
Yoo Heung-sam?
Lee So-young or Kang Chang-suk?
Whoever it was, just wait.
Wait just a bit.
From the top of your head
down to the tips of your toes...
...no one will be able to find
any trace of your body on this earth.
Because I'm going
to chew up every last piece of it.
One line for one year.
For this first time
I have to ink in six lines.
It will be easier from next year.
The more the tattoos
the shorter gets the chopstick.
The shorter gets the chopstick
the bigger gets the hole in the wall.
Anyway...
...time passes well.
9 years.
10 years.
11 years.
"The Ex-president
Arrested"
"Hong Kong
Handover Ceremony"
"Death of Princess Diana"
"Funeral:
Westminster Abbey"
"IMF Financial Support
Officially Approved"
12 years.
"Oath of Office"
"Gun Salute"
"President Kim Dae-jung
Arrives in Pyongyang"
"Korea Enters
World Cup Quarterfinals!“
13 years.
"Elected:
Rah Moo-hyun"
14 years.
I'll be out in a month.
I'll be out in only one month.
I'll be out.
I 'll be out after a month.
I 'll be out of here.
One month, in just one month
I 'II be out.
I'll need money when I get out
what should I do?
Should I steal or rob?
What shall I eat first?
Kimchi stew, grilled eels?
Anything as long as
it's not fried dumplings.
Where is this place anyway?
I hear noisy traffic
so this must be a city.
But the important thing is
just what floor this is.
What if I break through the wall
and it's the 52nd floor?
Even if! fall to my death
I'm still getting out.
I'm getting out.
In one month, I'm getting out.
Right now
you're lying on a field.
When you hear the bell...
...you will turn your head
and look down.
You will see
an endless field of green grass.
The sun is shining bright
and there's a gentle breeze.
It's a human being.
Don't stop me!
Mister...
...even though
I'm no better than a beast...
...don't I have the right to live, no?
Mister...
...even though
I'm no better than a beast...
...don't I have the right to live, no?
That phone booth alley
was right here.
Now there's
an apartment building.
Still, dumping me on the roof...
he's not the most flexible type.
I want to tell you my story.
Die a little later.
What?
I see.
Now, I'll tell you my story.
You see, the reason
why I want to die...
Mister!
It's a woman human being.
That crazy guy took my sunglasses...
Laugh, and the world laughs with you.
Weep, and you weep alone.
My home is gone.
I can't call my friends or relatives...
...because I'm someone
who's murdered his wife.
Because I'm a fugitive.
I swear man.
Nah, he'll kick your ass.
Come on, trust me man.
You fucktard!
Fucktard...
Never heard that one before.
TV doesn't teach you curse words.
10 years of imaginary training.
Is it any use in real life?
It is.
Striped beakfish.
Oplegnathus fasciatus.
Lives in the warm waters
of coastal reefs.
Despite its weak reflexes...
...it's known to resist
tenaciously when caught.
In South Kyoung-sang Province
its offspring...
What's this smell?
Don't even think about
asking me any questions.
I don't know a thing.
Pardon?
I said I want to eat something alive.
Oh, right...
Long time no see.
This is my first time.
Maybe not?
But she looks familiar.
You look very familiar.
Where have we met?
"The Search for the Best Chefs"
Channel 11 Thursdays at 6:30
The youngest female
Japanese cuisine chef in Korea.
Oh that?
They said the ratings are low
but I guess not.
Women's hands are warm
so they can't make sushi.
You sure do know a lot.
Who are you?
Do you like your clothes?
Why...
- Why did you lock me up?
- Who do you think I am?
- 'loo Heung-sam'!
- Wrong.
- Did Lee So-young hire you?
- No, Wrong again.
Lee Jung-VOW?
Kang Chang-sum Hwang Joo-yeon'!?
Kim Na-sung'? Park Jin-woo?
Im Duk-yoon? Lee Jae-pyung?
Kuk Su-ran? Who is it'?
Who the hell are you?
Me?
I'm sort of a scholar
ano' my major is you.
An 0h Dae-su-ologist.
An expert on Oh Dae-su.
Who I am isn't important.
The important thing is why.
Think it over.
Review your whole life.
School is over, so now
it's time for homework. Right?
Keep this in mind...
Be it a grain of sand or a rock
in water they sink the same.
Let me ask you one thing.
You hypnotized me in there
didn't you?
What was the hypnotic suggestion?
I miss you.
Hurry and come to me.
Here you are.
It's alive, right'?
May I slice it now?
I must be different from other women.
My hands are very cold.
What's with her?
Sir.
Hold on.
Hey mister, wake up...
Keep this in mind...
Be it a grain of sand or a rock
in water they sink the same.
You're awake?
Is this true?
That fever medicine
really works.
You fainted so easy for
someone who exercised so much.
Lack of sunlight over a longtime
leads to deficiencies in vitamins A and E.
Hence my lack of immunity
against the influenza.
Do you usually talk that way?
The bathroom door is broken
and doesn't lock.
Don't get any ideas.
I could slice you like sashimi.
What's this?
Suppositories.
How else could I feed medicine
to someone who's fainted?
15 years of imaginary training.
Is it any use in real life?
It isn't.
I deserve to die for that.
I bring you here only to deny you.
I get why you're angry.
I admit it.
I brought you here
because I like you too, but...
You don't even know my name.
I'm Mido.
You know...
Later, when I feel I'm ready...
Then we do it.
Scouts honor.
That song, "The Face I Miss"
in your journal. That's the sign.
When I sing it
get yourself ready right away.
When it actually comes to
the critical moment, I may resist.
But show no mercy.
Just give it to me!
Give it to you?
The ants...
Do they still come out?
Do you still feel them?
When it comes to loneliness
it's always the ants.
The real lonely people I met...
...they all hallucinated ants
even if just for a second.
Come to think about it...
You know how ants always
move in groups.
So I suppose the real lonely people
keep imagining ants.
Of course, I never did myself.
She called from overseas
five or six years ago.
Asked if her dad showed up.
She didn't even know that
he killed her mother.
She must have called us since
she only has few relatives.
She had lost a lot of her Korean.
Her foster parents are
both doctors or something.
Anyhow, Miss Reporter...
Dae-su is really
not caught yet?
Your daughter's address is on the front.
On the back is a map to your wife's grave.
Eva...
Stockholm... Eva...
Do you want to call her?
Want me to call her?
Want to go to
the grave together?
No, after I kill that bastard first.
"Blue Dragon"
Is it the one?
I haven't even started chewing.
"Blue Dragon"
$0'?
Was that the same taste?
Be it 10 or 100 restaurants
it doesn't matter.
I can't ever forget the taste
I had for 15 years.
"Blue Dragon"
Shall I make you a log-in ID?
Your favorite movie or song?
I was talking to him...
"Evergreen: Where did you go? Talking to someone?
Princess Sashimi: I was talking to him.“
"The Count of Monte Cristo?"
There's no one
by that name here.
"How's life in a bigger prison
Mr. Oh Dae-su?"
Who are you?
"Who are you..."
"A lonely prince locked up
in a high tower."
Who is he?
I don't know.
Just someone I chat with sometimes.
And talk about sushi.
Where are you going?
I can't trust you.
"Purple... "
Purple Blue Dragon
A dragon that's purple and blue.
What does that mean?
Why order from so far away?
We passed five Chinese places
just on the way here.
Feels like my lungs will explode.
Tell your chef to go easy on the scallions
in the fried dumplings.
Sure.
- Set it down and go.
- Okay.
We can't do it by ourselves if it's
someone protected by bodyguards.
There are people
who specialize in that.
You'll have to hire them too.
We do it by ourselves
only if they are small fries.
But if it's over six months
we'll bring them in for free.
Yes, that's right.
Why did you imprison me, you...
...fucktard.
In our 7.5 floor business
we guard client info with our lives.
I'm going to pay you back
for all 15 years of my life.
With each one pulled out
you age by one year.
Stay still.
Ready to talk?
I don't know...
I didn't see his face...
I recorded the call...
"Oh Dae-su"
All AB blood types raise your hands.
Hurry, he lost a lot of blood.
Damn, look at him.
Is he dead?
You little piece of shit...
You piece of shit!
- Go, motherfucker!
- Get the fuck out!
Fuckface!
You fucked up son of a bitch!
Just kill him
damn asshole.
Fucking asshole!
Yet another day
I couldn't get by quietly.
I've now become a monster.
When my vengeance is over
could I return to being the old Dae-su?
Mister, are you alright?
Look at all this blood.
Mister, what happened to you?
Saewoon Apartments
in Eung-am, building 8.
Please take care of him.
- Thank you.
- Not at all.
Well, then...
Farewell, Oh Dae-su.
Farewell...
A bastard you hate
but wouldn't want to kill.
A bitch you detest
but want more than to kill.
We'll take care of them.
Don't they go mad
being locked up for so long?
If you prefer that he doesn't
we can administer some medication.
There's this one called
“Risperdal Solution"
It's known to be a reliable
treatment for schizophrenia.
The duration is always the issue.
- How long are you thinking of...?
- 15 years.
- Too long?
- What did he do wrong...?
Oh Dae-su, you see...
...talks too much.
Go to sleep.
It's about time you visited Joo-hwan's
Internet cafe tomorrow.
Sit wherever you'd like.
Joo-hwan.
Oh Dae-su, you see...
...talks too much.
Have you heard
this voice before?
Do you know anyone who would
hate me this much?
I don't know all the 260 names
of your women's husbands.
"Mido (Princess Sashimi)"
- Who's Mido?
- This girl who cries over nothing.
Joo-hwan.
Did I really talk that much?
Dae-su, the way I see it
you should look for the perpetrator...
...among those who used to be
in your close proximity.
"Search for friends: Evergreen"
"Over 50 search results."
"Evergreen invites you
to be anline friends."
"Congratulations. As of yesterday statute of limitations
has expired for the murder suspect Oh Dae-su."
But please remember.
Open quote.
Like a gazelle from
the hand of the hunter
Like a bird from
the snare of the fowler
Free yourself.
- Close quote.
- Who are you?
Who are you, you rotten bastard?
I had decided
while I was locked up.
That I wouldn't
trust anyone if I get out.
That if! find anyone
to be suspicious...
...I would create a secret which
only that person and I will know.
The messenger ID, 'Monster'
is a trap that I made to catch you.
You bring a complete stranger home.
Who are you?
Who is Evergreen?
I tracked down that ID, Evergreen
and found out the personal details.
- Ready to jot it down?
- Go ahead
The name is Su Dee-ah.
Ever heard that surname, 'Su '.7
- Address?
- It's in Eung-am.
Saewoon Apartments
Building 7, unit 407.
I'm not doing fine
in this life in a bigger prison.
"Evergreen."
"Who are you?"
You were going to
say that, right?
No, you must find out on your own.
Come on, it's a game.
First, who?
Then, why?
Once you solve the questions
come see me anytime.
I'll mark the answers for you.
You have until July 5th.
Only five days left.
Too short?
Do your best. If you pass
I'll kill myself instead of Mido.
That's right, Mido.
I'm going to kill every woman
you love until you die.
You're notorious for not being
able to protect your women.
Wow, you're strong
Mr. Monster.
You truly are the monster
of my creation.
But this way, you won't
ever find out the "why?"
The question that bugged you
for the last 15 years.
You don't care anymore?
Take that seat.
Ah, the dental torture.
You won't get enough time
to torture me.
I have a weak heart
so I have this motor inside.
When it was put in
do you know what I said to the doctor?
Doctor Hopkins...
...give me a remote control
that can switch the motor off.
Pardon? Why?
Sol can kill myself easily
any time I want.
I'll give you a 100 grand more.
Oh, what a conundrum.
You want to kill me right away...
...but you won't find out
why you were locked up.
You want to torture me but
I say I'll kill myself first.
To get your revenge
or to find out the reason.
Oh, that is the big question.
I've been watching you
for 15 years.
I fared well thanks to you.
I wasn't bored or lonely.
Seeking revenge is the best cure
for the ones who were hurt.
Try it.
The loss of 15 years.
The pain of losing your wife and child.
All these would go away.
In other words
vengeance is healthy.
But what happens after
you've fulfilled your vengeance?
I bet that hidden pain
will probably come back again.
"Are you there
Mr. Oh Dae-su?"
"Mr. Oh Dae-su
long time no see."
Hasn't she been tied up for too long?
I think you also left the door open.
Please save me.
I need saving myself.
Rudolph the red nosed reindeer
had a very shiny nose.
This dentist is really good.
Don't move.
What's with you?
Now...
...here we go.
You know, they say that
cowardice comes from imagination.
So try not to imagine.
It'll make you fucking brave.
Now, here comes the real thing.
Yes?
Well, sir, I do thank you for
telling me about this place...
...but I haven't even started.
What?
Let's go.
Let's really go.
Let's fight.
Tenacious.
Your hand.
I'm going to cut off your hand.
You touched Mido's breasts.
Then what about my tongue?
You still don't trust me
you rotten bastard?
I don't think we'll
reach an agreement.
I looked into it...
...and their reason for not paying
more than 270 million...
...wasn't to do with
the evaluation of this building.
It's likely that their
convertible bonds holders are...
So I think there won't be a big issue.
Of course, there's the 25 percent stake
held by their chairman and his relatives...
Dae-su.
Yeah.
Did he really say
that he'll kill me?
Yeah.
Because I am
a woman you love?
Dae-su.
What?
I wonder where my love is.
The night is getting lonelier.
The words we spoke with our eyes...
...can be felt with these hands.
Countless nights may pass...
...but my heart is turned to you.
Though I may shed my sad tears...
...it's still your face that I miss.
They packed up and left in a rental car.
Mido called the restaurant and quit.
Let's go after this is done.
You should get some rest today.
I have insomnia anyway.
"The night is getting lonelier."
Mr. Han, do you really think...
...Mid0 has fallen in love
with Oh Dae-su?
Already?
Dae-su, it really hurts.
But I'm enduring it.
I want you to know that.
How did you hold out?
For 15 years?
There's always a way.
Do you like it?
You really like it, right'?
I want to be good to you.
Do not worry about the future.
Don't imagine anything.
I feel thankful for
all those years in that prison.
If I was still my old self
would Mido have liked me like this?
The fact that he knew I wanted to
cut off Park's hand means...
...he's planted a bug on us.
He knew where we were by tailing us.
"I've been bugged.
Please find it."
Maybe, he let you go...
...because he has fun watching you
run wild seeking revenge.
Never telling you why
toying with you forever.
Could that be it?
Evergreen Press
Online Printing System.
Evergreen Pasta and Pizza.
Evergreen Services, specializing in
security, parking, cleaning.
Evergreen Tree Garden.
Evergreen Old Boys...
...Sangnok High School
alumni homepage.
Evergreen Secret Diary
Jung Sang-rok's personal site.
Norwegian Wood, Evergreen...
"Welcome to Evergreen Old Boys...
...the Sangnok High School
Alumni Homepage."
But it's time to close up.
Can't I look at the
records of Class '79?
It's dark so turn on the lights.
Take your time.
Joo-hwan?
Let me ask you something.
Do you know
Lee Woo-jin of Class '79?
I think he went to
America to study.
Lee Woo-fin?
Don't know him. Is that his name?
How did you find out?
Looked through all the yearbooks
and found his face.
I wouldn't know him
just by his name.
"Scissorhands
Hair Salon... "
Got anything else?
Like the school records?
Do you know Lee Soc-ah'?
She was in our year.
- Lee Sea-ah? She died.
- What class was she in?
Homeroom two.
She was in my class...
...next to yours.
What about her?
But why is there...
...no photo, because she was dead.
How did Soo-ah die?
That's right, you wouldn't know.
She died after you transferred.
She went alone to the Habchun Dam
fell into the river, and drowned.
A week later they found
her bloated body in the water.
- What was she like?
- Her?
She was a total slut.
Acting like a prude on the outside
but a filthy whore on the inside.
There was a huge rumor at the school
that she fucked anyone and everyone.
I should've gotten in there.
Anyway, her family was super rich.
Her grades were really good, too.
But the crucial thing was
that she was such a slut.
This is such an old story.
Dae-su, I don't remember too well
since it was so long ago...
...but that Soo-ah...
Wait, didn't you also...?
Hey, what's going on?
Joo-hwan!
Joo-hwan
what's happening?
Joo-hwan!
Mr. Oh Dae-su?
My sister wasn't a slut.
I really want you to know that.
Because you got rid of all the bugs
I had to come all the way here.
To listen in.
So, Mr. Roh Joo-hwan...
...died because of you.
Okay?
You son of a bitch!
I'm going to kill you!
I am going to rip you
into little pieces!
Motherfucker!
We're not open yet.
Please come back in an hour.
A man who got six gold teeth here
recommended this place.
Mr. Park'?
I had to move because of you.
To celebrate...
...I bought some new TVs.
Do you like it?
There are so many channels.
Exciting, huh?
Some of them even
refuse to leave.
You lived in a place like this
for 15 years?
Got used to it after 11 years.
Come on, I don't need money.
An enemy's enemy is a friend.
We threw away the hand
because it rotted.
My wife will be happy...
Damn sons of bitches
I want to kick their asses.
So why did you bring me here?
Let me go!
If I don't return after July 5th
then let her go.
While I was locked up
I remember someone visiting me.
- What did that person do?
- Was it three times?
I put hypnosis-inducing
drug in your water.
Sodium Barbiturate?
TV Man knows it all.
Dae-su!
"Scissorhands
Hair Salon... "
That's nonsense.
Even though it was a
Catholic school...
...doubt she killed herself
because of those rumors.
There probably was
another reason.
Like she got pregnant
or something.
But I don't think Soo-ah
really was a slut.
She was such a
neat and tidy girl.
She wouldn't put out
for just anyone.
There must have been a guy
she was going out with.
So who was that guy?
Well, I wouldn't know.
Choon-shim.
You knew Lee Soo-ah, right?
Who was her boyfriend?
Don't know?
Shut the hell up.
What would you know
about friendship?
Shut your trap.
Then who'd know?
Who?
Joo-hwan?
What?
Yeah, I know him.
But how would he know?
[Yeah'!
Ream]?
Okay, hang up.
I'll call you in a bit.
Choon-shim says Joo-hwan
had told her about it.
And says that
you would know the best.
Ring, ring, move aside.
You'll get hurt if you hesitate.
"Oh Dae-su"
Look at you.
Put it out!
I'm transferring today
to Seoul.
So butt out, Miss Kim.
You good-for-nothing...!
- You're Oh Dae-su, right?
- And you're Miss...?
I heard you're popular
among the girls.
You know how rumors are.
I heard you're really funny.
Say something funny.
Being stuck with one image
isn't healthy, but...
There's this father and son.
They went to the public bath...
See you later.
"Take Care
Homeroom Three Fuckheads!"
- Come on.
- Wait.
- Come here.
- No...
- Hurry and come here.
- Okay, okay.
Satisfied?
- Raise this up.
- No way.
- Raise it.
- No.
What?
It tickles.
Give it here.
What are you doing?
- Let me see.
- See what?
- Stop.
Go away.
Was it really Soo-ah?
You sure?
I don't know her name.
All I know is that she's in your class
and she rides a red bike.
Have a good trip.
See you in Seoul if I go.
- Where are you going?
- Going on a date with Choon-shim.
You're dead meat
if you tell anyone!
No way.
You get locked up for 15 years
just for saying that?
Was that such a big sin?
Be it a grain of sand or a rock
in water they sink the same.
That's what Lee Woo-jin believes.
Then what's special about
July 5th?
That's the day...
...Lee Soo-ah died.
It's over then.
You said it's not about vengeance
but finding out why he locked you up.
Now we'll run away where
he can never find us, right'?
I can't end it like this.
Vengeance has now
become a part of me.
But you don't even know
where he lives.
Like a gazelle from
the hand of the hunter
Like a bird from
the snare of the fowler
Free yourself.
It's from The Proverbs chapter 6 verse 4.
"Proverbs" is another word for "Maxim".
Ana' Evergreen said
he lives in a high tower.
So chapter 6 verse 4
must mean the floor numbers.
Fourth floor? Sixth floor?
Or the sixty-fourth floor?
P?
Penthouse!
Please press the passcode.
What would you like me to pray for?
Wrong entry.
Please press again.
"Dear Lord...
...please let me meet
a younger man next time."
Please make Lee Woo-jin
kneel down to Dae-su...
...and beg him for mercy.
You slept with your sister.
Let's go up and talk.
Sic him!
Let's talk it out.
Feels great.
You slept with your sister.
So refreshing.
And I started the rumors.
That's why your sister died.
Looking through the mirror
reminds me of that day. Same for you?
How unfair of you to erase my memory
and then to tell me to find it.
I won, so...
...die like you promised.
You think you couldn't remember that day
because you were hypnotized? Really?
Do you know the real reason
why you couldn't remember?
Let me tell you.
You just forgot.
Is that a let down?
But it's true
you simply forgot.
Why?
Because it wasn't your business.
Your rumor grew to the point where
they were saying Soo-ah got pregnant.
My sister got sucked into that rumor
and in the end, began to believe it.
Then, her period actually stopped
and her belly began to swell.
Amazing, isn't it'?
Ever thought about the girl, pregnant
with a child who's also her nephew?
Understand now?
'I our tongue
got my sister pregnant.
It wasn't Lee Woo-jin's dick.
It was Oh Dae-su's tongue.
Is that why you killed your sister?
I thought about the boy, about to
father a child who's also his nephew.
You were probably afraid.
Afraid that everyone will find out
once the baby's born.
When you realized that it was all just
her imagination after you killed her...
...how you must have hated me.
It's understandable.
They say Soo-ah died alone at the dam
but who took this photo?
What about this date, July 5th?
This is no fun.
I'll just finish what I was telling you.
Listen carefully. My story is really fun.
Ever heard of
post-hypnotic suggestion?
You suggest something
during hypnosis...
...and then it's acted out
in your awakened state.
Still haven't figured it out?
You bring a complete stranger home
who are you?
Who are you, you rotten bastard?
We hypnotized you both.
One very fortunate thing
was that you both were...
...highly receptive to hypnosis
compared to average people.
Isn't this fun?
One word gets you pregnant
one word gets you in love.
But no matter how much you two
are receptive to hypnosis...
...or no matter how good
a hypnotist Ms. Yoo is...
...getting people to
fall in love isn't easy.
So do you know what we did?
- Oh that?
- Your first suggest/on, of course...
...was to go to that restaurant
as soon as you were released.
Next, to react to the specific
melody from the cell phone.
When you hear the melody
you were to say certain words.
Who are you?
Do you like your clothes?
To the man who says those words
Mido was to perform a certain action.
When she grabs your hand
your reaction was to be, of course...
Your true mistake was not
failing to find the answer.
You kept asking the wrong question
so how could you find the right answer?
It's not "Why did Lee Woo-jin lock me up?"
It's "Why did he let me go?"
Once again...
...why did Lee Woo-jin release
Oh Dae-su after just...
".15 years?
"Laugh, and the world laughs with you.
Weep, and you will weep alone."
Mr. Han.
Mister Han!
Mme...
Mido doesn't know, right?
Why did you hide her there?
You thought he'd hate me
because I cut off his hand?
Didn't you stop to think
maybe it was a trap?
How can you protect your woman
with that brain of yours?
I've been secretly protecting Mido
since she was three.
But what about you?
Mr. Park's hand?
You imbecile.
Know that new prison of his?
He said he had to move.
So I gave him that building
in payment for his hand!
Dae-su!
There's a box here.
It's that same violet box.
He's telling me to open it.
No!
No, Mido, don't.
Don't open it no matter what.
If you open it
something terrible will happen.
What's in it?
You know, don't you?
Mido. My sweet pea
wait a bit longer.
I'll be there very soon.
Can't you come right now?
I'm scared.
My sweet pea
you can wait for me?
Yes.
Good.
Good girl.
I'll call you very soon, okay?
I beg you.
Please don't tell Mido.
What has she done wrong?
You know it was all my fault.
I have...
I have committed a terrible sin
to your sister.
And I was very wrong to you.
So please leave Mido alone, okay?
If Mido finds out the truth...
...you asshole...
...from the top of your head
down to the tips of your toes...
...no one will be able to find any trace of
your body on this earth. Why?
Because I'm going to
chew up every last piece of it.
WOO-jin!
Mr. Lee Woo-jin
I made a mistake.
Please forget what I said.
Sir! Boss!
WOO-jin!
We're Evergreen Old Boys
remember?
With the energy
from the green pine tree...
...the Great Sangnok High...
I'll do whatever you want.
I'll do anything.
I beg you.
Woo-jin, if you want me
to be a dog, I will!
I'm Woo-jin's dog from now on!
I'm your puppy!
Look, I'm wagging my tail.
I'm a dog.
I'll guard your house.
I'll be your slave dog.
The box...
Just leave it closed.
Now...
...what joy will I live for'?
Dae-su.
It really hurts.
But I'm enduring it.
I want you to know that.
How did you hold out?
For 15 years?
My sister and I knew everything
but still loved each other.
Can you two do the same?
Dae-su.
Do you like it?
I want to be good to you.
Sou-ah.
Woo-Km.
I know you've been scared.
So let go of me, okay?
Remember me, alright?
I have no regrets.
Do you?
Up until this point is
the whole story of my adventure.
Thank you for listening to
this terrible story to the end.
I hope you now understand
my sending a letter...
...instead of talking to you in person.
This is because I have no tongue.
To be honest
I have no reason to help you.
But you see...
I was touched
by this last sentence.
"Even though I'm no better than a beast...
...d0n 't I have the right to live?"
But the hypnosis may go wrong
and mess up your memories.
Will that be okay?
Once you're ready...
...stare at that tree.
The tree is slowly changing
into a concrete pillar.
You 're now inside Lee Woo-fin's penthouse.
It's a dreary night.
The sound of your footsteps to the window
echo through the room.
When I ring my bell...
...you'll be split
into two persons.
The one who doesn't know the secret
is named, "Oh Dae-su."
The one who keeps the secret
is named, "The Monster."
When I ring my bell again...
...the Monster will turn around
and begin walking.
With each step
he will age by one year.
When the Monster reaches seventy
he will die.
There's no need to worry.
It will be a very peaceful death.
Good luck.
What's wrong?
Look at you.
Who were you with?
I love you...
...Dae-su.
2016 @ PLAIN ARCHIVE. ALL RIGHT RESERVED.