JAKE: I remember those cheers.
They still ring in my ears, and for
years they remain in my thoughts,
'cause one night I took off
my robe, and what did I do?
I forgot to wear shorts.
I recall every fall,
every hook, every jab.
The worst way a guy
can get rid of his flab.
As you know, my life wasn't fab.
Though I'd much...
Though I'd rather hear you
cheer when you delve...
No, no. Though I'd rather hear you
cheer when I delve into Shakespeare.
"A horse, a horse!
My kingdom for a horse!"
I haven't had a winner
in six months.
And though I'm no Olivier,
I would much rather...
if he fought Sugar Ray,
he would say that the thing
ain't the ring, it's the play.
So give me a stage where
this bull here can rage,
and though I can fight,
I'd much rather recite.
That's entertainment.
ANNOUNCER: Jake La Motta and Jimmy
Reeves in the Cleveland Arena.
La Motta is undefeated, but
he is well behind on points.
(BELL CLANGS)
The Bronx Bull has taken a lot
of punishment in this round.
Jake is cut around the left eye.
Jack, tell me why?
Why the fuck do we have
to come to Cleveland
for you to get beaten
by a mulignane?
Come on, Jack, do the fucking
right thing here, will you?
He's got you by the balls, Jake.
You're out-pointed.
You're coming up to your 10th.
You're gonna have to knock him out.
JOEY: I want you
to bite him, kick him,
do anything you got to do.
Nobody's looking.
You know what to do.
MAN 1: Listen to Joey. Listen to Joey.
Just like home,
all over the fucking mooli.
Knock the motherfucker out.
You understand? Knock him out.
Hey, you want to go in there?
You want to go in there and...
(WOMAN SCREAMING)
WOMAN: Help!
MAN 2: You need a knockout.
Let's go get a knockout,
and that's where it's at.
REFEREE: Tenth and final round.
Good luck to you both.
ANNOUNCER: La Motta fighting
out of a half-crouch.
Reeves is up against
a tough fighter,
a man who doesn't know
how to back up.
La Motta continues to bore in.
La Motta out with
a bob and a weave,
hooks a left to the jaw
and Reeves is down.
The crowd is urging Jake on.
(PEOPLE CLAMORING)
The referee is toiling over Reeves.
He tries to get up.
La Motta comes at him once again.
Reeves misses a right, takes
a left and another left,
a hard left to the jaw, and Reeves
is down for the second time,
and a determined Jake La Motta
is making a great comeback
here in the 10th round.
Reeves is up again.
La Motta comes at him
with a left hook to the jaw,
another left and a right to the body,
three more lefts to the mid-section,
a hook on the jaw, two
more lefts to the head,
a right and a left
to the jaw by La Motta,
and Reeves goes down
for the third time,
and the referee is pulling
La Motta away.
Two, three,
four, five, six, seven.
The referee is hunched over Reeves,
but time is running out.
La Motta waits.
Eight, nine.
And there is the bell.
Reeves has been saved by the bell,
but did La Motta do it soon enough?
JOEY: Jack, Jack, come here.
It's no good.
This is Ohio, not New York.
You waited too long.
Joey, put my robe on right.
Put my robe on right.
Ladies and gentlemen,
(BELL CLANGS)
under the rules of the
Ohio Boxing Commission,
after 10 rounds,
the winner by a unanimous decision,
Jimmy Reeves.
ANNOUNCER: The colorful Jake La Motta, the
Bronx Bull, has lost his first fight.
That's Jake's fight. Come
on, that's Jake's fight!
Jake won that fight!
Don't leave. Don't get
out of the fucking ring.
Stay here. You won.
Let him go first.
Stay here, I'm telling you.
ANNOUNCER: La Motta ﬂoored
Reeves seven times in the fight,
but La Motta still lost.
CROWD: Jake! Jake! Jake! Jake!
Jake! Jake! Jake! Jake!
(WHISTLE BLOWING)
(BELL CLANGS)
(SCREAMING)
(ORGAN PLAYING STAR-SPANGLED BANNER)
JOEY: They pick up his arm,
he's dead.
They tell him he won the fight.
People went crazy.
That shit would've never happened
if Tommy was over there
taking care of him.
I mean, you know he's gotta be
with Tommy to fight in New York,
to get a title shot.
I mean, he's gonna wind up fucking
punch-drunk, your brother.
I know.
You know.
You gotta make him understand
that it's the best thing
for everybody involved.
I said I know.
You know, but you got
to make him know.
You got to tell him,
make him understand it.
Jesus Christ!
You want to stop.
When the fuck are you gonna
stop with all that stuff?
I told you, I
understand everything.
He just wants to do things
for himself. That's all.
Hard to understand?
That's because he's got
a head like concrete.
You make me laugh. You think it's easy?
Why don't you talk to him.
You know what to say.
Tell him.
You know I can't talk to him.
And why can't you talk to him?
'Cause he don't like me.
Yeah, nobody likes you. You
ought to be used to that.
They know.
They know who's the boss.
The judges didn't know, who
knows what happened with them?
The people knew.
You don't believe me,
you thought I was over
there fooling around, huh?
You thought I was fooling around, didn't you?
Tell me the truth.
I ain't gonna fool around.
That's in your mind.
Yeah. So what?
That championship belt on me,
that's when I fool around.
Is it done?
No, it's not done.
Don't overcook it. You
overcook it, it's no good.
It defeats its own purpose.
What are you doing?
I just said, don't overcook it.
You're overcooking it.
Bring it over.
You want your steak?
Bring it over!
It's like a piece of charcoal!
Bring it over here!
You want your steak?
Yeah, right now!
Good!
Good. Here's your stupid steak.
You can't wait for it
to be done? Here.
No, I can't wait.
Good. Okay Happy? Happy?
That's all I want.
Here. No.
More. There.
You bother me about a steak, huh?
That's great.
You bother me about a steak?
Yeah!
I agree with you.
He should be with Tommy.
If he's in a good mood,
I'll talk to him.
What the fuck do you want me to do?
But, Joey, Tommy tells me
every day to talk to you
to speak to Jake to
straighten this thing out.
I mean, I'm going to wind up
in the middle of this thing.
You're in the middle? I'm his brother.
He's got me fucking nuts.
You're his brother, if you can't talk
to him, who's gonna talk to him?
I'll talk to him. Do what
you can, that's all.
That's all I'm asking you.
All right, I'll see you tomorrow.
Let me go up.
Where you gonna be?
We'll be at the gym or the other joint.
One of the two.
I'll catch you by the gym.
All right.
Sal.
Yeah?
Go fuck yourself.
IRMA: Complain some more.
I want to hear.
I want to hear it.
You call those carrots? That's
right, they were carrots.
You call that food?
You ate them.
Did you eat them? You call that food?
I got no choice.
I'm sick of you already.
I can't believe you.
I got no choice.
You got no choice?
Get away from me!
Please! No!
Get in there.
Get your hands off me!
Get away from me!
Fuck you.
I'm sick of you.
LARRY: What's the matter with
you up there, you animals?
What?
MAN: Come on.
You animals.
This son of a bitch
just called me an animal.
Hey, you.
Come on, Jack.
I'm gonna get a hold of that dog
and I'm gonna eat him for lunch.
You hear what I'm saying?
You hear me, Larry?
Larry?
LARRY: Crazy animal!
Who's an animal?
Your mother's an animal,
you son of a bitch.
You're gonna find your dog dead
in the hallway tomorrow, you bum.
IRMA: Jake, I can't take it!
The whole block,
people could hear you.
I'll kill the whole family.
Sit down, relax.
Be calm.
You break anything in there,
I'm gonna kill you.
I swear to God, I'm gonna come
in there and I'm gonna kill you.
IRMA: Yeah, sure.
You want to calm down?
(SHOUTING)
(CHUCKLING)
What? What'd I do?
Come on, honey.
Let's be friends.
Truce, all right?
IRMA: It's not all right!
You can't.
I'm telling you,
you can't fucking eat and
drink like an animal,
put up with this fucking braciola.
You can't do this.
I'm telling you.
Forget about the Reeves thing.
You got a million
other fights coming up.
You just can't keep doing this.
What's wrong?
Something's the matter, I know.
What's bothering me?
My hands.
Your hands?
What about them?
I got these small hands.
I got a little girl's hands.
I got them, too.
What's the difference?
You know what that means?
No matter how big I get, no matter
who I fight, no matter what I do,
I ain't never
gonna fight Joe Louis.
Yeah, that's right. He's a
heavyweight, you're a middleweight.
We know that.
I ain't ever gonna get a chance
to fight the best there is.
And you know something?
I'm better than him.
I ain't never gonna get a chance.
You're asking me what's wrong.
But you're crazy to even think
about something like that.
I mean, he's a fucking heavyweight,
you're a middleweight.
It's impossible,
it'll never happen.
So why go crazy thinking about it?
It's not normal.
Do me a favor.
Yeah, what?
I want you to hit me in the face.
What?
Forget about it.
Joey, I want you to hit me in the face.
Go ahead.
Go ahead, take your best shot.
I said forget about it.
I ain't doing it.
Come on, we have
fights all the time.
What, are you worried now you're
gonna hit me in the face?
Hit me in the face. Go ahead.
No.
What, are you afraid?
Afraid of what?
Come on, don't be a little faggot.
Come on, hit me.
I ain't a faggot.
Take your best shot, then.
Come on, Jack,
you gotta be a real jerk.
You want me to
punch you in the face.
Hey. Joey.
Did I not tell you just to do it?
Now, I'm telling you,
you gotta do it.
I ain't hitting you.
Hey, I'm your older brother, Joey.
I'm telling you something.
I know what you said.
I ain't doing it.
I don't care if you get mad.
Fucking nut.
I'm not doing it.
I don't have any gloves, anyway.
What am I gonna hit
you with, the table?
Use that over there.
What?
That's right, use that.
(EXHALES)
Wrap it around your hand. How
many times I gotta tell you?
Not too many more.
Go ahead.
All right, go ahead.
You want me to hit you?
I want you to hit me
with everything you got.
I want you to fucking
lay me out. Go ahead.
You sure? All right.
Yeah, go ahead.
Harder.
Yeah?
You throw a punch like
you take it up the ass.
Come on, harder.
Harder. Harder.
That's hard, you fuck.
What do you want?
Take it off. Take it off.
Oh, come on, you want to stop now.
That's enough with that.
Take it off.
Come on. Come on.
Don't fuck around.
A girl, huh?
I'm gonna smack you again.
Throw it again.
That's enough.
Go ahead.
I said that's enough.
Harder. Harder.
No. Your fucking cuts are
opening and everything.
What are you trying to prove?
What does it prove?
Hey, Vito.
Joey, what's what?
Jake, you're looking good.
How you doing?
JAKE: Joey,
come here.
He looks mad, huh?
I spoke to him yesterday.
I don't know.
You told them to come up here?
Answer me when I talk to you.
Yeah, why? I can't have
my friends up here?
I heard this fucker
didn't win the fight.
Take it easy.
Don't ever bring them up here again.
You hear me?
(BELL CLANGS)
Come on.
They look like two fags up there.
(GRUNTS)
(BELL CLANGS)
Joey, we're gonna go.
I'll call you tomorrow.
Hey, Jake, watch you
don't hurt yourself.
How's your wife?
ls everything okay?
Listen, anybody bothers you,
you let me know. Okay?
Yeah. Wave.
They're your friends. What
the fuck is wrong with you?
You gotta make
a fucking jerk out of me.
They only came up here
'cause Tommy told them to
come up and try to help us.
What's the matter with you? Help who?
What's the matter with you?
(PANTING)
How are they gonna help me?
What, by taking my money?
Is that what you're talking about?
Taking my money?
I'm in here breaking
my ass, not them.
Don't ever bring them up
here again, you hear me?
Come on, what are you, a jerk?
I'm a jerk?
You're a fucking asshole.
What the fuck, you hit me?
Yeah, yeah, you fucker, try this.
Maybe you can't?
Motherfuck
(RADIO PLAYING JAZZ)
Hey, Mike, give me a Coke.
Shove off. You're gonna
go to the dance?
JAKE: Who's that girl?
JOEY: Which one? The one
I was talking to? Yeah.
The blonde?
Yeah.
Vickie.
Where's she from?
She's from the neighborhood.
She's a neighborhood girl.
What's her last name?
Vickie, that's all I know.
They call her Vickie.
She knows them?
She knows them. They know her.
She comes to the pool every day,
and everybody knows each other,
you know how that shit works.
She go with them?
She don't go with nobody.
She's 15 years old.
Where the fuck's she gonna go?
Where you gonna take her?
Copacabana?
JAKE: I heard there was
a girl that he went with,
that was a very beautiful,
young girl, blonde.
That's not her?
JOEY: I doubt it very much.
What are you thinking about anyway?
She ain't the kind of girl you
just fuck and forget about.
Joey, how many times
I gotta tell you,
why you always cursing
when I'm talking to you?
Don't do it around me.
Do it around your friends.
It's a thing. Just don't
do it to me, that's all.
She's not the kind of girl
you bang and forget about.
She's not like that.
You got to spend time with
her, get involved, you know.
Did you bang her?
No.
Tell me the truth.
I just told you the truth.
I tell you the truth the first time.
You don't have to ask me again.
I never do that.
I always tell you the truth.
If I didn't, you would know.
I took her out a couple times.
You went with her and you
didn't try to fuck her?
I try to fuck anything,
you know that.
But she didn't go with it?
She didn't go for it.
Naturally.
She knew better.
What do you mean,
"She knew better"?
She knew you were an animal.
She knew it was no good to go with.
Her whole reputation
would be ruined.
I thought he was
talking to you, Vickie.
That's the same guy?
Yeah, it's the same guy.
I gotta break his legs.
He was over here yesterday.
He was here yesterday?
You missed him.
I was up at the house yesterday,
and he was over here.
You stay in the neighborhood,
you'll find him.
No, I'll catch him.
JAKE: Friends, they're in a huddle.
Big business meeting.
They come by the pool, they sit
around and talk. Big deals.
They make sure she can hear.
Like the big man.
Get the fuck out of here.
Don't get your hair wet.
JAKE: Big shot.
I'll get him alone in a back
room, smack him around,
no more big shot without his gun.
Real tough guys.
They're all tough guys.
JOEY: What are you thinking about?
Keep looking.
Where the fuck you going?
You're dead. You're married.
You're a married man.
It's all over.
Leave the young girls for me.
JAKE: Big shot.
Come on, let's get out of here.
Come on, you gonna stay here all night?
We'll never get...
Where the hell do you think
you're going at this hour?
What are you? A cop?
I'm going out. Business.
You fucking worm. You
go out, I'm going out.
Hey, do what you're gonna do.
What do I care?
Run out!
See if I care!
I'm not gonna be here
when you get back.
You fucking bunch of guineas.
You're always hanging out together.
JAKE: Why don't you
just stop already?
Why don't you fucking stop?
You're not going on business.
IRMA: You're going to
suck each other off.
JAKE: Why don't you
have some respect?
The whole building hears you.
Suck him! Suck him, baby!
Larry! Hey, Larry.
(DOG BARKING)
Now you got something to talk
about with that fucking dog
and this one up here.
Fucking juke. Why don't you hit
her in the head with a bat, huh?
Don't call her names.
She's still my wife.
Yeah, but how much abuse
you want to take?
I hit her enough.
What am I supposed to do?
Go ahead, just leave me
here like a dog!
You and your fucking ass...
You, too, you... Go out!
What's the matter with you, huh?
What's the fucking matter with you?
You're gonna leave me here?
I couldn't give a shit,
you fucking queer!
Faggot! Go stick it
up your... Faggot?
I called you a fag!
(JAZZ MUSIC PLAYING)
Beans.
Jack.
Hey, Beansy got a table in the back.
He said we could sit with them.
Beansy who? Which Beansy?
Beansy who?
Beans, you know,
he's one of the guys.
You'll know when you see him.
She should be over there?
I don't know, but you can
see from there at least.
Come on, let's go.
I don't want to look.
Hello, Joe.
How you doing?
Thanks for the seats.
Hey, what's up?
Nothing. I got trouble with these two
motherfucking greaseballs downstairs.
They got me crazy.
Hello, Father, how you doing?
Hey, Father, what is it?
Father, you want
to get laid? You sure?
(ALL LAUGHING)
JOEY: Father, where you going?
Bless the table.
Give us a shot, will you?
Hey, did you put money
in the basket this week?
You see her right there?
I saw her. I saw her.
Over there?
I saw.
Who are they with?
Go ahead.
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
Get the fuck out!
Get out! Get out! You! Get out.
Get out of here,
you fucking bum, you!
JAKE: Go back where you came from.
Hey, Vickie.
Vickie! Vickie!
Hi, Joey.
How you doing?
I'm all right.
What are you doing?
Nothing much.
That your car?
No. It's my brother's.
Did you ever meet my brother?
No. Is that him?
Yeah. Want to meet him?
All right.
Hey, Jack.
There.
Vickie, this is my brother Jake.
He's gonna be the next champ.
How you doing?
Nice to meet you.
Nice car.
You like that car?
It's nice.
Where you from?
Around here.
You wanna go for a ride?
All right. You gotta
give me a few minutes.
I have to change, okay?
All right? All right, I'll
pack it all up. All right.
I'll be over here.
Okay.
Move over.
I never played this game before.
Go ahead. It's the only
way you're gonna learn.
Go ahead. Here, I'll
show you how to do it.
That's right. That's right.
Like this?
Hit it? Just hit. That's it.
Nice.
Hit the little one.
JAKE: You see it?
No.
(LAUGHING)
What does that mean?
It means the game is over.
Come on, let's go.
(KNOCK ON DOOR)
JAKE: Daddy?
Dad?
Come on in.
Probably went shopping or something.
Let me see over here.
Daddy?
Yeah, must have gone shopping.
Sit down.
Want something to eat?
VICKIE: No.
You sure?
Mmm-hmm.
Why don't you sit over here?
Sit a little closer.
You're so far away, like on
the other side of the room.
Tell you something.
Come here.
Sit over here.
Come on.
That's better.
No. Thank you anyway.
Here's your water.
Want to see the rest of the place?
All right.
I bought it for my father.
I bought the building.
Yeah?
From fighting?
Yeah.
What else?
This is the dining room.
And some bird.
It was a bird. He's
dead now, I think.
Sit down.
That's me and my brother.
We're fooling around.
I know.
You look good, though.
What are you smiling about?
I don't know.
You know how beautiful you are?
Anybody ever tell you that before?
Yeah, they tell you all the time.
ANNOUNCER: Sugar Ray Robinson
and Jake La Motta
in Detroit for their second fight.
The undefeated Sugar Ray defeated Jake
at Madison Square Garden last October.
You can see the contrast
in their styles.
The speedy Ray Robinson up on
his toes, the dancing master.
La Motta, the brawler, moves in
with a punch most of the time.
Now he's hurt Robinson.
(PEOPLE CHEERING)
La Motta coming at Robinson again.
Both hands at the head, a
left and a right to the jaw.
A hard left hand to the body,
thrown by La Motta.
(BELL CLANGS)
Round eight, and it's anybody's
fight at this point. Ten-rounder.
La Motta drives
both hands to the head.
Hurts Robinson again, hooks the left
hand to the jaw, a right to the body.
Robinson comes back
with a right on the nose.
La Motta drives him
across the ring.
A left and right to the head,
a hard left into the body,
and Robinson is
driven out of the ring
for the first knockdown
of his career.
This is the nearest
Robinson has been to a loss.
The fight nears its end.
La Motta has taken
charge of the fight.
The undefeated Sugar Ray, his
winning ways are in jeopardy.
La Motta coming at him again.
La Motta feigning left hand.
(BELL CLANGS)
After 10 rounds, Judge Rossi,
8-2, La Motta.
(PEOPLE WHISTLING)
Judge Murphy, 7-3, La Motta.
ANNOUNCER: La Motta has
won the fight.
A unanimous decision
for the Bronx Bull.
Jake La Motta handing
Sugar Ray Robinson
his first loss as a professional,
and Robinson doesn't like it.
With this sudden victory, La Motta broke
what was considered the impossible,
the invincible Sugar Ray's record.
La Motta has proved himself
a great fighter,
and he shouldn't be denied a
shot at the middleweight crown.
You sure we should be doing this?
Come here.
You said never to touch
you before a fight.
Come here before
I give you a beating.
You said I couldn't. You've
been good for two weeks.
Come here.
Touch my boo-boos.
"Boo-Ba?"
Boo-boo.
Give the boo-boo a kiss.
Make it better.
Take off my pants.
Jake.
You know how to take off my pants?
Now, take off the rest.
You made me promise
not to get you excited.
Go ahead. Do it.
Take off your panties.
I like the gym smell.
I like the smell of the gym.
All right, all right.
Get off.
No more. That's it.
I gotta fight Robinson.
I can't fool around.
(MOANS)
What are you doing?
What are you doing to me?
ANNOUNCER: Jake La Motta and Sugar Ray
Robinson meet for the third time.
These men are unique,
becoming classic rivals.
These two men,
fierce, powerful fighters.
Dangerous, so much so that no
other fighter will go near them,
and so they fight each other
three weeks apart.
They've each won one,
and they'll probably fight
again the way it looks now.
They go to close
quarters at the bell.
(BELL CLANGS)
Round seven, with Sugar
Ray well ahead on points.
La Motta may need a knockout.
There's a left hook to the jaw,
and Robinson is down for the
second time in his career.
He was down in the last fight, too.
La Motta watches Sugar Ray take
the count from the referee.
Robinson trying to get up.
REFEREE: Seven, eight...
He's up on his feet now,
and the referee is wiping off his gloves.
He is stunned.
La Motta comes at him.
Despite being knocked down,
Robinson is well ahead on points.
He hooks a left to the jaw, left and
a right to the head by Robinson.
(BELL CLANGS)
RING ANNOUNCER: Your attention, fans.
Judge Joe Lanahan scores it 8-1,
one even in favor
of Sugar Ray Robinson.
(CROWD BOOS)
ANNOUNCER: A big vote
for Sugar Ray Robinson.
RING ANNOUNCER: ...of 6-2,
and two even for the winner
by unanimous decision,
Sugar Ray Robinson.
They only gave him
that fucking decision
'cause he's going in
the Army next week.
That's the only reason.
I knocked him down. I don't
know what else I gotta do?
I don't know what I gotta do.
You won and they robbed you.
They're miserable because their mothers
take it up the fucking ass. That's why.
I've done a lot of bad things, Joey.
Maybe it's coming back to me.
(KNOCK ON DOOR)
Who knows? I'm a jinx maybe.
Who the hell knows?
Okay. Forget about all that shit.
This was your shot.
They robbed us.
JOEY: They out and out robbed us!
Jake, it's Vickie.
You want to talk to her?
No, I don't want to talk to nobody.
Joey, take her home.
JOEY: All right.
Jack, you're going
to be all right?
Yeah, I'll be all right.
Are you sure?
Yeah.
Make sure she's all right.
All right.
Don't ever do that Janiro bullshit again.
No more deals like that.
You hear what I'm saying?
What are you talking about?
What am I talking about?
Look at that. 168 pounds.
Stop eating. What's this
with the smart-ass?
I told you I didn't want
to do it in the first place.
Didn't I tell you that?
No, you didn't say that.
You're the one who told me
you could get down to 155 pounds.
Where'd I get it? What, did I
pull it out of the fucking air?
JAKE: I don't know if I'm
gonna make it down to 155.
If I'm lucky, I make it to 160.
And on top of that, you
sign me for a fight at 155,
and if I don't make
the 155, I lose $15,000?
JOEY: That's right.
(EXCLAIMS)
You're supposed to be a manager.
You're supposed to know
what you're doing.
I did just what I wanted to do.
That's what I'm worried about.
You did exactly...
You want a title shot?
What are you talking about?
Do you want a title shot?
What am I, at a circus over here?
I ask him, he's got more sense about this.
What are you doing?
You've been killing yourself
for three years now, right?
There's nobody's
left for you to fight.
Everybody's afraid to fight you.
Okay. Along comes this kid Janiro,
he don't know any better.
He's a young kid, up-and-coming.
He'll fight anybody.
Good. You fight him.
Bust his hole. Tear him apart. Right?
What are you worried about?
What's the biggest thing
you got to worry about?
The weight? I'm worried
about the weight.
You worried about the weight?
What are we arguing about for?
I just said the weight.
Okay, let's say you lose
because of your weight,
are they gonna think you're
not as tough as you were?
You're not the same fighter?
Good. They'll match you
with all those guys
they were afraid of matching
you with before. What happens?
You'll kill them, and they
gotta give you a title shot.
Bring me coffee, please.
Why? There's nobody else.
Nobody's left.
Who they gonna give it to?
Coffee.
In a minute.
You listening to me?
Please, honey, bring me the coffee.
All right.
How long I gotta wait?
JOEY: Are you listening?
Now, let's say you win,
you beat Janiro,
which you definitely
should beat him.
Right? Right?
Yeah. Yeah.
They still got to give
you a shot at the title.
You know why?
Why?
'Cause the same thing as before.
There's nobody left. There
ain't nobody around.
They gotta give you the shot.
You understand?
If you win, you win. If
you lose, you still win.
There's no way you can lose,
and you do it on your own,
just the way you wanted to do,
without any help from anybody.
You understand?
Just get down to 155
pounds, you fat bastard.
You stop eating.
What's the problem?
Stop eating, that's all.
You can do it.
You don't understand anything.
You understand that?
VICKIE: You know, Joey's right.
This Janiro's
an up-and-coming fighter.
He's good-looking, he's popular,
you beat him now...
Excuse me, excuse me,
what do you mean good-looking?
I'm not saying good-looking, I'm
saying popular. If you win...
Who are you to say about
good-looking and popular?
I'm not saying anything. I'm
just telling you Joey's right.
What are you?
An authority or what?
Nothing.
Get out of here. Take the
baby and get out of here.
Everybody, all of a sudden,
is an authority about this.
Where did she find out he's
good-looking, first of all?
LENORE: She didn't mean nothing.
Who asked you?
You gonna start with me now?
When people are talking,
you don't interrupt.
It's none of your business,
especially if it's
my brother and his wife.
They got nothing to do with you.
Now get out of here. Go inside.
Get in and take the baby inside.
Come on, let's leave
the grouches here, okay?
Come on.
Change her diapers.
Can't you see? She's gonna... Look,
she's gonna cry. She stinks.
You make her cry.
I'm gonna make you cry.
LENORE: Yeah.
They're a couple of babies.
JOEY: 155 pounds.
Let's go to the training camp.
No distractions, no wives,
no phone calls,
nobody around to bother you.
All right? Your usual
schedule, your usual diet...
Joey, Joey, listen,
I want to ask you something.
When I'm away, you ever notice
anything funny going on with her?
With who? Vickie?
Yeah.
Like what?
What do you think I mean?
No, I don't notice anything.
I want you to keep an eye on her.
All right?
For what, Jack?
She don't do anything wrong.
I want you to keep an eye on
her while I'm away. All right?
You'll just start
trouble for nothing.
I'm telling you,
you're cracking up.
Hey, Joey, I got a
reason, all right?
You and I both know any
woman, given the right time,
the right place, the right circumstances,
they'll do anything, right?
I mean, anything's
possible. All right?
Yeah.
Well, you're right.
Yeah, you know?
You're not wrong, but you're
picking on this girl.
'Cause I saw you before,
you're worried about your weight,
you're getting aggravated,
you tell her... What do you...
"Go inside, go inside.
"Who asked you, who asked you?"
Bothering her for that, you're gonna
give her an excuse to go out.
She was talking about a guy.
So?
So what? She was
talking on your behalf.
On my behalf? She was
talking about a pretty kid.
She's saying he's good-looking.
What are you talking about?
So you make him ugly.
What's the difference?
Never mind, never mind, just do it.
All right.
You know what you should do?
Go inside and be nice to her.
Make up with her.
Tell her you're gonna take her out.
We'll go out.
You want to go out before
you go away, don't you?
This way you go away
with a clear head.
You know you took her out, you wined
and dined and had a good time.
All right?
All right.
Where do you want to go?
Out out, you know.
All right.
Listen, though, don't... If you
tell her now, pull her on the side.
Don't say nothing
in front of Lenore.
'Cause I'm not taking her.
It's on your head.
All right.
What, you think
I'm gonna go tell her?
Do what you gotta do.
I am.
MAN: Good evening,
ladies and gentlemen.
It's great to be
back at the Copa lounge.
What a great audience.
Come on, lady, laugh it up.
I laughed when you came in.
(PEOPLE LAUGHING)
But seriously speaking, folks, we
have a special guest with us tonight.
I'd like to introduce the world's
leading middleweight contender,
the Bronx Bull, the Raging Bull,
let's hear it for the great Jake
La Motta, ladies and gentlemen.
What's your name again?
Janet.
Janet, sorry.
I've just been...
It's toast time.
He hits me with a left hook.
No hand, just a hook he had.
(CROWD LAUGHING)
Where are you going?
Going to the bathroom.
SAL: Hey, Vickie.
Hi.
You're looking great.
Joey here? Thanks.
Yeah, they're over there.
Jake's here, too.
That's great.
Listen, I'm over here
with Tommy and
some of the old gang.
You get a chance, come
over and have a drink.
It's a nice night.
SAL: Hello, Jake, how are you?
Hello.
You're not drinking, are you?
Joey, how are you?
JOEY: How you doing, Sal?
Look like you're having
a ball over there.
Yeah.
Listen, I'm over there
with Tommy Como.
Why don't you come over
and have a drink?
Tommy's here.
I didn't even see him come in.
I'll see you later, Joey.
JOEY: Man, that's some suit.
He looks good, huh, Jack?
I thought that was my best joke.
Vito, look who's here.
WOMAN 1: Hi, Vickie.
WOMAN 2: Hi, Vickie.
Hey, Vickie.
How are you, honey?
Good to see you.
Say hello to John. Come on, sit down.
Have a drink.
VICKIE: I can't, I have to get back to Jake.
I just came by to say hello.
All right, honey,
thanks for coming by.
Not a bad kid
that Vickie, you know.
She's with that fucking gorilla.
Must've caught a hundred
beatings off that guy.
(CLEARS THROAT)
What took you so long?
I went by Tommy's table
to say hello.
I saw you say hello to him.
What took you so long?
Nothing. I said hello.
I came back.
What else did he say?
He asked me if I wanted a drink,
I said, "No, Jake and Joey
are over there," and I left.
What were you
talking to Sal before?
He asked me if Joey was here.
I said, "He's over there."
He said, "Tommy's over there. Why
don't you go say hello?" And I did.
Are you interested in him?
No. Why would I be
interested in him?
You sure you're not
Yeah.
In other words, you're
not interested in him
but you could be
interested in somebody?
Jake, don't start, huh?
VICKIE: You're still mad
about some stupid incident?
JAKE: Shut up, or I'm
gonna smack you in the face.
These are from Mr. Como.
Shall I take this?
What?
I'm not through with it.
Okay.
These are the jokes, folks.
I'll tell you the truth.
Hi. How are you?
Bald-headed fag.
Hey, Joey.
Tommy, thanks for the drinks.
How are you, Joey?
How are you?
TOMMY: Where's Jake?
He's over there.
He don't wanna come.
Call him. If you call
him, he'll come.
All right.
All right, I'll be right back.
JOEY: Here he comes.
What is it? You don't
call anybody anymore.
We never see you anymore,
for crying out loud.
Yeah, you never come around anymore.
You can't even make a call?
What is it?
I'm busy. I'm going away fighting.
I'm busy.
I'm out of town a lot.
Busy. Busy. Busy.
Look at him, taking me seriously.
I'm only kidding you.
What a fucking kid. That's the
best fucking fighter around.
Jake.
How you doing?
The mulignanes, forget about it,
they're all afraid to fight you.
Okay.
How you feeling? All right?
I'm all right.
Good? Strong?
Strong. Yeah, I'm doing okay.
That Janiro's got to
watch his ass, right?
I think he should.
Last three, four times, I won
nothing but money with the guy.
Well, he's no piece of cake.
That's a good fighter.
SAL: Very attractive guy,
all the girls like him.
No marks. Clean.
Jake, am I wrong or did
you gain a few pounds?
Yeah, a few pounds. I'll knock
it off right away. No problem.
Right off, right off.
Well, look, let me ask
you something.
I'm just talking,
now, just talking.
I come to you and I'm telling you
that I'm gonna bet
a lot of money on you
in this fight with Janiro, right?
Yeah.
What would you tell me?
What could you say to me?
I would say bet everything you got.
Everything?
Everything.
'Cause I'm going to
open his hole like this.
Excuse my French, girls.
I'm gonna make him suffer.
I'm gonna make his mother
wish she never had him.
There something personal?
Make him look like dog meat.
What? Did he say
something in the papers?
No, he's a nice kid.
He's a pretty kid, too.
I mean, I don't know,
I got a problem with
if I should I fuck
him or fight him?
Crazy. Fuck him or fight him.
You're really liable to
get fucked with this kid.
Watch out.
By who?
SAL: Janiro.
You mean, you want me
to get him to fuck you?
Me? No, I don't want him to fuck me.
Yeah.
I could do that easily.
SAL: How you gonna do that?
'Cause I get you both in the ring,
and I'll give you
both a fucking beating,
and you both can fuck each other.
I'll get all full of blood.
You're used to that.
TOMMY: Come on, drink up. That's
ginger ale, Jake. Come on.
Jake, good luck.
Good luck, Jake.
Hey, Vick.
Vickie.
What?
You awake?
No.
Can you hear me?
What?
You ever think of anybody else
when we're in bed?
What do you mean?
You know, like, when we make love.
Nobody. I love you.
How come you said
that thing about Janiro?
What did I say?
You said he had a pretty face.
I never noticed his face.
Well, how come you
said that, then?
I don't even know what I said.
I don't even know
what he looks like.
Go to sleep.
(PEOPLE CHEERING)
He ain't pretty no more.
ANNOUNCER: And the winner
by unanimous decision,
in 10 rounds, Jake La Motta.
Give me a little piece of ice,
just a sliver, just for my tongue.
No water.
Come on, I'm dying.
Fucking hard-on.
Four pounds.
Keep working.
Cut the bullshit.
Joey, I saw him fight with
Janiro, I couldn't believe it.
He destroyed this guy. It
was absolutely incredible.
He knocked his nose from one
side of his face to the other.
Fucking thing was hanging off.
MAN: Joey, who you fighting next?
Will you tell me who
you're gonna fight next?
We never talked about it... You
know he's away at training camp.
From all I've seen, they gotta
give him that title shot.
Jackie Curtie, Joey.
You should know each other.
Hi, Joey, pleasure. Heard a
lot of nice things about you.
We're gonna get
the title shot, too.
I'm sure. Man, I like your brother.
Made lot of money on him.
Yeah, probably more than
he did, that's for sure.
JACKIE: Made some nice cabbage
on the Oscar Jackson fight.
MAN: Whatever happened to Oscar?
Ever see him anymore or...
He's punchy. He probably died.
Who the fuck cares?
Make yourselves comfortable.
That's a beautiful table.
Worst table in the house.
And he's complaining to me.
It's a beautiful table.
JACKIE: He's working downtown, big building.
Works in the elevator.
Happened to be there the other day.
I'm not Italian.
I don't care.
Took me right up.
That Oscar's always a stand-up guy.
Joey, he did you a lot of good.
Who's talking?
Gave your brother
a hell of a fight, too.
MAN: Yeah, Mickey,
Cutty Sark and water, huh?
Excuse me one minute.
Are you going to come back, Joey?
Come on back. Okay.
MAN: Hey, Joe.
Hey, Joey.
Something's happening.
They're having a problem.
You're worried about it?
VICKIE: I'm just sitting
there ordering a drink.
Shut up. Just shut up.
Both of you are the same.
You know that?
I feel like I'm a prisoner.
I can't walk.
I look at somebody the
wrong way, I get smacked.
You think you're
right or something,
the way you're fucking yelling?
Yeah, I am right. You're wrong.
No, you're wrong.
Look, I am right. I'm tired
of having to turn around,
having the both of you
up my ass all the time.
You shut up. Don't make me...
No.
Look, I'm tired of
listening to you.
Don't make me get
nuts in this place.
I'm not wrong.
And what am I supposed to do?
I'm 20 years old,
I gotta go home and sleep
by myself every night?
What the fuck did you marry him for?
'Cause I love him.
You do?
Yeah, I love him, but
what am I supposed to do,
this guy don't
even want to fuck me?
He's just been
a contender too long.
He'll be all right as
soon as he gets his shot,
and then everything will be okay.
You won't have to go fucking
running around when he does.
Jake is never gonna be a champ.
Too many people hate him.
And you're drinking with them.
And I'm gonna finish my drink,
and I'm gonna have a good time.
I'm doing it. Now, what are you...
Get your stuff.
I just said you ain't staying
here, get your stuff.
You're making an asshole out of my brother.
Get your stuff.
Joey, come on.
Shut up!
Shut up! Mind your fucking
business and shut up.
You're taking this all wrong, Joey.
I said shut up!
Come on, what's the matter with you?
There's nothing going on here.
This is innocent. We're
only having a few drinks.
Relax, relax.
Come on, you know better than that.
All right.
It's all calm now.
Just relax, come on.
We've been friends a long time.
JOEY: I'm just upset.
It's my brother's wife.
Joey, there's nothing
going on over here.
I'm sorry. I really am.
Good friends,
we can straighten this...
Nothing going on?
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
JOEY: Fucking hard-on!
Get up! Get up!
I'll rip your fucking head off!
SAL: What's the matter here, Joey?
What the fuck are you doing?
Come on. Come on.
Come on.
Fucking cunt.
Stop it. I'll sock
your fucking eyes out!
MAN: What are you, nuts?
Don't mention it, Tommy.
You do what you do,
we do what we gotta do.
Don't mention no names.
You're wrong, Joe.
He's wrong. Don't fucking
send him to jail.
I said get out of here.
Take it easy. Come on,
now, take it easy.
(PEOPLE CLAMORING)
TOMMY: A lot of years between you.
You done a lot of things together.
Now, I understand, Joey,
it was your brother's wife,
but you don't raise your hands.
You don't create a scene like
that in a place like that.
Now, we've heard everybody's
point of view here,
and we're gonna forget about it.
I shouldn't forget about it, but
we're gonna forget about it.
What I want you to
do now, you two guys,
I want you to shake hands,
forget this whole thing,
and no grudges.
That's the most important
thing, no grudges.
Now, come on, shake hands.
It's all right with me if it's
all right with you. All right?
I only wish this thing
never happened, Tommy.
We all wish it never happened.
We get over it.
Salvy, let me talk
with him alone a minute.
Yeah.
All right, I'll see you Monday,
Tuesday or something. All right?
What are you, fucking nuts?
You're killing me.
Aside from everything else,
Joey, the family all right?
Yeah, they're fine.
Everybody's fine.
So, what is it with you?
You can't talk?
I'm talking, what do you mean?
I don't know. Why you got
this funny attitude, Joey?
I can't figure you out.
What is it with all
the quick answers?
"Yeah, yeah,
they're all right. Yeah."
You want to get out of here
fast or something? What?
No, it's not like that, Tommy.
It's just, you know, all the
aggravation and everything.
All the fights and all.
Listen to me.
Now, Jake...
The guy's become an embarrassment.
He's embarrassing me
with certain people,
and I'm looking very bad.
I can't deliver a kid from
my own goddamn neighborhood.
What is it with him?
Why does he have to make
it so hard on himself?
For Christ's sakes, he comes to
me, I make it easier for him.
The man's got a head of rock.
You know, it's hard to explain, Tommy.
He's...
Jack respects you.
I mean, he don't even
say hello to anybody.
You, he talks to.
He likes you.
It's just that when he gets
something on his mind,
you know, he's got a hard head.
He likes to do things his own way.
I mean, Jesus Christ could
come off the cross sometimes,
he don't give a fuck. He's
gonna do what he wants to do.
He wants to make it
on his own, you know?
Thinks he can make it on his own.
Make it on his own?
He thinks he's gonna walk in there
and become champion on his own?
Huh? Huh?
He's crazy.
You know he's nuts.
Yeah, he's crazy.
And he's got no respect for nobody.
He doesn't listen to nobody.
That's not crazy.
He respects you.
He doesn't respect anybody.
Now, you do this for
me, you understand?
You tell him.
I don't care how colorful
he is or how great he is,
he could beat all the Sugar Ray Robinsons
and the Tony Janiros in the world,
but he ain't gonna get
a shot at that title.
Not without us, he ain't.
Now, you're a smart kid.
You go there.
You tell him.
Son of a bitch.
$20 shoes.
Aren't you gonna ask
me what happened?
Huh?
What's the matter?
(EXCLAIMS)
What's wrong?
I remember when I met her here.
Who?
Vickie.
Why? What's the matter?
What'd she do now?
I know she's doing something.
I just want to catch her once.
Just once.
Hey, Jack. Want to
do yourself a favor?
Bust her fucking hole.
Throw her out.
Either that, or live with her
and let her ruin your life.
'Cause that's what's happening.
I mean, how much could you take?
How much shit could you take?
So, what did that guy say?
He gave me the old "good
news, bad news" routine.
Good news is you're gonna
get the shot at the title.
Hmm.
And the bad news is they want you
to do the old flip-flop for them.
(SCOFFS)
So what else is new?
What'd you expect?
You didn't know that was coming?
You win some, you lose some.
This one, we'll lose.
(CHUCKLES)
Billy Fox, 173 and 3/4 pounds.
Jake La Motta, 167.
MAN: I guess you've heard
by now about a lot of
the stuff that's going
around, a lot of rumors.
Matter of fact, a short time
ago, you were a big favorite.
Then all of a sudden,
you're a 12-5 underdog,
and people are talking.
It's as simple as that.
That's funny,
I never heard anything.
It's not good. As a matter of fact,
the bets are off on this one.
Nothing going in this one.
Matter of fact, smart money is saying that
you're getting ready to hit the tank.
That's bullshit.
Yeah, that's bullshit.
You got any money you want to bet?
Come on.
No, I'll take the action. You bet
it on Fox, 'cause I'm gonna win.
There's no way I'm going down.
I don't go down for nobody.
That's what I wanted to hear.
I want you to know that.
All right, bye.
All right, Colonel.
Okay, that's it.
You came down here just for that nonsense?
That was it?
That was it.
(BELL DINGING)
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen.
Welcome to the Madison Square
Garden feature attraction.
In this corner,
weighing 175 pounds...
Commissioner, how about a picture?
Fellas, can we get
a picture over here?
...the undefeated Billy Fox.
(CROWD CHEERING)
Hi, Steve. Your brother
get out of the hospital?
He's all right.
Did he get out?
Good, good.
Charlie, let me sit
over there, will you?
Yeah, sure.
Tommy, what's the matter?
Everything all right?
It's all right, yeah.
REFEREE: Touch gloves now.
Come out boxing.
Five seconds, Alex.
(BELL DINGS)
(GRUNTING)
(CROWD SHOUTING)
Come on. Stand up.
Come on, stand up.
Why don't you go on and
hit me, you fucking bum.
Come on.
What are you doing, Jake?
Come on, box him.
(BELL DINGS)
What the fuck's
the matter with you?
Whoa! Whoa!
What do you think you're
doing out there? Huh?
A little slow, that's all.
What are you doing out there?
Take it easy, take it easy. He'll
be all right. Little slow.
He'll make it up.
What do you want?
God damn it.
Come on, pick it up a little, Jake.
I'm sorry.
(BELL DINGS)
MAN 1: Come on, Jake!
I got some money on you.
MAN 2: Tank job!
MAN 3: Hit him back, you burn!
Come on!
Fucking bum.
You're taking a dive in the fourth?
MAN 2: You bastard!
MAN 4: Pocket your dirty money!
MAN 5: Jake! Fucking Jake!
MAN 2: Come on, you phony bastard!
Take him!
(CROWD BOOING)
JOEY: What the fuck are you waiting for?
Stop the fight, you jerk.
And you standing there.
Fucking go down, will you?
ANNOUNCER: The referee stops this bout
at two minutes, 26 seconds...
Phony! Fake!
...In the fourth round.
The winner by technical
knockout, and still undefeated,
Billy Fox.
(SOBBING)
Don't fight anymore.
It's a free country.
JAKE: What'd I do? What'd I do?
What'd I do?
(SNIFFLES)
Get out of here!
It's all right, Jake.
It's all right.
Why did I do it?
(DOOR OPENS)
They got some balls. Some balls.
I take the dive. What
more do they want, huh?
They want me to go down, too?
Well, I ain't going down. I
ain't going down for nobody.
Why don't you do me a favor, huh?
Do something for me.
Just put your hands up. I
want to show you something.
Put your hands up.
What the fuck is
so hard about that?
That's what I want to know.
Hey, Joey. You don't understand.
You don't understand.
I had to fight a bum. He's a bum.
I fought the guy.
I tapped him like that.
All of a sudden, he's like this all
over the place. What am I gonna do?
You didn't have to fucking
pick him up and help him.
What am I gonna do? If I don't pick
him up, then what am I gonna do?
I'm gonna be in worse trouble.
I don't know.
"Purse was withheld."
Look at this.
"Purse was withheld
pending D.A.'s probe."
Look at that. Look how
they make me look, huh?
Like a bum, like a mammalucco.
A what?
Like the mammalucco of the year.
Tommy ain't gonna forget us.
You're gonna get your shot
as long as he don't die.
As long as who don't die?
Tommy.
What are you talking about?
So, in other words, Tommy
ain't gonna forget you.
You're gonna get your shot
if he don't die and all.
You gotta make sure the
guy stays alive. Why?
He got a disease or something?
No. I'm just saying. You know,
I'm like, kidding, like.
Well, what's wrong with him?
ls something wrong with him?
Ain't nothing wrong with him.
I mean, that's the only way you
wouldn't get it, is if he dies.
He wouldn't be able to... Well,
why you talking like that?
JOEY: What do you want me
to do? It's an outdoor arena.
What do you want to do,
fight in the rain?
It's a stadium.
You waited this long.
You can wait longer.
Joey, you want to wait 24 hours? I
don't want to wait no 24 hours.
I don't either, but we
gotta, so we'll wait.
Hello.
You guys want to stop now.
Get off the phone with them.
Why do you give them the satisfaction?
Fucking reporters.
Get off the phone with them. He
don't want to talk to nobody.
How many times do we have to tell you?
You hear him yelling?
There's enough confusion up here.
Please don't call.
No comment. Right.
Thank you. Bye.
Pains in the asses.
I don't believe them.
Why do you give them
the satisfaction?
Why don't you just hang up on them?
That's all.
I'm gonna get something to eat.
What do you want to eat?
I don't want nothing.
Huh?
Well, eat something.
You gotta eat something.
Can't go without eating.
Eat a steak. You chew it, you spit it out,
you'll still make the weight tomorrow.
You worried about that, huh?
All right, I'll order a steak.
At least if you want it, it's here.
You don't want it, do
whatever you want with it.
Go ahead.
Vickie, what do you want?
Order me a piece of cake.
That's all you want
is a piece of cake?
Why don't you get a cheeseburger,
get some French fries.
Better for you, it's
like a whole meal.
Yeah, that's good. That's good.
Order me one of those.
You'll have something good to eat.
JAKE: Wait a minute.
What do you want to eat?
Since when did you
order one of those?
That's what I want.
It's a free country.
You order what you want,
don't let nobody influence you.
I'm not telling her what to eat.
I was just suggesting.
What are you telling her what...
I'm not telling her.
I don't...
Personally, I don't give
a fuck what she eats.
Well, what are you telling her for?
Order me a cheeseburger.
Just order a cheeseburger,
that's all.
What are you guys doing so long, anyway?
How long does this thing take to do?
Forty seconds.
Forty seconds is no good. You
gotta do it in 30 seconds.
If we gotta stitch him up,
that's how much time.
(KNOCK ON DOOR)
Jack, get up!
What?
Somebody's here to see you.
Hey, Jack. Hey,
Tommy, how you doing?
How are you?
Say hello to Charlie. Charlie!
Jake, how are you? Good, Charlie.
Good to see you.
Lots of luck.
Thank you.
How you feeling?
I'm feeling all right,
Tommy. Thank you.
Are you feeling good?
I'm feeling as good
as I'm gonna feel.
I gotta get in there and fight,
then I'll know how I'm gonna feel.
All right. Now, we just came by
to wish you luck and all that.
Thanks.
You need anything?
No.
You sure? Nothing?
No. No thank you, Tommy.
All right. Take care.
Good luck. God bless you.
All right, Tommy, thank you.
You'll be all right.
Yeah, I will.
See you later, everybody.
Vickie, goodbye.
VICKIE: Tommy, wait.
JOEY: Tommy, we really
appreciate your coming.
TOMMY: Yeah.
You know that.
It was really nice of you, you know?
And we really appreciate it.
Come on, Joey, anytime, anytime.
A time like this is
very important to him.
Anytime.
I just want to say goodbye.
So long, honey.
TOMMY: I want you to take good
care of that guy, all right?
VICKIE: I'll take care of him.
Joey, any little thing,
I want you to call me.
He's very nervous? Ka-boom, call.
Goodbye, honey.
Would you look at
that face? What a face.
Can you believe that girl, huh?
Look at that beauty, just
as beautiful as ever.
Hey, at least you look good.
Bye-bye, Tommy.
So long, everybody.
So long, Tommy.
JAKE: Vickie.
Vickie.
Hey, come here.
Come here a minute.
What's all that about?
All what?
You know what I'm talking about.
What was that all about?
What happened?
I don't know.
I just said goodbye.
All of a sudden you're
so friendly with him.
I just said goodbye. What
do you want me to do?
You don't do that. You say hello. You say goodbye.
That's all, you hear?
Whatever.
You hear what I said? You don't
ever have any disrespect for me.
You hear what I said?
Yeah, I hear.
All right, go in there.
Come here. Why don't
you stop that, huh?
Shut up!
Stop it!
Shut up! Shut up! I'll fucking
take care of you later.
Shut up!
I'm disgusted with the two of you.
Get to you later.
Hit the fucking...
That's all.
(CROWD CHEERING)
(BELL DINGING)
ANNOUNCER: For the Middleweight
Championship of the World, 15 rounds.
In this corner, the
very worthy challenger,
weighing in at 158 and 1/4 pounds,
the Bronx Bull, Jake La Motta.
REFEREE: Shake hands and come
out fighting at the bell.
(BELL DINGS)
(BELL DINGING)
JOEY: Now finish him off. He's
all stupey-eyed and sorry.
MAN: Come on, Jake!
JOEY: Blow on him, he'll
fucking fall right over.
Jack, look at him.
You feel all right?
No way.
He can't continue?
Hey, Commissioner. Come on in,
I'm gonna stop the fight.
(BELL DINGING)
ANNOUNCER: Cerdan,
unable to continue.
The referee has stopped the fight,
and the winner, by a technical
knockout in the 10th round,
and the new Middleweight
Champion of the World,
the Bronx Bull, Jake La Motta.
(ALL CHEERING)
CROWD: Jake! Jake!
Jake! Jake! Jake! Jake!
(INAUDIBLE)
Don't shake that.
Jack, don't shake it like
that, I'm telling you.
It's the worst thing you could do.
(DOOR SHUTS)
You're home.
Hi, Vick.
Hi, Joe.
How's it going?
Hello.
Where were you?
I went out.
What's the matter?
Television won't work.
Where'd you go?
I don't know. Went out, went shopping,
went to my sister's, you know.
What's the matter with you, huh?
What's with this
kissing on the mouth?
I just said, "Hello." Can't
I kiss my sister-in-law?
Ain't the cheek
good enough for you?
I don't even kiss Mom on the
mouth the way you kiss.
All of a sudden
you're like a Romeo.
So, you're not supposed to
kiss your mother on the mouth.
That's what I'm talking about.
How's that?
That looks like something.
Get back. I can't see nothing
with your stomach in the way now.
What are you giving
me dirty looks for?
You're supposed to be a champion.
You eat like there's no tomorrow.
That's it.
Look, go ahead.
Forgot how long it took
you to get to the title.
All the years of hard work, huh?
You forgot.
You're gonna defend it next month.
Keep eating.
Give me dirty looks like I don't
know what I'm talking about?
Hey, Joe, what happened with you
and Salvy at the Copa that time?
When?
When you gave him a beating.
You mean, when I caught his head in
the taxicab door, was banging it,
and smacked him with
a glass and everything?
Yeah.
I told you about that, didn't I?
No.
I never told you?
No, you never told me.
It was no big thing, anyway.
I smacked him on the mouth.
He was drunk, he started some shit.
Had to go downtown, straighten
it all out with Tommy.
It's all forgotten about
supposedly, anyway.
How come you never
told me about it?
Didn't have anything
to do with you.
Had nothing to do with me? No.
Who'd it have something to do with?
Vickie?
Hey, Jack, I just explained the
whole thing to you, didn't I?
Yeah. It was between me and Salvy.
If it had anything to
do with you and Vickie,
I would've told you about it.
That's not what I heard, Joe.
What do you mean, that's
not what you heard?
That's not what I heard.
What'd you hear?
I heard some things.
You heard about me and Salvy...
I heard things, Joey.
Yeah, you heard that I cracked
Salvy all around. What'd you hear?
I heard things, Joey.
I heard things.
What things you heard?
I heard some things.
You heard things. You want to worry?
Don't start that worrying shit.
You know what you
should worry about?
Worry about this
title fight next month.
That's what you should worry about.
Do that.
Christ.
Did Salvy fuck Vickie?
What?
Jack...
Joey...
Don't start your shit.
No, really, don't start.
Joey, I asked you. Didn't I ask
you to keep an eye on her?
And I did keep an eye
on her. Yes, I did.
Then, how come you
gave him a beating?
I told you that.
I told you what that was all about.
Didn't have nothing to do with you.
He thinks he's a wise guy now.
Joey, don't lie to me.
I'm not lying.
What do I look like to you, huh?
Hey, I'm your brother. You're
supposed to believe me.
Don't you trust me?
No, I don't.
You don't.
That's nice.
I don't trust you
when it comes to her.
I don't trust nobody.
Tell me what happened.
I told you exactly what happened.
He got out of line,
I slapped him around,
Tommy straightened it all
out, and it's all over.
You give me that look, Joey.
I got to accept
your answer, you know,
but I'm telling you now,
if I hear anything,
I swear on our mother
I'm gonna kill somebody.
I'm gonna kill somebody, Joey.
Well, go ahead and kill everybody!
You're the tough guy.
Go kill people.
Kill Vickie.
Kill Salvy. Kill Tommy Como. Kill me
while you're at it. What do I care?
You're killing yourself,
the way you eat.
You're a fat fuck.
Look at you.
What do you mean? I don't understand.
What do you mean, kill you? You?
Me! Kill me! Start here!
Kill me first.
Do me a fucking favor! 'Cause
you're driving me crazy!
You're a killer, you're a big shot.
Just kill. You're a killer.
Excuse me, what do you
mean by "you," though?
So? What does that mean?
Don't mean nothing.
Even you don't know
what you meant by "you."
Don't mean nothing.
Joey, that meant something.
You mentioned Tommy, you mentioned
Salvy, you mentioned you.
You included you with them.
You could've said anybody,
but you said you and them.
Yeah, you really let this girl
ruin your life. Look at you.
She really did some job on you. You
know how fucking nuts you are?
Look what she did to you.
You fucked my wife?
What?
How could you ask me
a question like that?
How could you ask me? I'm your brother.
You ask me that?
Where do you get your balls
big enough to ask me that?
Just tell me.
I'm not answering. I'm not gonna
answer that. It's stupid.
You're very smart, Joey.
You give me all these answers, but you
ain't giving me the right answer.
I'm gonna ask you again.
Did you or did you not?
I'm not gonna answer.
It's a sick question,
you're a sick fuck,
and I'm not that sick
that I'm gonna answer it.
I'm not telling you anything.
I'm gonna leave.
If Lenore calls,
tell her I went home.
I'm not staying in this nuthouse with you.
You're a sick bastard.
I feel sorry for you.
I really do.
You know what you should do,
try a little more fucking,
a little less eating.
You won't have troubles
upstairs in your bedroom,
and you won't pick it out
on me and everybody else.
You understand, you fucking wacko?
You're cracking up.
Fucking screwball, you.
(DOOR OPENS)
(DOOR SHUTS)
(CLEARS THROAT)
Where were you?
At my sister's.
Where'd you go after that?
To the movies.
Yeah? What did you see?
Father of the Bride.
How come you didn't
tell me about the Copa?
Hmm?
Tell you what about it?
You know.
How come you didn't
tell me about it?
Why didn't you tell
me about it, huh?
I don't know what
you're talking about.
Why didn't you tell me, huh?
Did you fuck my brother, huh?
Did you?
Get off me, you fat pig!
Did you, huh?
No!
Open the door.
VICKIE: Get away!
Come on, open the door.
I wanna talk to you.
Get away from me.
You're sick.
JAKE: I just want to ask you one thing.
Why did you fuck Joey?
Get away!
Open the door.
No.
(SCREAMS)
Why'd you do it?
Why'd you do it, huh? Why'd you do it?
I didn't do...
Why'd you do it? Why'd you do it?
Why'd you do it?
Why did you fuck them?
Do what? I didn't do anything!
I fucked all of them! What
do you want me to say?
What do you mean you fucked?
Who'd you fuck?
I fucked all of them! Tommy,
Salvy, your brother! All of them.
I sucked your brother's cock!
What do you want me to say?
You sucked his cock?
Yeah, I sucked his cock
and everybody else on the
fucking street, too.
What do you want? You're nothing
but a fat pig, selfish fool.
I'm not fucking with you.
His fucking cock's
bigger than yours, too!
Where you going?
Where you going, you bastard?
You sick animal!
Where you going, you...
VICKIE: Get off me,
you piece of shit!
If I see you put your hands
in that plate one more time,
I'm gonna stab you with this knife!
You hear me?
I told you, keep your
hands out of the plate!
Can't get any peace around here, Joey.
All right!
Just relax.
What, do I have to eat like you...
God!
What's the matter with you, huh?
You fucked my wife?
You fucked my wife!
(SCREAMING)
Jake, get off of him!
I'll kill you!
VICKIE: Call the police!
Get out!
JAKE: Vickie. Vick, don't leave.
Honey, please.
Honey, look, I... I'm a bum
without you and the kids.
Don't go.
Just...
ANNOUNCER: Less than a minute to go,
and La Motta is losing the title
that he won from the
gallant Marcel Cerdan.
After the tragic plane crash
that took Cerdan's life,
Laurent Dauthuille vowed to
bring the title back to France.
And tonight, he only has
to last this 15th round
to be crowned the new
Middleweight Champion.
La Motta's taking terrible
punishment on the ropes
as Dauthuille bangs him with
lefts and rights to the head.
Another left! Another
right to the jaw!
And La Motta turns around!
He's been playing possum!
He's got Dauthuille hurt!
It's a right to the body,
two more hooks to the jaw!
Another left and a
right to the head!
Dauthuille is reeling
around the ring!
The tide has turned,
no question about it!
And he wobbles into the
ropes and goes down!
Dauthuille is down.
Referee Lou Handler comes
over and starts the count.
He's trying to get up.
Six, seven...
He'll never make it.
Nine, ten!
You're out!
It is all over!
He is knocked out,
and Jake La Motta,
with 13 seconds left to
go in the final round,
has made one of the most
remarkable comebacks
in all boxing history.
RING ANNOUNCER: Jake La Motta!
Come on. Just tell him
you're sorry, you miss him.
He's your brother. You have to
talk to him sooner or later.
I'll dial him for you.
You can talk to him.
Just tell him you're sorry, then
you can say whatever you want.
Hmm?
Here.
Hey, champ, I'd like to
ask you a few questions.
Not now.
I've been waiting
for about an hour.
Excuse me, my wife is...
I got a great angle here for you.
Don't bother me, please. Fantastic.
Absolutely great story.
Get out of here. Come on.
You're the champ.
Get out of here. You're a great guy.
Come on.
I asked you nice, will you...
JOEY: Hello.
Hello.
Salvy, this ain't funny anymore.
Is it you?
I know somebody's there.
I can hear you breathing.
You listening?
Your mother sucks fucking
big fucking elephant dicks.
You got that?
Wasn't home.
ANNOUNCER: The fight of the year.
Now, the next time that friendly
bartender says, "What'll you have?"
Give him that answer the whole
world gives, "Pabst Blue Ribbon."
Those punches by La Motta
explain themselves.
They've fought five times
between 1942 and 1945.
This has so far been a blazing bout
for the middleweight championship.
That's great action by La Motta.
He couldn't score the big one.
That's it. That was his last shot.
Round number 13, the hard-luck number.
There's the buzzer.
And I think you know both the boys.
Robinson hurting La Motta.
He's hurting him now.
He has La Motta on Queer
Street, holding on.
Well, certainly that was one
of the most damaging evidences
of punching that you
have seen in recent years.
Come on!
Come on, come on!
Come on! What are you standing for?
Robinson, apparently tired,
punched with a fare-thee-well and rocked
Jake La Motta right to his heels.
Come on, Ray!
These are clean, whistling shots. How
he can survive them, nobody knows.
No man can endure this pummeling.
The fight is stopped on a
signal from Frankie Sikora.
Row after row after row from the ring,
the crowd is standing and cheering
as he just cannonaded Jake La
Motta into a death defeat.
Ray.
And when I say that, I mean
Jake wouldn't want to quit.
He wanted to go.
Hey, Ray.
I never went down, Ray.
You never got me down, Ray.
You hear me?
Never got me down.
Yeah. See?
Where we going?
And in the 13th round,
the hard-luck round,
the Championship of the
World has changed hands.
And there you see it, a
champion gone down to defeat.
And so now, we wait
for the announcement
from Eddie Flint,
the ring announcer.
And then we'll get up in the ring
and join with the radio
audience throughout the world
and have a brief interview
with Ray Robinson.
Now we're waiting for the time to be
announced, and it is being handed
between the commissioner
and Eddie Flint.
The fight was stopped
on a signal from...
RING ANNOUNCER: Attention,
ladies and gentlemen!
The winner by a technical knockout
in two minutes and four
seconds of the 13th round,
and the new World
Middleweight Boxing Champion,
Sugar Ray Robinson!
(CROWD CHEERING)
MAN: Why are you pulling out
of Wednesday's fight, Jake?
It's over for me. Boxing's over for me.
I'm through.
I'm tired of worrying
about weight all the time.
That's all I used to think about
was weight, weight, weight.
After a while, you know, you realize
there are other things in life.
I mean, I'm very grateful.
Boxing's been good to me.
I got a nice house, I got three great
kids, I got a wonderful, beautiful wife.
What more could I ask for, huh?
What's your name?
Bob.
Bob. Take a picture, Bob.
Yeah, let him... Let him take
a picture, honey, for us.
Yeah. Smile.
Thank you, Bob. Hey, Bob,
take a picture of all of us.
Jackie, come here.
Sit over there.
All right, everybody, smile. Smile.
MAN: Vickie... Mrs. La Motta, how do
you feel about Jake's retirement?
I think it's great, you know. He picked
the right time to stop fighting.
He's home with us all the time now.
It's really good.
You know what?
You through?
JAKE: Yeah.
You know, I just bought a
club on Collins Avenue.
It's a bar, package store, everything.
Guess what I'm gonna call it?
MAN: I don't know, what're you
gonna call it? Take a guess.
All right, shut up.
Enough, enough.
Thank you.
(FEEDBACK SCREECHING)
(CROWD LAUGHING)
Just want to see what the...
What the microphone on a
sexy girl sounds like.
(KISSING SOUNDS)
Yeah, it sounds...
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen.
I haven't seen so many losers
since my last fight at
Madison Square Garden.
Okay, honey.
Thank you very much.
Ain't that something?
MAN: Bring us another drink.
(SPEAKING ITALIAN)
Yeah, look at this terrific girl.
She's the kind of girl you want
to bring home to your father,
especially if he's a degenerate.
(CROWD LAUGHING)
Did I say that?
No, seriously, folks,
it's a thrill to be standing here
before you wonderful people tonight.
Well, in fact, it's a
thrill to be standing.
(CROWD LAUGHING)
If you believe it's a thrill to be
standing for you wonderful people,
then you're all full of shit.
By the way, me and my wife
Vickie's getting married.
Now, what am I talking
about? I'm out of it.
(LAUGHS)
Is she here? Is she here?
She's not here.
Vickie? No, she's not here.
By the way, me and my wife
Vickie's gonna celebrate,
it's a little different,
our 11th wedding anniversary.
(CROWD APPLAUDING)
Thank you.
That reminds me about
two friends of mine.
One was married, one was single.
The married guy
tells the single guy,
"Oh! What's the matter with you?
"What's the matter
with you? Look at me.
"And look at you.
"And look at me, and look at you."
Let me get on with it.
"When I come home at night,
"my wife's at the door with
a tall drink in her hand.
"Then she gives me a nice hot bath.
"Then she gives me a nice rubdown.
"Then she makes
passionate love to me.
"Then she makes me a nice dinner.
"What more could you ask
for? You ought to try that."
The other friend says,
"Hey, that sounds great.
"When does your wife get home?"
And though I'm no Olivier,
but if he fought Sugar Ray,
he would say that
the thing ain't the ring,
it's the play.
So give me a stage where
this bull here can rage,
and though I can fight, I'd
much rather hear myself recite.
(CROWD SINGING)
That's entertainment
Jake! Jake!
You were just great.
It's a good thing Sugar Ray
wasn't here tonight, huh?
He told that joke last week.
Come on.
He repeats himself,
getting a little senile.
Jake, I would like you to meet
State's Attorney Bronson.
How are you? Nice to meet you.
Jake, hi.
And his wife.
Nice to meet you.
You shouldn't be here this week.
It's next week we got the
shakedown payments, right?
Got a sense of humor.
It's a good seeing you.
That is a joke, right?
It's a joke, only you
know if it's a joke.
All right, we'll
talk about it later.
This is your wife?
Yes. Mrs. Bronson.
Very pretty lady.
Charmed to meet you.
Thank you.
He's really a nice guy. You can
take a joke, can't you, doll?
(EXCLAIMS)
I'm sorry.
It's all right.
Carlo. Carlo.
Carlo, give them another drink.
Something happened over here.
Darling, Linda, come here.
Where's your wife?
My wife? Yeah. Why isn't she here?
What's it to you?
What do you think,
I'm gonna bring her around here, let
you bums get involved with her?
Come on!
Especially with the State's
Attorney over here?
He comes here a lot, darling.
Watch him.
He knows I'm only kidding.
Thank you.
Keep an eye on him.
What's the problem?
WOMAN: Well, there's really not a
problem, but she doesn't look 21,
so I just had to ask for some ID.
How old are you, honey?
21.
Mmm-hmm.
Can you prove that you're 21?
Prove it to me.
Any girl that can kiss like that
can drink at my joint any time.
What about you? How old are you?
21.
Can you prove that you're 21?
Yeah.
Would you prove it to me?
Come here.
WOMAN: She's 21, too?
She had to convince
me that she's 21, too.
WOMAN: Okay.
Jake.
Watch it.
Your wife's outside.
She's waiting for you.
Why don't you tell
me a little louder?
Come on, Jake.
(IMITATING SNEEZING)
(ALL LAUGHING)
It was a busy night last night.
Everything all right?
I'm leaving you, Jake.
All right. What else is new?
No, I mean it this time.
I didn't want to tell you till
I had everything worked out.
Move over.
Why?
So you could put your hands on me?
Open the door.
No.
Come on, honey, open the door.
No. Look, Jake, I got a lawyer.
We're getting a divorce, and I'm
getting custody of the kids.
Let me in for a minute. Come on.
No, I already made up my mind.
I'm leaving.
That's it.
Kids are gonna be with me,
and if you show your face around,
I'm gonna call the cops on you.
All right, that's it.
Come on, don't act that way, honey.
Hey, Jake.
Jake.
Hey, Jake. Come on, champ. Come on, wake up.
Wake up, champ.
What's up?
We're from the D.A.
Yeah, I know where you're from.
They want to talk with you.
You all look the same to me,
anyway. What's the difference?
They want to talk with you, Jake.
About what?
I don't know. I don't run the joint.
They just told me to bring you in.
But what do you want? For what?
Do you recognize this girl?
She been in the club?
This is the same girl?
Yeah.
No. I don't know her.
She says you introduced
her to some men.
I introduced her to men.
I introduce a lot of
people to a lot of people.
You tell me I
introduced her to men.
I introduced him to men.
But I don't say nothing.
She's 14. Come on.
Put on your shoes, Jake.
She's how old?
Fourteen.
She's 14.
Let me see that.
Let me ask you something.
Are you gonna tell me
that that girl looks 14?
She's 14. I'm asking
you man to man.
What am I gonna say?
Now, come on. We gotta go.
We gotta go downtown?
That's right.
For what? Because of this girl?
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
Vick.
VICKIE: You drunk?
Vickie, open the door.
I'm out on bail.
I'll pick up one thing
and I'll leave. I promise.
The kids are sleeping.
I won't bother them.
Let me get something.
All right. Don't make no noise.
What?
Don't make no noise.
I won't. Just let me get one thing.
VICKIE: What are you doing?
I gotta get $10,000.
My lawyer says if I could
spread $10,000 around,
I could get the case dropped.
Yeah, but they don't have
a case against you.
No, you kidding me or what?
You ever see a 14-year-old
testify in court?
You saw the papers.
"La Motta on a vice rap."
VICKIE: What are you
doing to the belt?
JAKE: What difference does it make?
Well, can't you get the
money from your friends?
Yeah, what friends?
Jake! You're gonna
wake my kids up, Jake!
You're gonna wake
the kids! Stop it!
What's the matter with you?
Don't you put the dishes
so they don't fall down
out of the fucking...
Get out!
What about the belt, Mr. La Motta?
Isn't that what you wanted to
sell me, the championship belt?
Yeah, but these are
the jewels from the belt.
Yeah, but where is the belt? The belt
of a champion is a very rare item.
I wish you'd come to me in the
first place, Mr. La Motta.
You'd have had the
belt and the jewels...
Give me $2,000 for them.
Give me $2,000.
$1,500 top.
That's all...
You can't give me $2,000?
$1,500 top, Mr. La Motta.
I'm sorry.
I'd lose.
I don't want to...
Come here. Come here.
Don't tell me you're
not gonna make a profit.
I know you're lying.
Go around the corner, I bet you I
get twice for what you're offering.
I can't raise the $10,000.
I tried. I tried.
I tried a lot of places.
Yeah, but what am I gonna do?
If that's what they're gonna do,
they're gonna do. What can I do?
Then fuck them. Let them
do what they're gonna do.
MAN: Get in the goddamn
cell, now, come on!
That's right, can't
hurt folks no more.
This is where it's at, right here.
Who was the one goddamn
trying to shirk, huh?
You'll pull your load here, boy.
That's right.
I don't want no more!
Get in the goddamn box, champion!
I'll break you on one of my fucking
farms, you son of a bitch!
You hear me?
Hold onto him just a minute!
I got him.
See it? See it? Look at it, son!
Live in it!
Go on, boy.
MAN: You understand that?
On your mother's cunt, then!
Your mother's...
Cocksucker!
Live in it!
Let that son of a bitch sit.
Fuck him!
Fuck you! Fuck you!
Fuck your mother!
(GASPING)
Dummy. Dummy.
Dummy. Dummy. Dummy.
Why? Why? Why? Why?
(SOBBING)
(SHOUTING)
why? why? why? why?
(SCREAMING)
You motherfucker!
(CRYING) My hand.
Why'd you do it? Why?
You're so stupid.
So fucking stupid.
You're stupid.
They call me an animal. I'm not an animal.
I'm not an animal.
Why do they treat me like this?
I'm not that bad.
I'm not so bad.
I'm not that guy.
JAKE: Guy comes home, finds his
wife in bed with another guy.
The wife says, "Look
who's here, bigmouth.
"Now the whole
neighborhood will know."
(CROWD LAUGHS)
Thanks. Thanks for laughing.
Spread it around a little bit.
The first night I was here,
I said to the owner, I said,
"Listen, where's the toilet?"
He said, "You're in it."
MAN: Come on, let's go. Let's go.
Hey, why don't you leave me alone?
I'm trying to do my routine.
UP Yours.
Pop, you're gonna force
me to make a comeback.
Funny.
Fuck you
and the horse you rode in on,
(MAN LAUGHS)
and the whole cavalry behind you.
Funny man.
That's why I'm here.
Give him another drink.
Piss in it for me.
I'm now gonna introduce a woman
who's made a worldwide tour
with top billing and all that other
bullshit, where they all hated her.
I want you all to give
her a warm welcome.
I know you're capable of it.
You look like a bunch of junkies.
Her name is Emma 48's.
(MUSIC PLAYING)
(CROWD CHEERING)
Taxi.
Honey...
Listen, I'm gonna take a little walk. I
got a couple things I gotta take care of.
All right.
Will I see you later?
Yeah, yeah.
Take that, I'll be
home later. All right.
Thank you.
Be careful.
Hello.
Hey. What are you doing? Joey.
Come on, Joey. Why
don't you turn around?
Huh?
Come on, Joey, turn around.
Hey, Joey, come on.
Joey.
Joe.
Come on, Joey, what are you doing?
Huh?
Come on. What are you
getting so angry about?
Come on. Be friends.
Come on, you're my brother.
Be friends.
My brother?
Yeah, you fucking burn.
Give me a break.
Come on, kiss me.
Come on.
Give me a kiss, come on.
Wait. Let me call my wife and kids.
Don't you want them to see the kiss?
You're gonna forgive and forget? It's
a long time ago. Forget about it.
Just give me a kiss, come on.
Come on.
You're my brother.
Give me a kiss.
Come on.
How's everything? All right?
Good.
Everything's all right?
You don't want to do
this here. Come on.
Let me call you. We'll get
together in a couple days.
You'll call me?
I will.
Don't forget.
Huh?
I'll call you.
All right.
JAKE: And nobody could take
that away from me. Nobody.
Some people aren't that lucky.
Like the one that Marlon Brando
played in On the Waterfront,
an up-and-comer who's
now a down-and-outer.
You remember that scene
in the back of the car
with his brother Charley,
a small-time racket guy?
And it went something like this.
It wasn't him, Charley.
It was you.
You remember that night at the Garden,
you came down to my dressing room,
and you said, "Kid, this ain't your night.
We're going for the price on Wilson?"
Remember that? "This
ain't your night."
My night.
I could've taken Wilson
apart that night.
So what happens?
He gets a title shot outdoors in
a ballpark, and what do I get?
A one-way ticket to Palookaville.
I was never no good after
that night, Charley.
It was like a peak you reach,
and then it's downhill.
It was you, Charley.
You was my brother.
You should've looked out
for me a little bit.
for me just a little bit.
You should've taken care
of me just a little bit,
instead of making me take them
dives for the short-end money.
You don't understand.
I could've had class.
I could've been a contender.
I could've been somebody, instead
of a bum, which is what I am.
Let's face it.
It was you, Charley.
(DOOR OPENS)
How you doing, Jake?
Everything all right?
Yeah.
Ready? It'll be about five minutes.
Okay.
Need anything?
No.
You sure?
I'm sure.
Lot of people out there?
Yeah.
It's crowded.
(DOOR SHUTS)
Go get them, champ.
(GRUNTING)
I'm the boss, I'm the boss.
I'm the boss.
I'm the boss, I'm the boss, I'm the boss,
I'm the boss, I'm the boss, I'm the boss.
(GRUNTING)