JEWS FORBIDDEN
You!
Come here!
Why didn't you bow?
I'm sorry.
You are forbidden
to walk on the pavement.
Walk in the gutter!
I didn't come here to listen to the music.
- Hey, what's going on?
Are you bored?
- You're cold? Come on, move!
Move on!
- Yeah! That's it! Dance!
Dance!
- Come on, dance! Go on!
Yeah, that's nice. And you?
Don't you wanna dance, too?
Now we clear the street for
a Jewish dance floor.
And... you...
Yes, you both!
Faster!
That's nice.
And faster! Yeah...
Go!
- And faster!
I said, faster!
Move on! Move! Faster!
I said, dance!
Good, they're here,
You little bastard!
Stop it, stop it!
Stop it! Stop!
Come on, come on! Come on boy.
Come on.
Stand up, stand up!
Lights! Lights!
Open up! Light on!
Quick! Come here!
Stay!
Open up! Come on! No luggage!
Open up!
- No, please, no!
We didn't do anything, please, no!
Stand up!
You, stand up! Get up!
Throw him out!
Ah!
- Be quiet, Mama, for God's sake!
My God!
Come on! Run! Run!
- Run!
Hey, Mr Rubinstein.
- You... bandit!
Boom, boom. Dead!
- I am really scared.
For this joke Mr Rubinstein
gets a cigarette, hm?
Cigarettes, thank you.
Right. All men are created equal.
Only the Germans are created
a little more equal.
Out! Assemble in the yard!
Go, go, go, go!
We're employed here.
We've got certificates.
Here.
You, to the left!
You!
You! You!
The rest of you get dressed and then
report back here. Bring your belongings.
Fifteen kilos only.
- Where are you taking us?
Left about turn!
Forward, march!
Stop! Come here!
- Stop!
What's that?
- A working column.
Right turn!
You, come here!
You!
You! You!
Down!
Left about turn!
Forward, march!
Did you fix the car?
You know, it'll break!
Get him away from here.
Assemble! Fall in!
Carry on.
What are you doing?
Go on working!
It's so cold.
- Potatoes. Once again potatoes.
Any fucking plaster?
Yes.
What were you up to?
Nothing.
What the fuck are those?
We're allowed
to take food into the ghetto.
Three kilos of potatoes and a...
Open it.
Yes.
It's only potatoes and bread.
- You're lying, I can smell it.
Open it.
- Yes, yes.
I... I...
- Potatoes.
You're all the same.
Give a Jew a little finger...
he takes the whole hand.
You lie to me again
and I'll shoot you personally.
Stop!
Oh, shit.
- Just wait!
What's going in here?
I'll soon teach you discipline!
Jew pigs!
Know why we beat you?
- No.
- Why?
To celebrate New Year's eve!
Now, march! Go on, march!
- Beware, go on! And sing!
Sing something cheerful!
And sing it now and loud!
Do you have a cigarette?
Do you have a match?
DO NOT PASS
Unit, move!
Fischke, go to the 4th floor!
I'm there. There's no one.
Go on. Check the attic.
I'm checking the attic.
No one to see over here.
Then come down!
- Yeah, come down!
Any news from your mother?
- Nothing since three weeks.
If she were in trouble,
you would know it.
But how? I'm in worrying about her.
Don't worry.
As I said repeatedly:
this side first!
Just like this.
Just let them step away
before shooting, asshole.
Good, now the hospital!
What, here? Are you sure?
You mean, that's the hut?
- It has to be the right one.
But it's totally destroyed.
Who the hell are you?
Who are you?
Do you understand me?
- Yes.
What are you doing here?
I was...
I was trying to open this tin.
- Where do you live?
Do you work here?
- No.
What's your work?
I am...
I was a pianist.
A pianist.
Come.
Play.
Are you hiding here?
Jew?
Where are you hiding?
In the attic.
Show me.
Have you anything to eat?
Jew?
Please.
What's all that gunfire?
The Russians.
On the other side of the river.
All you have to do is hang on
for a few more weeks.
What's happening?
- We're getting out.
Are the Russians here?
- Not yet.
I... I don't know how to thank you.
Don't thank me. Thank God.
It's His will that we should survive.
Well. That's what we have to believe.
Here, take this one.
What about you?
- I've got another one. Warmer.
What will you do when it's all over?
I'll play the piano again.
On Polish Radio.
Tell me your name.
I'll listen out for you.
Szpilman.
Szpilman...
Good name for a pianist.
Musician?
You're musician?
- Yes.
Do you happen to know another musician,
a Mr Szpilman? A pianist!
Polish radio?
- Yes, of course, I know Szpilman.
I helped Mr Szpilman
when he was in hiding.
Tell him I'm here.
Ask him to help me.
- What's your name?
Hosenfeld.
- What?
Wladyslaw Szpilman continued to live in
Warsaw until his death on 6th July, 2000.
He was 88 years old.
The name of the German officer
was Captain Wilm Hosenfeld.
All that is known is that he died
1952 in a Soviet prisoner-of-war camp.