Where's the money, Lebowski?
The Big Lebowski is about a
character named Jeff Lebowski,
played by Jeff Bridges,
this sort of aging pothead
who lives in Los Angeles
and who becomes the victim
of a case of mistaken identity
just because he happens
to have the same name
as a millionaire
who lives out in Pasadena.
And by virtue of that, he's thrust into
this intrigue surrounding a kidnapping
involving
the millionaire's wife.
The Big Lebowski
started, really,
with us thinking about
a friend of ours
in Los Angeles,
who the character that Jeff Bridges
plays is sort of loosely based on.
This is a guy who we've
known for about 15 years,
who actually
does call himself the Dude,
and it was imagining him
in the context of
a Chandler kind of a story
that got us started
on the script.
It just seemed interesting to
us to thrust that character
into the most confusing
situation possible,
the person, it would seem
on the face of it,
least equipped to deal with it.
That's sort of
the conceit of the movie.
Wait. Let me explain
something to you.
I am not Mr. Lebowski.
You're Mr. Lebowski.
I'm the Dude.
So that's what you call me.
You know?
That, or His Dudeness, or Duder,
or, you know, El Duderino, if you're
not into the whole brevity thing.
Are you employed, sir?
Employed?
The Dude, who is...
He's better known as the Dude, but
his real name is Jeff Lebowski,
and he gets confused
with another Lebowski,
a fellow who's...
You know,
a lot wealthier fellow.
And he gets
mixed up for this guy,
and all kind of hell
and confusion breaks loose.
"We have Bunny."
LEBOWSKI: ...written by men who were unable
to achieve on a level field of play.
"Gather $1 million..."
Cowards!
"...in unmarked, non-consecutive 20s."
Weaklings!
"Await instructions. No funny stuff."
Bums!
Bummer.
This is definitely
the Dude we wanted.
I think he did have
a good time making the movie.
He got to eat
whatever he wanted.
Yeah.
I mean, it was clear to Jeff
that the character wasn't into the Los
Angeles health, fitness and beauty,
and that he could
let himself go,
which he probably kind of
enjoyed, even just for that.
Yeah, and he really...
Yeah, one thing he did take from the
real character, the real Dude, is...
You know, the real Dude is quite
overweight, and I think...
Jeff met him once, and I think
he looked at him and went,
“Okay, I can kind of let my
waistline go for this part."
But all Jeff wanted to know...
Actually, pretty consistently,
Jeff Bridges, at the beginning of
the start of shooting every scene,
he'd walk up
to one or the other of us
and ask if we figured whether or not
the Dude burned one on the way over.
Yeah, "So do you think the Dude
burned one on the way over?"
So we'd think about it.
Usually we'd say, "Yeah, he probably
burned one on the way over,"
and Jeff would go
over in the corner,
rub his knuckles in his eyes
to turn them red
and do the scene, and that
was kind of the extent
of what you had to do
to direct Jeff. Yeah.
Some actors like talking
about it more than others.
(SIRENS APPROACHING)
No, you're not wrong.
Am I wrong?
You're not wrong, Walter.
You're just an asshole.
Okay, then.
Play Quintana and O'Brien next week.
They should be pushovers.
Man, would you just...
Just take it easy, man.
In this one,
in this particular case,
the story was very loosely based
on the narrative structure
of a Chandler novel. You know?
And those novels
are very episodic in nature.
They usually follow
the main character
as he encounters
these different characters
on a journey to uncover a mystery
or find a missing person
or whatever it may be
in the novel.
So that was sort of the...
In this case, that was sort
of the model for the story.
In each movie, it's a little bit
different in terms of where the...
Actually, the one case where it got,
just in terms of plot, most involved
and most difficult
for us to manage
was Miller's Crossing,
which was a gangster movie,
sort of a homage,
or a rip-off, depending on
your point of view,
of Dashiell Hammett.
And that got very...
Just in the sense of the convolution
of the plot, got very involved,
and that was sort of,
as I say, difficult to manage.
This one, yeah, not as much.
It was partly...
In this one, we sort of figured,
if things become
a little bit too complicated
and are unclear,
it really doesn't matter.
I mean, the plot is not the...
And, again,
this is similar to Chandler.
The plot is sort of secondary
to the other things that are
going on in the piece, I think.
And if people get
a little bit confused,
it's, I don't think,
really necessarily
going to get in the way
of them enjoying the movie.
Yeah, you look at something
like The Big Sleep,
and nobody seemed to know,
including the people who wrote it,
what the hell was going on
in that plot either, so...
The hero, the Dude,
is not a private eye,
but he's
really a guy who's a throwback
to the characters of...
You know, early '70s,
late '60s kind of guy.
What makes a man,
Mr. Lebowski?
Dude.
Oh, I don't know, sir.
Is it being prepared
to do the right thing,
whatever the cost?
Isn't that what makes a man?
Sure.
That and a pair of testicles.
Sam Elliott
would actually ask us for...
Like, "What am I doing
in this movie?"
Yeah, Sam would say, "I don't
know what I'm doing here, boys.
"Happy to be here,
don't get me wrong, but..."
We didn't have anything to tell Sam.
We didn't know either.
But, you know, didn't
hurt his performance any.
How're you doing there, Dude?
Not too good, man.
One of those days, huh?
Yeah.
Well, a wiser fellow
than myself once said,
"Sometimes you eat the bear,
and..."
Much obliged.
"Sometimes the bear,
well, he eats you."
That some kind of Eastern thing?
Far from it.
I like your style, Dude.
We really wrote that part for
Sam 'cause we like his voice.
You know,
he's got that really...
I mean, he really
can hit that lower register.
Also, he's got that
really big mustache,
so when you're cutting the movie,
you can move his lines around,
cheat them
into his mouth wherever.
ETHAN: You know,
you can never see his lips.
It's a good thing about
working with Sam Elliott.
Walter's kind of an
interesting character for me.
I'm trying to do justice to him.
He was written so wonderfully.
He's head of
a security agency, his own.
I think he gets by all right.
Doesn't really... The most
nattily dressed fellow in town.
He's got his own agenda.
He was...
He's got an Army background,
and that's his career, is reminding
people of his service in Vietnam.
He means well,
but he is a little oafish.
That wasn't her toe, Dude.
Whose toe was it, Walter?
How should I know?
I do know that nothing about
it indicates that it was her...
The nail polish, Walter!
Fine, Dude.
As if it's impossible to get some nail
polish, apply it to someone else's toe...
Someone else...
Pinking shears.
Where the...
Are they gonna get...
You want a toe?
I can get you a toe.
Believe me,
there are ways, Dude.
You don't wanna know
about it. Believe me.
Yeah, but, Walter...
Hell, I could get you a toe by 3:00
this afternoon, with nail polish.
Yeah, we wrote the Walter part
for John, who...
I guess this is the third
movie we've done with him.
And...
Well, actually, as we wrote the part
that Turturro plays for Turturro
and the part that
Steve Buscemi plays for Steve.
So those parts were essentially
written for those actors.
Were you listening
to the Dude's story, Donny?
What?
Walter...
Were you listening to the Dude's story?
I was bowling.
So you have no frame
of reference here, Donny.
You're like a child who wanders
into the middle of a movie
and wants to know...
Walter, what's the point, man?
There's no reason...
Here's my point, Dude.
There's no fucking reason
why these two...
Yeah, Walter, what's your point?
Walter, what is the...
Look, we all know
who is at fault here.
We saw John Turturro
play an Hispanic character
in a play
at the Public Theater about...
Must be about
11 or 12 years ago.
And ever since then, we've wanted
to write something for him
where he plays
an Hispanic character.
And this just seemed like
the right opportunity for it.
JOEL: I mean...
And then, to really give him
something to sink his teeth into,
we made him a child molester.
But...
I think it's really a
pretty vivid characterization
given the amount of screen
time he has, don't you think?
Yeah. Yeah. John goes
to the core of things.
The characters were conceived
as being
partners in
a dysfunctional marriage.
The Jeff Bridges and John
Goodman character, they were...
And at the point where we
were writing the script,
we sort of conceived them
in the sense that...
You know, designed them so
that they would be able to...
Or constantly would be
pushing each other's buttons
in terms of
those kinds of reactions,
you know, the sort of getting
on each other's nerves
and yet, still, at a certain
level, really liking each other.
One of the things that Jeff,
I think...
It's interesting, because one of the
things that Jeff sort of came to
while we were rehearsing,
before we started shooting,
was he conceived
the character, appropriately,
as being very mellow
and laid-back,
and yet, in practically
every scene in the movie,
he ends up exploding
because of what Walter is doing
or saying or making happen.
And that was something
he hadn't associated,
on the first reading in the
script, with the character,
but is very much a part of how
they, the two characters,
relate to each other.
It's a definite buddy movie.
That's what I love about it,
and...
The dialogue's
just funnier than hell.
I mean, it's one of those
where you crack the page
and you start laughing
every two pages,
and enough where you gotta
sit for five minutes
and then you can
pick it up again.
Walter, I love you,
but sooner or later you're
gonna have to face the fact
you're a goddamn moron.
No time to argue.
Hey, man...
The bridge.
Hey, Walter... Hey, Walter!
Hey, Walter...
WALTER: Here goes the ringer!
What the fuck?
Okay, Dude, your wheel.
Hey, man... What the fuck!
At 15 m.p.h., I roll out.
I double back, grab one of
them and beat it out of him.
The Uzi.
Uzi?
You didn't think I was rolling
out of here naked, did you?
Walter, please! Fifteen, Dude!
Let's take that hill!
Walter!
(MAN IN ME PLAYING)
We've done four movies
with Roger Deakins
as the cinematographer.
JOEL: Well, it's funny.
We met Roger...
Specifically, the way we
started working with Roger is,
when we did Barton Fink,
we were shooting a movie
in Los Angeles,
non-union,
and for that reason, we...
But on the other hand,
we wanted to work with someone
whose work we knew and liked,
as opposed to someone
who was just starting out.
And that meant a foreign DP
who wasn't in the unions
in the United States.
So we went...
We'd seen Roger's work, I
think, on a number of things,
but in particular Mike
Figgis' movie Stormy Monday,
I think was the last one we'd
seen before we talked to him.
And we met Roger and liked him
and hired him to do that movie,
and we've been
working together since then.
You know, Roger's just...
He's one of the top three
or four DPs
working in the world
right now, I think.
He's like... There's nobody
better than Roger.
And just personally,
we get along really well.
So it's been
a good collaboration.
ETHAN: Yeah, Julianne Moore ls really good.
Yeah, It wasn't meant to be...
It isn't specifically English,
the accent.
It's some vague,
non-specific geographically,
“swell finishing school for girls
in Switzerland," maybe, accent
that she came up with.
Yeah, she just read the script
and sort of intuitively grasped
that there should be something
horribly regal about the character.
She's very funny.
Julianne Moore plays a wonderful
avant-garde artist who specializes in
some sort of feminist art. I
couldn't really put my finger on it.
Yeah,
something to do with women.
Do you like sex, Mr. Lebowski?
Excuse me?
Sex. The physical act of love.
Coitus. Do you like it?
I was talking about my rug.
You're not interested in sex?
You mean coitus?
I like it too.
It's a male myth about
feminists that we hate sex.
It can be a natural,
zesty enterprise.
However, there are some people,
it is called satyriasis in
men, nymphomania in women,
who engage in it compulsively
and without joy.
Oh, no.
Oh, yes, Mr. Lebowski.
Well, movies always
get weird reactions.
Like, some people, some
journalists we talk to, say,
"Well? So how did you come up
with the story?
"Just sit around
and smoke a lot of pot?"
It was really strange. We got
that from one journalist.
Then, when we were doing
an interview in Germany,
a German journalist asked us,
"So how do you
come up with the story?
"You sit around in a room
and drink a lot of beer?"
(SNORTS)
I'm throwing rocks tonight.
JOEL: Steve doesn't say much
in the movie. He...
Well, we thought it would
be interesting after...
You know, he plays sort of a motor mouth in Fargo.
He never really shuts up.
And so we thought it would be interesting
to go the other way in this movie
in terms of the character
that we wrote for him.
Somebody pointed out
to us recently
that he's been in
the past five movies of ours
and we've killed him
in each one.
Yeah. Yeah, I don't know what the...
Yeah. I don't know why.
In progressively more
gruesome ways, too, actually.
Well, not that his death in this
one is particularly gruesome,
not to reveal too much.
But his remains seem to get smaller
and smaller in each of our movies.
I don't know what we'll do next.
No, don't do...
Not on the rug, man.
The carpet.
You know, it's interesting,
we just got a call
from Floor Covering Weekly,
a magazine to the trade
about floor coverings,
that wanted to do a story
on The Big Lebowski
because catalyst for the story
was the floor covering.
So we did a really long...
We were so excited about being
on Floor Covering Weekly
that we did a really long interview with the woman.
She was really taken aback.
It was the one time
we've talked to a journalist
where they were anxious
to get off the phone
and were just humoring us as we
mattered on about the carpet
and all the other
floor coverings in the movie.
And she promised to send us
a copy of the magazine,
but it hasn't materialized yet.
Yeah, it's hard to believe that there's
actually a weekly about floor covering.
Yeah, how much is there to say?
'Cause that's...
And you would think,
by virtue of that,
she would be interested
in a lot of material
about the movie.
Filling some pages. Yeah.
We even offered to pose for
her if she'd do a cover.
Pose for a cover picture, the two
of us in front of the Persian carpet
which Jeff Bridges' character
appropriates.
And she was sort of polite,
but declined.
Then we started
getting suspicious
that maybe the whole thing
had been a hoax
and she wasn't actually
a legitimate representative
from Floor Covering Weekly,
but some journalist who'd been
turned down for an interview
in another context.
But, yeah, it is true that the movie does...
The catalyst for the plot...
The whole beginning
of the movie has to do
with a rug being soiled in a
sort of very particular way.
And the main character's
journey through the movie
is an attempt to get redress
for his soiled rug.
That, also, was loosely taken
from real life.
One of the characters
that the movie was based on
used to have a rug that he'd, I think,
salvaged out of the trash from somewhere,
that he would go on and on about
how it tied the room together
in his little apartment.
So, yeah, the rug became
a very important element.
Yeah, then it just
seemed to take off.
Actually, literally.
I mean, we got into the whole flying
carpet, Thief of Bagdad thing
with one of his
pothead hallucinations.
We gave the script
to Joel Silver, the producer,
who gave us
a really interesting note
which we actually ignored
but maybe shouldn't have.
He said that the movie should have
ended with him getting his rug back
or some mention of the rug, which
would have been a nice resolution,
but we never did do it.
(JUST DROPPED IN PLAYING)
We thought we could do many
of those shots practically,
the shots where
we don't see Jeff full-figure,
floating between the girls'
legs in the bowling alley.
But actually,
the human body is such
that Jeff's shoulders
are just a little too broad
and the girls, though they
were cast to be tall,
were just not tall enough,
so that Jeff couldn't actually
fit between their legs.
They had to be shot
in separate passes.
There was a pass of the camera
tracking past the girls' legs
and then a shot of Jeff being
propelled over the bowling alley.
And they had to be composited
in a computer
with Jeff shrunk very slightly
so that he could, indeed,
plausibly pass between their legs
but not shrunk to the extent
that you'd notice.
But, yeah,
all those shots of Jeff
with the dancing girls
in the Busby Berkeley sequence
are composited in a computer.
So they were shot separately.
The shots where the camera
actually goes through the legs
were shot practically, on a
stage, just with a camera on a...
Well, we did it two ways.
We had a little skateboard,
essentially,
that the camera sat on,
that was sent down...
With a motor on it, and the camera was...
You could...
Sent down between their legs,
and it was controlled by an
operator with a joystick.
It's similar to a device that
we used in the bowling alley
where we would chase the bowling
balls down the bowling lane.
This little motorized
skateboard with a camera on it
could get up to
about 20 miles an hour
and chase these bowling balls
down the lane.
Well, you know, another convention
of the private eye movies...
I mean,
Raymond Chandler's stories,
but, again,
private eye movies generally,
is at some point
the private eye gets slugged,
or gets slipped
the Mickey Finn or whatever,
and goes into some sort of
delirium or hallucination.
That's sort of...
That's certainly
a hallmark in the movies
and in many of the novels that
movies are based on as well.
So in that respect,
we had license to do it
by virtue of the genre,
but also, it seemed like
we had a special license
to do that sort of splashy thing
by virtue of the character
as being a heavy drug user.
So, you know,
it just lets you do things
that are sort of a departure
from the rest of the movie,
and do, in a sense,
come out of nowhere,
are stylistically not like
the rest of the movie.
(JUST DROPPED IN PLAYING)