The Big Lebowski
has grown in ten years.
People have seen this film more
than any film that I've been in.
They've written books.
There's the Lebowski Fest.
People are obsessed with that movie.
They're obsessed with it.
What the hell is it?
What attracts people to it?
It hits something
in the young people.
Let's roll, please.
Rolling.
Mark.
Action.
It's gigantic.
This movie was released
after Fargo.
And, you know,
Fargo was very successful.
And I think the critics didn't know what
to make of this when it was released.
I remember when it came out,
everybody was like, "So what?"
There was sort of, like,
a little bit of a thunk.
And I loved it. I can remember going
to the premiere here in New York
and I was like,
"That was so funny."
People didn't seem to
think it was that funny.
It's taken me many years
to actually get the film.
I mean, I liked it,
but then I liked it more.
And it wasn't until the fourth time,
I think I saw it with my son...
You might want to watch
out that front window, Larry.
...that I realized
how hilarious the film is.
Son, this is what happens when
you fuck a stranger in the ass!
And over the years, I think it's kind of
gotten the attention that it deserves.
JEFF BRIDGES: I rarely will
watch a movie of mine on TV,
but Lebowski,
when that comes on,
it'll hook me, you know,
because there are so many
little flavorful parts about it.
That rug really tied the room
together, did it not?
It's a great film to discover. There's a lot
of support out there for those discoverers,
for those little urban achievers or
whatever you want to call yourselves.
MOORE: I always say that it's sort of a
Rorschach test, what movies people remember.
When you walk down the street and
somebody says, "Hey I loved you in..."
And I first noticed it
happening with college guys.
And it's sort of
the frat boy kind of thing.
When a young man came by, who was 21,
22, it was always The Big Lebowski.
...without batting an eye, a man will refer
to his dick, or his rod or his Johnson.
What they say, they either point
at me and scream "Roseanne!"
Or call me Tom Arnold, or they'll
whip out a line from Lebowski.
The lines are very whippable.
Smokey, my friend, you're
entering a world of pain.
Every time John says,
"Shut the fuck up, Donny."
You know, I just love that.
Shut the fuck up, Donny!
"Shut the fuck up, Donny."
That's a big one.
Donny, you're out
of your element.
Dude, the Chinaman
is not the issue here.
One of my favorite images
in the film is
when John Turturro
was cleaning his bowling ball.
It's semi-obscene,
and I don't even know why.
TURTURRO: I get mail from
all kinds of people,
and I get all kinds of weird
sex mail from women and men.
This is it!
Let's take that hill!
"Dude, slow it down, when we
hit 15 mph, I'm rolling out."
And he has an Uzi wrapped up in paper,
which, naturally, destroys the car.
Hey! Hey! Careful, man!
There's a beverage here!
DUDE: Let me just praise my own work.
I love, "I got a beverage here."
You know, I get stuck
into the limo there,
and when I'm trying to describe the new
shit that's come to light, you know?
I mean, it's not just... It might not
be just such a simple... You know?
I tried to be
very faithful to the script.
I didn't want to add any extra
"man's" or any extra "fuck's,"
or even the ellipses that the
guys put in there, you know?
I wanted to put the pauses
where those were.
MOORE: In the Coen brothers movie, the
language is always so wonderful, so rich.
Their language is so specific that
you would do something and then
Ethan and Joel will say, "Okay, now do it
again, but leave out these two words."
So you just kind of change... The cadence
of the sentence would be changed.
They did a great job in creating
the rhythm of the dialog.
Saturday, Donny, is shabbos,
the Jewish day of rest.
That means I don't work, I don't drive
a car, I don't fucking ride in a car,
I don't handle money,
I don't turn on the oven
and I sure as shit
don't fucking roll!
It's very, kind of, old movie style. People
have to rattle off all this exposition
and do it quickly and with a
certain amount of humor and style.
GOODMAN: We got that, I think,
during the rehearsal.
We just got used to
each other's rhythms.
We all know who is at fault here, so
what the fuck are you talking about?
People always ask me
if it was improvised.
No. God, no. But it was the pauses,
there's, you know, line dot dot dot.
And so, sometimes to discover
the truth of the scene,
we would improvise during rehearsal, to
figure out, put it in your own words.
But I tried to always
go back to the script.
MAN: Six Baker. Take two, mark.
And action.
BRIDGES: To have a mind behind your character,
like Joel and Ethan, it's a wonderful gift.
I have a brother, who I love very much.
We had a good time working together.
But to imagine directing a film with
Beau, my brother, would be very tough.
Because, you know,
we have very strong opinions,
and we approach things
in slightly different ways.
And I asked Joel,
"How do you guys do it?"
He says, in the writing of it,
they've been working on this,
and they've honed and they've had
all their discussions and arguments
if they had any, you know, that kind
of thing to work it all out prior.
So when they came to the directing
part, it was all pretty much in place.
And they were just kind of open to see
what else anybody else had to say.
They know who they wanna work with.
They know exactly what they wanna do.
And it makes for
a very wonderful atmosphere.
MOORE: I think that was the thing
that I found really amazing.
They seem to be in complete
harmony, in accord, always.
And sometimes Joel would talk to you,
and sometimes Ethan would talk to you.
And I thought, well, they'll come up
together, there will be some discussion.
But it just doesn't work that way. One
will talk and then the other will talk
and they seemed to be
on the same page.
BRIDGES: The big disagreement that
I can remember between the two
was in the dream sequence when my head
is about to hit the bowling balls.
Joel, who would kind of be the
point man, as far as directing...
He would usually be the guy
who would...
Although Ethan would be
kind of flitting around,
and he would add
his thoughts as well.
But Joel said, "Now, when
you hit the bowling balls,
"you're kind of grimacing when
you hit the bowling balls."
And Ethan came up and he said,
"Grimacing, really?
"I thought he'd be smiling.
He would kind of enjoy it."
Joel said, "No, I think..."
Ethan said, "Really? Well."
And Ethan kind of looked,
and then there was...
"Well, let's shoot it
both ways. Okay."
And that's basically the biggest
disagreement they'd ever had.
TURTURRO: it's actually interesting
the way they do things.
'Cause it's a Mom and Pop candy store.
One-stop shopping.
And they're involved with every
little thing, and everything counts.
MOORE: Their specificity
of vision, the way they shoot,
the way the production design
is, the script...
Three pigs in blanket.
...their shots,
everything is so deliberate.
GOODMAN: They're very specific about
things they talk about, like an iron lung
or a Ziploc bag
with somebody's homework.
These things are
almost iconic now,
but they're just very simple things
just put in very strange ways.
In an odd sort of way, you're
just incredibly relaxed,
because everything is
taken care of all the time.
BRIDGES: On the set, the environment
that they created was so loose,
that you felt like you had
all the time in the world.
You could try it this way,
you could try it that way.
They were always very inclusive,
wanted to know, you know,
"You got any ideas?
What do you wanna do?"
BUSCEMI: I think just two
very down-to-earth guys,
and they love what they do,
and I love to work with them.
Working with those guys
is a joy. It's a joy.
BRIDGES: When I watch The Big Lebowski, I
love the story and all the characters,
but for me, it's very hard to
separate it from my own life.
There's a bit of a home movie
aspect to it even when I watch it,
'cause I remember what
we had for lunch that day,
or what the other takes were.
BUSCEMI: The whole movie
was just easy to do.
I don't remember there being anything hard about it.
We just had a great time.
Donny, please.
It was a once
in a lifetime deal.
Characters like Walter
don't come along every day.
I've seen a lot of spinals,
Dude, and this guy's a fake.
If this is what I'll be remembered
for, then that's aces with me.
I think it's just wonderful.
It's one of my favorite movies.
Not only the movies I've been in, but
just flat out one of my favorite movies.
TURTURRO: College kids are not going to
classes because of The Big Lebowski.
And I blame this all
on Joel and Ethan.
I think they're recognizing it for what it is.
It's a brilliant film.
And that's why our society is in crisis.
'Cause of The Big Lebowski.
You don't need the marijuana
to watch the movie, kids.
It's good without it.
TURTURRO: The Dude.
What kind of example is he?
The Dude abides.
It goes on forever.
This stuff could never end.
Who knows what happened
to Walter?
He could have become a priest
or something like that.
Maybe there'll be
a Lebowski Junior.
'Cause he's 10 years old now.
I wonder where that dude is today, must
be about 10 years old now, you know.
I wonder what he's doing.
Probably selling pot to
all his friends. I don't know.