EDDIE CHUNG: After a long day
at work in the spring of 2004,
I met up with a
friend at the bar.
Pissed, tired and just uptight,
I was in need for a beer.
Three in, I discovered he and a couple
of buddies were heading to Las Vegas
for a far-out convention
called the Lebowski Festival.
I had seen The Big Lebowski
when it first came out,
but like many, I did not
get the grandeur of the movie.
Curious, I packed up my camera
gear and set off to Lost Wages,
expecting nothing,
but hoping for everything.
Take it easy with the camera, man.
Just take it easy, man.
You name me one movie that has
so many touches of life in it.
Nothing is lost in this movie.
You know, we're the only
four people in the world
who really have a big
following for this movie.
A guy went overseas...
I know the story.
And the guy, he was sitting
in a bar in the UK,
and he was kind of venting to
the bartender, as people do.
And he turned to the bartender, and
he goes, "Friends like these men."
And then the bartender kind of looked
up, and his eyes kind of sprouted,
and they're like,
"Friends like these."
And they began to quote
Lebowski quotes all night.
CHUNG: Now, the story unfolded when
Will Russell and Scott Shuffitt
decided to riff fines from
the movie The Big Lebowski
and noticed people
were riffing back.
So goes the idea of a fest.
In the most unlikely of places,
a Baptist-run bowling alley,
Will and Scott opened the doors
to the very first Lebowski Fest.
My name is Scott Shuffitt,
I am co-producer
of the first annual Big
Lebowski What Have You Fest
being held in the Fellowship
Lanes, Louisville, Kentucky.
Will Russell,
official Louisvillian.
Scott and I, about three months
ago, we were vending a convention
for the Mothership Connection.
They knew those Lebowski lines,
and we began to realize that
there was a community out there,
a very, very 'large community of people
with feeling towards a fantastic movie
that was created
by the Coen Brothers.
Someone said we should have
a Big Lebowski convention.
It happened.
And then it was just
like... I was, like...
The next thing you know,
we were taking notes.
The bowling alley that we
picked was the Fellowship Lanes,
which was a Baptist-run
bowling alley.
They had a big sigh at the door
when we walked in that said,
"No Cussing. “
They also allowed no drinking,
but they smoked lots of cigarettes,
and they sold all the hot dogs,
so those Baptists
were very happy.
Fellowship Lanes. We should have a
dress-as-your-favorite-character contest.
Highest bowling score.
It really just... It wrote itself.
We put up a website,
and it was just unbelievable
the response we got.
Fantastic.
Yesterday, we had, like, 160
unique visitors to the site.
Everybody is just
in love with this idea.
The media.
The bowling guy.
So, I'm Mike Walsh. I am driving around
the country, bowling in all 50 states,
and I came here, kind of out of my way.
I was scheduled to be bowling
with some funeral directors
in South Jersey tonight,
but I heard about the
party through my website.
Someone e-mailed me about
this one, so I checked out
the Big Lebowski website,
and I couldn't miss it.
Anyone who's bothering
to throw a party
on the shady side of
Louisville has got my vote.
I understand this is the First
Annual, and with a lot of things,
they never happen again the second time,
but I can feel there is a vibe here,
and you know that this thing
is going to last for 50 years,
and I'll be damned
if I miss one.
CHUNG: So it began.
(PEOPLE CHEERING)
Two guys from Louisville, Kentucky,
planted the seed for a social phenomenon.
The concept is simple. Gather fans, bowl,
drink like Russians, and just be Dude.
You see what happens?
This is what happens.
And, eventually, the media caught
on to spread the Lebowski lexicon.
We were driving to her
parents' house when I found out
that we were in Spin magazine, which
was probably the biggest moment
in Lebowski Fest history so far.
We were mentioned as one of
the 19 events you can't miss
with, like, Lollapalooza, and Bonnaroo,
and fucking Warped Tour and Ozzfest.
It was unbelievable.
This is what The Big Lebowski does,
is it brings people together
from the far
corners of the world.
Even if those corners are just North Carolina
and Kentucky, it brings them together
in the spirit of goodwill
and friendship.
An Achiever is the
self-applied title
of someone who is a fan
of The Big Lebowski.
It doesn't matter what you're
into as far as your job,
or what kind of music
you're into.
You could walk up to
pretty much any Achiever
and just start up
a conversation.
They are a very diverse
group of folks.
I mean, you'll have from a
layabout to judges, professionals.
CHUNG: What do you guys
do for a living?
I'm actually a district attorney, but
I don't want to say where 'cause...
And I have a white-collar
job in Atlanta as well.
I work in advertising.
I'm a whore.
(ALL LAUGH)
Well, to me, Achiever has kind
of taken on a new air about it
since I've started my first
real job this past fall,
and I have the forum to
get me through the day,
and these people are really funny.
They're great folks.
I can't wait to go to Louisville.
I haven't been to Louisville yet,
and I'm looking
forward to going.
CHUNG: In the summer of that same year, I
went to Louisville for the first time.
Dios mio, man.
What I found there was every bit as
stupefying as 5 had ever seen before.
What started as a one-day event
took on a carnival atmosphere.
Over 4,000 people attended,
not exactly a lightweight.
Some of the local Achievers
took me across the river to
their private residence
in Indiana
and their friendliness
was overwhelming.
My name's Andy Cheney.
I post to the forum with all the
other fellow Achievers here.
At my house in Indiana, it's the cookout,
the forum cookout, before the movie.
And there's plenty of burgers,
there's plenty of beer,
and thanks to our other fellow Achievers,
there's plenty of White Russians to have.
It's a good time, and
there's dogs to play with.
The best way I've always been
able to put Lebowski Fest
is imagine the best party you've
ever gone to, and then double it,
and I think last night is
a perfect example of that,
just a group of people
getting together,
things getting pretty, what could
be considered out of hand,
but it's still just,
like, a good time.
Everyone's really friendly
with each other.
Our troubles are fucking over, and
then we're going to the movie.
It's a way of life.
CHUNG: A year later, the
festival came to my hometown,
Los Angeles, the City of Angels.
Jeff “the Dude" Dowd, who was the
inspiration for the character, the Dude,
made an appearance, along with some
of the other actors from the movie.
If you ask me, this whole thing
is about friendship, new friends
and forever-going-on
friendship.
My name's Jerry Haleva.
I'm in the dream sequence,
and so I'm trying to convey Saddam as
if he's working at this bowling alley.
They said, "How about coming to the
Lebowski Fest down in Los Angeles?"
And I said, "Great!"
I had not been familiar
with the Lebowski Fest,
and then I was invited to come down to
the one in Lakewood a year or so ago.
I'm sort of driving along,
and I see all these people.
I've described it to people as,
clearly, the only place I've ever gone
where I felt like a rock star.
And it dawned on me, 'cause I could see these
guys with bathrobes on and flip-flops.
And it wasn't about, again, that
I play Saddam in the movies,
it was that I was Saddam
in The Big Lebowski.
So, I thought, "They're going to jump
on my car, they're going to swamp me."
That group of people,
everybody knew who I was.
Well, everybody was just the
opposite of what I thought.
My friend, he lives in
Portland, and he was like,
"I tell people I'm
from Kentucky,
“and they're, like, 'That's
where Lebowski Fest is from."'
And I'm like, "Fucking A. That
is what I'm talking about,
“putting Louisville on the map
as the home of Lebowski Fest
"instead of some backwoods
kind of hick thing, you know."
We're ready to throw some
rocks, knock some pins.
Maybe harass a few 8-year-olds.
Let's see what happens.
MAN 1: Saddam!
MAN 2: Bring the Seattle
Seven, too.
Hey, Seattle Seven, come over.
Tim!
There he is.
We found our party.
MAN 3: This is our spot, man.
Apparently, I am standing in the
line you can see behind me,
waiting to get into the Lebowski
Fest bowling extravaganza.
The line is currently very long,
indicating that it is obviously the
most popular part of the festival.
I'm apparently dressed as Saddam Hussein,
which has a very small part in the movie
and hands out the bowling shoes
during a dream sequence to the Dude.
Now, the mustache I am wearing
is made of real human hair,
which I did not realize until
after I had purchased it.
It's also made in Korea,
so yeah.
I just don't want to think of
where this hair has come from.
And it's applied with spirit gum, so
I really shouldn't smoke anything
'cause I will burn.
CHUNG: When released in 1998, The Big
Lebowski did not fill many seats,
but that was then.
Years later, the movie found its
audience and became a cult sensation,
to use the parlance of our time.
To my amazement, the costumes begin
to take on a cerebral element,
delving into the minds of
the characters from the movie.
Last year, I went as the walrus,
and that is from the scene
where Donny mistakenly takes the quote
by Lenin as being by John Lennon,
so he keeps saying, "I am the walrus.
I am the walrus."
So I came as a walrus. It's getting
hard to find a good costume.
Everything's been done, so you got to
really try hard to find a good costume.
Why did you dress
up like Sandy Koufax?
'Cause Walter says in the movie,
"Damned right he's Jewish.
"3,000 years of beautiful tradition
from Moses to Sandy Koufax."
So we had to be the span
of Moses to Sandy Koufax.
And Brian's also one of his buddies
who died facedown in the mud,
so we represent
Walter's subconscious.
Well, I was inspired by
the Lebowski Fest West.
I saw a girl dressed
up as the toe,
and I thought, "Well, if you can be the
toe, you can be anything in the movie."
Who's in the movie
more than Jeff?
The Caucasian.
So here we are. You can't have a
Lebowski Fest without the Caucasian.
Eddie! Eddie!
ALL: (CHANTING) Eddie! Eddie!
CHUNG: After years of filming,
I discovered the Achievers
embraced me as one of their own.
Without even realizing it, I had a
character to play in this whole scene,
the Chinaman with the camera.
Excuse me, camera-American.
There's only one documentarian, and
that documentarian's name is Eddie.
So many bullshit
documentaries going on.
Johnny-come-lately
wannabe motherfuckers.
They don't got the
fucking street credit
of the one and only real
Lebowski Fest documentary.
Did you guys ever hear
of the Seattle Seven?
That's the Dude, and six other guys.
We traveled all the way from Seattle.
Seattle Seven right there.
It started out as a
fucking Vietnam protest,
but then it just turned into
a fucking bowling team now.
It's bigger.
It's bigger. We just drink old sodas and
White Russians and just get her done.
The Big Lebowski.
CHUNG: The fest went to the city
where the other Jeffrey Lebowski,
the real Dude,
protested the man,
marking his place in the
American cultural revolution.
When I was first asked to
go to what was the second
Lebowski Festival in Louisville,
I was very surprised, I mean,
really surprised, by what I saw.
What you saw there,
which was really great,
was all these people gathering
together and making new friends.
But I met couples and people who were
secretaries and doctors and students
and, you know, all kinds
of different people.
The film got to them.
CHUNG: I realize now that the Fest is more
than just a celebration of the movie.
It breaks down barriers and
builds lifelong friendships.
Andy's wife said it best.
It is a way of life.
One more festival ends.
The last I will photograph, but definitely
not the last one to come as an Achiever.
These fuckers behind the camera,
they're married, they have kids,
and they're trying to get
some kind of shit on us.
All right? This is
some wholesome stuff.
Hey, hey, Travis.
Huh? How about your real name, Travis?
Travis. How do you like that?
It's on camera, isn't it?
We know it is.
Travis. Yeah. You're
gonna edit that out?
Some things that
we call "secrets"...
What are you laughing
about, Ronnie,
the sound guy?
Really aren't "secrets."
Yeah? You should see these two,
what they did last night. Huh?
It was dangerous.
I mean, porn stars
wouldn't go that low.
Dangerous.
How about that?
The truth is out now.
You got the camera
all pointed on us.
Look at these guys.
Just a note, here. Just a note,
this guy's totally unprepared.
He has no list of questions.
I mean, he's a total slacker,
alienated, Lebowski guy.
Just a note, here. This is
who comes to interview me.
All right?
Nothing. Nothing.