RENTON: Choose life. Choose a job.
Choose a career. Choose a family.
Choose a fucking big television.
Choose washing machines, cars,
compact disc players,
electrical tin openers.
(TYRES SCREECHING)
(SPUD SHOUTING)
(LAUGHING)
Choose good health,
low cholesterol and dental insurance.
Choose fixed-interest
mortgage repayments.
Choose a starter home.
Choose your friends.
Choose leisure wear
and matching luggage.
Choose a three-piece suite
on hire purchase
in a range of fucking fabrics.
Choose DIY and wondering who the fuck
you are on a Sunday morning.
Choose sitting on a couch watching
mind-numbing, spirit-crushing game shows
stuffing fucking junk food
into your mouth.
(SHOUTING)
Tommy, go!
RENTON: Choose rotting away
at the end of it,
pissing your last in a miserable home,
nothing more than an embarrassment
to the selfish fucked-up brats
that you've spawned to replace yourself.
Choose your future. Choose life.
But why would I want to do
a thing like that?
I chose not to choose life.
I chose something else. And the reasons?
There are no reasons.
Who needs reasons
when you've got heroin?
(GURGLING)
SICk BOY: Goldfinger
is better than Dr. No.
Both of them are a lot better
than Diamonds Are Forever.
A judgement reflected in its relatively
poor showing at the box office.
And in which field, of course,
Thunderballwas a notable success.
RENTON: People think
it's all about misery,
desperation and death,
and all that shite
which is not to be ignored.
Fuck off! Jealous cunt.
(INDISTINCT)
RENTON: But what they forget
is the pleasure of it.
They're all dead like meat.
(LAUGHING)
SICk BOY: You prick!
RENTON: Otherwise we wouldn't do it.
-Do you want me to do it?
-Yeah.
Pure as the driven snow, that shit.
(LAUGHING)
RENTON: After all,
we're not fucking stupid.
At least we're not that fucking stupid.
(SIGHING)
(MOANING)
Take the best orgasm you ever had,
multiply it by a thousand
and you're still nowhere near it.
It beats any meat injection.
That beats any fucking cock
in the world.
RENTON: When you're on junk,
you have only one worry. Scoring.
When you're off it,
you're suddenly obliged to worry
about all sorts of other shite.
Got no money, can't get pissed.
Got money, drinking too much.
Can't get a girl, no chance of a ride.
Got a girl, too much hassle.
You have to worry about bills,
about food,
about some football team
that never fucking wins,
about human relationships, and all
the things that really don't matter
when you've got
a sincere and truthfuljunk habit.
I'd say, in those days,
he was a muscular actor.
With all the presence of someone
like Cooper or Lancaster,
but combined with a sly wit
to make him a formidable romantic lead
and closer in that respect
to Cary Grant.
(MOANING)
(GROWLING)
RENTON: The only drawback,
or at least the principal drawback,
is that you have to endure
all manner of cunts telling you that...
No way would I poison my body
with that shit.
All them fucking chemicals.
No fucking way.
It's a waste of your life, man,
poisoning your body with that shit.
Every chance you've had, Son,
you've blown it.
Stuffing your veins with that filth.
RENTON: From time to time,
even I have uttered the magic words.
Never again, Swanney. I'm off the skag.
-Are you serious?
-Yeah.
-No more. I'm finished with that shite.
-Well, that's up to you, man.
I'll do it right this time.
I'm gonna get it sorted out.
-I'll get off it for good.
-I've heard that one before.
The Sick Boy method.
It really worked for him, eh?
He's always been lacking in moral fibre.
-He knows a lot about Sean Connery.
-That's hardly a substitute.
You need one more hit.
-No, I don't think so.
-For the long night that lies ahead.
RENTON: We called him Mother Superior
on account of the length of his habit.
Of course I'd have another shot.
After all, I had work to do.
(DOOR OPENS)
RENTON: Relinquishing junk.
Stage one, preparation.
For this you will need one room,
which you will not leave.
Soothing music.
Tomato soup, ten tins of.
Mushroom soup, eight tins of,
for consumption cold.
Ice cream, vanilla, one large tub of.
Magnesia, milk of, one bottle.
Paracetamol, mouthwash,
vitamins, mineral water, Lucozade,
pornography.
One mattress.
One bucket for urine, one for faeces,
and one for vomitus.
One television and one bottle of Valium,
which I've already procured
from my mother, who is,
in her own domestic and socially
acceptable way, also a drug addict.
Now I'm ready.
All I need is one final hit
to soothe the pain
while the Valium takes effect.
Mikey. Aye, it's Mark Renton.
Look, I wondered, could you help me out?
This was typical of Mikey Forrester.
What the fuck are these?
Under the normal run of things
I'd have nothing to do with the cunt,
but this wasn't
the normal run of things.
Opium suppositories.
Ideal for your purposes.
Slow release, bring you down gradually.
Custom fucking designed for your needs.
I want a fucking hit.
That's all I've got, man.
Take it or leave it.
You're feeling better now, eh?
Oh, aye. For all the good
they've done me,
I might as well have
stuck them up my arse.
Heroin makes you constipated.
The heroin from my last hit
is fading away,
and the suppositories have yet to melt.
(GROANS)
I'm no longer constipated.
(RACING COMMENTARY ON TV)
I fantasise about a massive,
pristine convenience,
brilliant gold taps,
virginal white marble,
a seat carved from ebony,
a cistern full of Chanel No. 5
and a flunky handing me
pieces of raw silk toilet roll.
But under the circumstances,
I'll settle for anywhere.
(ELECTRICITY CRACKLING)
(FLIES BUZZING)
(GROANS)
Ugh!
Fuck.
(GROANING)
(SPLATTERING)
(SIGHING)
(CHUCKLES IN RELIEF)
(SPLATTERING CONTINUES)
(RETCHING)
(SPITTING)
Yes, you fucking dancer!
(GASPING)
(SQUELCHING)
And now,
now I'm ready.
The downside of coming offjunk was
I knew I'd need
to mix with my friends again
in a state of full consciousness.
It was awful.
They reminded me so much of myself,
I could hardly bear to look at them.
Take Sick Boy, for instance.
He came offjunk at the same time as me
not because he wanted to,
but just to annoy me.
Just to show me
how easily he could do it,
thereby downgrading my own struggle.
Sneaky fucker, don't you think?
When all I wanted to do was lie there
and feel sorry for myself,
he insisted on telling me once again
about his unifying theory of life.
It's certainly a phenomenon
in all walks of life.
What do you mean?
Well, at one point you've got it,
then you lose it, and it's gone forever,
all walks of life.
Georgie Best, for example,
had it, lost it.
Or David Bowie, or Lou Reed.
RENTON: Lou Reed,
some of his solo stuff is not bad.
No, it's not bad,
but it's not great either, is it?
In your heart, you know that
although it sounds all right,
it's actually just shite.
So, who else?
Charlie Nicholas, David Niven,
Malcolm McLaren, Elvis Presley.
Okay, so what's the point
you're trying to make?
All I am trying to do is to help you
understand that The Name ofthe Rose
is merely a blip on an otherwise
uninterrupted downward trajectory.
What about The Untouchables?
I don't rate that at all.
Despite the Academy award?
That means fuck all.
It's a sympathy vote.
So, we all get old,
we can't hack it any more and that's it?
Yeah.
That's your theory?
Beautifully fucking illustrated.
Give me the gun.
SICK BOY: (IMPERSONATING SEAN CONNERY)
Do you see the beast?
Have you got it in your sights?
(IMPERSONATING SEAN CONNERY)
Clear enough, Miss Moneypenny.
This should present
no significant problems.
(DOG YELPING)
(BARKING)
(MAN SHOUTING)
For a vegetarian, Rents,
you're a fucking evil shot.
RENTON: Without heroin,
I attempted to lead
a useful and fulfilling life
as a good citizen.
(ALL SLURPING)
(BURPING)
-Good luck, Spud.
-Cheers.
Remember, if they think you're
not trying, you're in trouble.
A hint of that and they'll be on to
the DHSS, "This cunt is not trying."
And your Giro's fucking finished, right?
Right.
-But then again, try too hard...
-You might get the fucking job.
-Exactly.
-Nightmare.
It's a tightrope, Spud.
It's a fucking tightrope.
I just get pure shy
with the interviewer cats.
I get all nervous and I can't answer
any of their questions
like I'm a footballer
and I get nerves on the big occasion.
Try some of this.
A little dab of speed
is just the ticket, man.
No, I went to Craigie, Craignewton.
I just put down Royal Edinburgh College
to help get the job.
There's too much discrimination.
They're both schools, right?
We're in this together,
and I wanted to put across
the general idea
rather than the details.
People get hung up on details.
Which school did I go to?
How many grades did I get?
Could be six, could be none.
It's not important.
What is important is that I am.
Mr Murphy, do you mean
that you lied on your application?
No! Well, yes.
Only to get my foot in the door.
Showing initiative and that, like.
You were referred here
by the Department of Employment.
There was no need for you to get
your "foot in the door" as you put it.
Yeah, cool. Whatever you say.
Sorry, you're the man,
the dude in the chair.
I am merely here. Obviously, I'm here.
Mr Murphy, what exactly attracts you
to the leisure industry?
In a word, pleasure.
My pleasure in other people's leisure.
Do you see yourself
as having any weaknesses?
Yes! I'm a bit of a perfectionist,
actually. Yes, I am.
See, for me, it's got to be the best
or it's nothing at all.
Like, if things get a bit dodgy,
I just cannot be bothered.
But, hey, I'm getting good vibes
about this interview thing today.
Seems to me like
it's going pretty well, eh?
Thank you, Mr Murphy.
We'll let you know.
The pleasure was mine, man.
RENTON: Spud had done well,
I was proud of him.
He fucked up good and proper.
You had to hand it to Spud.
Picture the scene.
The other fucking week there
down the fucking Volley.
Me and Tommy playing pool.
I'm playing like Paul fucking Newman,
by the way.
Giving the boy here
the tanning of a lifetime.
So it comes to the end, the last shot,
the deciding ball
of the whole tournament.
I'm on the black
and he's sat in the corner
looking all fucking biscuit-arsed
when this hard cunt comes in,
obviously fucking fancied himself.
Starts staring at me,
looking right fucking at me
as if to say, "Come ahead, square go."
You know me. I'm not the type
that goes looking for fucking bother,
but at the end of the day,
I'm the cunt with the pool cue
and he can get the fat end in his puss
any time he fucking wanted, like.
So I squares up, casual like.
What does the hard cunt do?
Or the so-called hard cunt. Shites it,
puts down his drink, turns and gets
the fuck out of there, and after that,
well, the game was mine.
RENTON: And that was it.
That was Begbie's story. Or at least
that was Begbie's version of the story.
A couple of days later
I got the truth from Tommy.
You always got the truth from Tommy.
It was one of his major weaknesses.
He never told lies, he never took drugs,
and he never cheated on anyone.
It was Wednesday morning.
We were in the Volley playing pool,
that much is true.
But Begbie is playing
absolutely fucking gash.
He's got a hangover so bad
he can hardly hold the fucking cue,
never mind pot a ball.
I'm doing my best to lose, you know,
trying to humour him.
But it's not doing any good.
Every time I touch a ball,
I seem to pot something.
Every time Begbie goes near the table,
he fucks it up.
Oh, fuck's sake.
So, he's got the hump, right.
But, finally, I managed to set it up
so all he has to do is to pot the black
to win one game,
to salvage a little bit of pride
and maybe not kick my head in, right.
So, he's on the black, pressure shot.
(RUSTLING)
Then it all goes wrong, big time.
Fuck!
(GROANING)
TOMMY: He picks on this specky wee gadge
at the bar
and accuses him of putting him off
by looking at him.
I couldn't believe it. The poor cunt
hasn't even glanced in our direction.
Fuck off!
TOMMY: He was going to chib him,
I tell you.
Then I thought he was going to do me.
The beggar is fucking psycho, man.
But he's a mate, you know.
So what can you do?
Can I borrow this?
RENTON: What, indeed, could one do?
Just stand back and watch,
and try not to get involved?
(GLASS SHATTERS)
(WOMAN SCREAMING)
Begbie didn't do drugs either.
He just did people,
that's what he got off on.
His own sensory addiction.
(SCREAMING)
(MAN SHOUTING)
The lassie got glassed
and no cunt leaves here
till we find out what cunt did it.
Who the fuck are you?
(SHOUTING)
(GROANING)
(MEN SHOUTING)
(WOMEN SCREAMING)
(ALL CLAMOURING)
(GLASS SHATTERING)
(THUDDING)
(HEAVY BREATHING)
-Lizzy, it's so good.
-I'm coming.
RENTON: As I sat watching the intimate
and highly personal video
stolen only hours earlier
from one of my best friends,
I realised that something important
was missing from my life.
(DISCO MUSIC PLAYING ON STEREO)
(TOMMY SPEAKING)
(SPUD SPEAKING)
-I read it in Cosmopolitan.
-It's an interesting theory.
Actually, it's a nightmare.
I've been desperate for a shag
but watching him suffer
was just too much fun.
You should try it with Tommy.
What, and deny myself
the only pleasure I get from him?
Did I tell you about my birthday?
-No, what happened?
-He forgot. Useless motherfucker.
BOTH: What are you two talking about?
BOTH: Football.
What are you talking about?
Shopping.
RENTON: The situation
was becoming serious.
Young Renton noticed the haste
with which the successful
in the sexual sphere, as in all others,
segregated themselves from the failures.
Heroin had robbed Renton
of his sex drive,
but now it returned with a vengeance.
As the impotence of those days
faded into memory,
grim desperation took a hold
in his sex-crazed mind.
His post-junk libido,
fuelled by alcohol and amphetamine
taunted him remorselessly
with his own unsatisfied desire.
Dot, dot, dot.
(INAUDIBLE)
And with that,
Mark Renton had fallen in love.
Excuse me. I don't mean to harass you,
but I was very impressed
with your capable and stylish manner
of dealing with that situation.
I was thinking to myself,
"Now, this girl's special."
Thanks.
-What's your name?
-Diane.
-Where are you going, Diane?
-I'm going home.
-Where's that?
-It's where I live.
-Great.
-What?
I'll come back with you if you like,
but I'm not promising anything.
Do you find
that this approach usually works?
Or let me guess,
you've never tried it before.
In fact, you don't normally
approach girls, am I right?
The truth is that you're a quiet,
sensitive type,
but if I'm prepared to take a chance,
I might just get to know the inner you.
Witty, adventurous,
passionate, loving, loyal.
(CAR APPROACHING)
Taxi!
A little bit crazy, a little bit bad.
But, hey,
don't us girls just love that?
Eh?
Well, what's wrong, boy?
Cat got your tongue?
I left something...
Are you getting in or not, pal?
Do you understand? I expect you to be
a considerate and thoughtful lover.
-Generous but firm.
-What?
Failure on your part to live up
to these very reasonable expectations
will result in swift resumption
of a non-sex situation.
Right?
Diane.
(DIANE SHUSHING)
-What?
-DIANE: (WHISPERING) Shut up!
Wake up, Spud.
Wake up.
Sex.
Casual sex.
(SNORING)
Tommy, let's put the tape on.
Now?
I want to watch ourselves
while we're screwing.
So, let's see what I'm missing.
(MOANING)
Not much.
COMMENTATOR ON TV:
There's the captain, Archie Gemmill,
picking it up from the outside.
I think he wants to go himself.
Is he gonna go?
He's going all the way. And he scores!
What a magnificent goal!
Gemmill at his very best.
What a penetrating goal that was!
(EXCLAIMS)
I haven't felt that good since Archie
Gemmill scored against Holland in 1 978.
(SPECTATORS CHEERING)
DIANE: Right.
You can't sleep here.
-What?
-Out.
Come on.
No argument. You can sleep on the sofa
in the hall or go home, it's up to you.
And don't make any noise.
Jesus.
LIZZY: What do you mean, "It's gone"?
Where has it gone, Tommy?
It'll be here somewhere.
-I might have returned it by mistake.
-Returned it?
Where? The video shop, Tommy?
The fucking video shop?
So every punter in Edinburgh
is jerking off to our video?
God, Tommy, I feel sick.
(WINDOW RATTLING)
(FLY BUZZING)
(DIANE SINGING)
(SHOWER RUNNING)
(BICYCLE BELL RINGING)
-MAN: Hi.
-Hello.
Fuck.
(MUMBLING INCOHERENTLY)
(WHIMPERING)
(EXCLAIMING)
Eh?
(MUSIC PLAYING ON RADIO)
Come in and sit down.
MAN: Like some coffee?
Aye.
-You must be Mark.
-Aye, that's me.
-Are you a friend of Diane's?
-More a friend of a friend.
Right.
Are you her flatmates?
(CHUCKLING)
Flatmates?
I must remember that one.
DIANE: Morning.
(CHATTERING)
-Good morning, Spud.
-Morning, Gail.
Mr Houston. Mrs Houston.
Morning, Spud.
Sit down and have some breakfast.
Sorry about last night, by the way.
That's all right.
I slept fine on the sofa.
I had a bit much to drink,
had a bit of an accident.
Don't worry, son. These things happen.
Does a man good
to cut loose once in a while.
This one could do with being tied up
once in a while.
-I'll put the sheets in the machine now.
-No, I'll wash them.
-There's no need.
-It's no problem.
It's no problem for me, either.
-I'd rather take care of it myself.
-Honestly, it's no problem.
-Really, no!
-Spud, they're my sheets.
-DIANE: I don't see why not.
-Because it's illegal, that's why not.
-DIANE: What, holding hands?
-No, not holding hands.
In that case, you can do it.
You were quite happy
to do a lot more last night.
That's what's illegal.
Do you know what they do
to people like me inside?
They cut your balls off
and flush them down the fucking toilet.
-Calm down. You're not going to jail.
-That's very easy for you to say, Diane.
-Can I see you again?
-Certainly not.
If you don't see me again,
I'll tell the police.
I'll see you around then.
(BELL RINGING)
Now what?
We go for a walk.
-What?
-A walk.
-Where?
-There.
Are you serious?
What are you waiting for?
Hey, Tommy.
This is not natural, man.
It's the great outdoors.
It's fresh air.
Look, Tommy, we know
you're getting a hard time off Lizzy,
but there's really no need
to take it out on us.
Doesn't it make you proud
to be Scottish?
It's shite being Scottish.
We're the lowest of the low.
The scum of the fucking earth.
The most wretched, miserable,
servile, pathetic trash
that was ever shat into civilisation.
Some people hate the English, I don't.
They're just wankers.
We, on the other hand,
are colonised by wankers.
Can't even find a decent culture
to be colonised by.
We're ruled by effete arseholes.
It's a shite state of affairs to be in,
Tommy.
And all the fresh air in the world
won't make any fucking difference.
SPUD: Sorry, man. Sorry.
No, I'm sorry.
I appreciate it, Tommy.
RENTON: At or around this time
Spud, Sick Boy and I made a healthy,
informed, democratic decision
to get back on heroin
as soon as possible.
Took about 1 2 hours.
(CHATTERING)
It looks easy, this, but it's not.
It looks like a doss,
like a soft option,
but living like this,
it's a full-time business.
(CAR ALARM BLARING)
SICK BOY: Ursula Andress,
the quintessential Bond girl.
That's what everyone says.
The embodiment, right,
of his superiority to us.
Beautiful, exotic, highly sexual,
yet totally unavailable
to anyone apart from him.
Shite. I mean, let's face it,
if she'd shag one punter from Edinburgh,
she'd shag the whole fucking lot of us.
(MUFFLED LAUGHTER ON TV)
Yep, I knew he was going to do that.
Lizzy's gone, Mark.
She's gone and fucking dumped me.
It was that videotape.
That Iggy Pop business
and all sorts of other shit.
She told me where to go
and no fucking mistake.
I said to her, I said,
"Is there any chance
of getting back together?"
But no fucking way.
Honor Blackman,
a.k.a. Pussy Galore, right?
What a total fucking misnomer.
I mean, I wouldn't touch her with yours.
I want to try it, Mark.
You're always going on about
how it's like the ultimate hit.
Better than sex.
Come on, man, I'm a fucking adult,
I can find out for myself.
I've got the money.
Personality, I mean,
that's what counts, right?
Personality, I mean that's what keeps
a relationship going through the years.
Like heroin.
I mean,
heroin's got great fucking personality.
RENTON: Swanney taught us to adore
and respect the National Health Service,
for it was the source
of much of our gear.
We stole drugs,
we stole prescriptions or bought them,
sold them, swapped them,
forged them, photocopied them.
Or traded drugs with cancer victims,
alcoholics, old-age pensioners,
AIDS patients,
epileptics and bored housewives.
We took morphine, diamorphine,
cyclizine, codeine, temazepam,
nitrezepam, phenobarbitone,
sodium amytal,
dextropropoxtphene, methadone,
nalbuphine, pethidine, pentazocine,
buprenorphine, dextromoramide,
chlormethiazole.
The streets are awash with drugs
you can have for unhappiness and pain,
and we took them all.
We would have injected vitamin C
if only they'd made it illegal.
(BABY GURGLING)
(IN AMERICAN ACCENT) Pardon me,
may I use your bathroom? Thank you.
(GROANING)
SPUD: Stop, psycho.
Rent-boy. No fucking skag.
(CHATTERING)
RENTON: But the good times
couldn't last forever.
(ALLISON SCREAMING)
(ALLISON WAILING)
I think Allison had been
screaming all day,
but it hadn't really registered before.
She might have been screaming
for a week for all I knew.
It'd been days
since I heard anyone speak.
Surely someone must've said something
in all that time.
Surely to fuck someone must have.
-Allison!
-Help me, please!
Calm down.
Everyone's going to be just fine.
RENTON: Nothing could have been
further from the truth.
(SCREAMING CONTINUES)
In point of fact,
nothing was going to be just fine.
On the contrary,
everything was going to be bad.
Bad, I mean, everything was going to be
even worse than it already was.
ALLISON: My God! No, my God!
(ALLISON SCREAMING)
Fuck!
ALLISON: Please, please!
(ALLISON SCREAMING)
RENTON: It wasn't my baby. She wasn't
my baby. Baby Dawn, she wasn't mine.
Spud's, Swanney's, Sick Boy's,
I don't know.
Maybe Allison knew, maybe not.
I wished I could think
of something to say.
Something sympathetic. Something human.
SICK BOY: Say something, Mark.
(ALLISON SOBBING)
Fucking say something, huh?
I'm cooking up.
(SOBBING)
Cook us up a shot, Rents.
I really need a hit.
RENTON: So she did,
I could understand that,
to take the pain away.
So I cooked up and she got a hit.
But only after me,
that went without saying.
Well, at least we knew
who the father was now.
It wasn't just the baby
that died that day.
Something inside Sick Boy was lost
and never returned.
It seemed he had no theory with which
to explain a moment like this.
Nor did I.
Our only response was to keep on going
and fuck everything.
Pile misery upon misery,
heap it up on a spoon
and dissolve it with a drop of bile.
Then squirt it into a stinking,
purulent vein and do it all over again.
Keep on going, getting up, going out,
robbing, stealing, fucking people over.
Propelling ourselves with longing
towards the day
that it would all go wrong.
Because no matter how much you stash
or how much you steal,
you never have enough.
No matter how often you go out
and rob and fuck people over,
you always need to get up
and do it all over again.
(TYRES SCREECHING)
(SPUD SHOUTING)
Sooner or later this kind of thing
was bound to happen.
(LAUGHING)
JUDGE: Because shoplifting is theft,
which is a crime,
and despite what you may believe,
there is no such entity
as victimless crime.
Heroin addiction
may explain your actions,
but it does not excuse them.
Mr Murphy, you are a habitual thief,
devoid of regret and remorse.
I'm sentencing you
to six months' imprisonment.
My only worry is that it will not
be long before we meet again.
Mr Renton, I understand you have entered
into a programme of rehabilitation
in an attempt to wean yourself
away from heroin.
The suspension of your sentence
is conditional on your continued
cooperation with this programme.
Should you stand guilty before me again,
I shall not hesitate to impose
a custodial sentence.
Thank you, Your Honour.
With God's help,
I'll conquer this terrible affliction.
RENTON: What can you say?
Well, Begbie had a phrase for it.
It was fucking obvious
that cunt was going to fuck some cunt.
Hope you've learnt your lesson, Son.
My son, I thought
I was going to lose you there.
You're nothing but trouble to me,
but I still love you.
(CHUCKLING)
You'd better clean up your fucking act,
sunshine. Cut that shite out forever.
Listen to Francis, Mark.
He's talking sense.
Fucking right I am. See, inside,
you wouldn't last two fucking days.
There are better things than
the needle, Rents. Choose life.
MOTHER: I remember
when you were a wee baby.
ALL: (SINGING) Mama's little baby
Loves shortening, shortening
Mama's little baby
loves shortening bread
(ALL LAUGHING)
I'm sorry, Mrs Murphy.
It was not fair,
Spud going down and not me.
Well, it's not our fault.
Your boy went down
because he was a fucking smack-head.
If that's not your fault,
then I don't know what is.
I was the fucking cunt
that tried to get him off it.
I'll get the fucking drinks in.
RENTON: I wished I'd gone down
instead of Spud.
Here I was, surrounded by my family
and my so-called mates
and I've never felt so alone.
Never in all my puff.
Since I was on remand,
they've had me on this programme,
the state-sponsored addiction,
three sickly sweet doses
of methadone a day instead of smack.
But it's never enough.
At the moment, it's nowhere near enough.
I took all three this morning.
Now I've got 1 8 hours until my next shot
and a sweat on my back
like a layer of frost.
I need to visit the Mother Superior
for one hit.
One fucking hit
to get us over this long, hard day.
-What's on the menu this evening, sir?
-Your favourite dish.
Excellent.
-Usual table, sir?
-Why, thank you.
Would sir care to pay for his bill
in advance?
No, stick it on my tab.
I regret to inform,
credit limit was reached and breached
quite some time ago.
Well, in that case...
Ah! Hard currency, that'll do nicely.
Can't be too careful when we're dealing
with your type, can we?
Would sir care for a starter?
Some garlic bread, perhaps?
No, thank you. I'll proceed directly to
the intravenous injection of hard drugs.
As you wish, sir.
(SHUDDERING)
Perhaps sir would like me
to call for a taxi?
(SIREN WAILING)
Open your eyes.
Wake up. Come on. Wake up.
(GASPS)
RENTON: I don't feel the sickness yet,
but it's in the post, that's for sure.
I'm in the junkie limbo at the moment.
Too ill to sleep.
Too tired to stay awake.
But the sickness is on its way.
Sweat, chills, nausea, pain and craving.
A need like nothing else I've ever known
will soon take hold of me.
It's on its way.
(SINGING) Oh, you've got green eyes
Oh, you've got blue eyes
Oh, you've got grey eyes
And I've never seen anyone
quite like you before
No, I've never met anyone
(LATCH RATTLING)
We'll help you, Son.
You'll stay here with us
until you get better.
We're going to beat this together.
Maybe I should go back to the clinic.
No! No clinics. No methadone.
That only made you worse,
you said so yourself.
You lied to us, Son,
your own mother and father.
-You could bring us some jellies.
-No!
You're worse coming off that
than the heroin.
-Nothing at all!
-It's a clean break this time.
You're staying here
where we can keep an eye on you.
I appreciate what you're trying to do,
but I just need one more score.
Just bring me one more hit, please.
I need one more fucking hit.
(DOOR LATCHING)
You fuck.
(LATCH RATTLING)
Hit! Hit!
(GROANING)
(SNIFFLING)
Well, this is a good fucking laugh,
ain't it?
You sweat that shite out of your system
because if I come back
and it's still here,
I'll fucking kick it out.
Okay.
(GRUNTING)
(PANTING)
God!
(BABY GURGLING)
(GROANING)
(GAME SHOW FANFARE PLAYING)
GAME SHOW HOST: Question number one.
The human immunodeficiency virus is a...
-Retrovirus?
-Retrovirus is the right answer.
(AUDIENCE CHEERING)
(GROANING)
SICK BOY: It's a mug's game, Mrs Renton.
I mean, I'm not saying
I was blameless myself, far from it,
but there comes a time when you have
to turn your back on that nonsense
and just say no.
(CRUNCHING)
(GROANING)
SICK BOY: Just say no.
ALLISON: Oh, my God, she's dead.
(BABY CRYING)
(GRUNTING)
(BANGING)
GAME SHOW HOST: Question number two.
HIV binds to which receptor
on the host lymphocyte?
Which receptor is that?
FATHER: CD4.
HOST: CD4 is the right answer.
(AUDIENCE CHEERING)
(APPLAUSE)
Better than sex, Rents. Better than sex.
The ultimate hit.
I'm a fucking adult,
I can find out for myself.
Well, I'm finding out, all right.
Tommy.
(BABY CRYING)
No!
Is he guilty? Or not guilty?
(SCREAMING)
(YELLING INCOHERENTLY)
He's our son.
Don't! Dawn! Dawn!
Stop!
(SCREAMING)
No! No! Don't do this to me!
Stop!
Mark.
Mark. Mark.
There's something you need to do.
Ow!
CALLER: Come alive, 35.
Box of tricks, 66.
MOTHER: Mark, you've got a house.
House, house!
For goodness' sake, Mark.
RENTON: It seems, however, I really
am the luckiest guy in the world.
Several years of addiction
right in the middle of an epidemic,
surrounded by the living dead.
But not me. I'm negative.
It's official.
Once the pain goes away,
that's when the real battle starts.
Depression, boredom.
You feel so fucking low,
you want to fucking top yourself.
RENTON: Tommy!
Tommy!
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
Tommy, it's Mark, man.
You all right, mate?
(DOOR LATCHING)
-Getting out much, Tommy?
-No.
-Following the game at all?
No, me neither, really.
You take the test?
Aye.
Clear?
That's nice.
I'm sorry, Tommy.
Got any gear on you?
No, I'm clean, man.
Well, sub us then, mate.
I'm expecting a rent cheque.
Thanks, Mark.
No bother.
RENTON: No bother. None at all.
Not for me, anyway.
Still, it's easy to be philosophical
when it's some other poor cunt
with shite for blood.
What do you want?
-Are you clean?
-Yes.
-Is that a promise, then?
-Yes, it is, as a matter of fact.
Calm down, I'm only asking.
-Is that hash that I can smell?
-No.
-I wouldn't mind a bit, if it is.
-Well, it isn't.
-It smells like it.
-You're too young.
I'm too young for what?
You're not getting any younger, Mark.
The world's changing, music's changing,
even drugs are changing.
You can't stay in here all day
dreaming about heroin and Ziggy Pop.
It's Iggy Pop.
Whatever. I mean, the guy's dead anyway.
Iggy Pop is not dead. He toured
last year. Tommy went to see him.
The point is,
you've got to find something new.
RENTON: She was right.
I had to find something new.
There was only one thing for it.
Lifestyle Letting Agency.
Oh, yes. It's a beautifully converted
Victorian town house.
Ideally located in a quiet road
near to the local shops and transport.
This one's two bedrooms
and a kitchen/diner.
Fully fitted,
in excellent decorative order.
Lots of storage space.
All mod cons
and it's going at 320 a week.
I settled in not too badly
and kept myself to myself.
Sometimes, I thought about the guys,
but mainly I didn't miss them at all.
This was boomtown, where any fool could
make cash from chaos and plenty did.
Tell you what I've got.
I've got a beautifully converted
Victorian town house.
RENTON: I quite enjoyed
the sound of it all.
Profit, loss, margins, takeovers,
lending, letting,
sub-letting, sub-dividing,
cheating, scamming,
fragmenting, breaking away.
Who's got the keys to Talgarth Road?
There was no such thing as society.
Even if there was,
I certainly had nothing to do with it.
For the first time in my adult life
I was almost content.
DIANE: "Dear Mark, I'm glad you found
a job and somewhere to live.
"School is fine at the moment.
I'm not pregnant, but thanks for asking.
"Your friend Sick Boy asked me last week
if I would like to work for him.
"But I told him where to go.
"I met Spud who sends his regards.
Or at least I think that's what he said.
(SPEAKING INCOHERENTLY)
"No one has seen Tommy for ages.
"And finally, Francis Begbie
has been on television a lot this week.
"He is wanted by the police
in connection with an armed robbery
"in a jeweller's in Corstorphine.
"Take care. Yours, with love, Diane."
(DOORBELL BUZZING)
DIANE: Francis Begbie.
Oh, no.
Armed robbery? With a replica?
How the fuck can it be armed robbery
with a fucking replica?
(GUN CLICKING)
Fucking scandal. My gear, look.
Supposed to be fucking solid silver,
it's fucking garbage.
There's young couples investing
all their fucking hopes in that stuff.
-It's a scandal, Franco.
-Too fucking right it is.
How about one of these Pot Noodles,
by the way?
I'm fucking Lee Marvin.
Hey, Rents.
RENTON: Begbie settled in
in no time at all.
I've no fucking cigarettes.
Aye, right.
(CLINKING)
It's me.
Rents!
(SNORING)
RENTON: Yeah, the guy's a psycho.
But it's true, he's a mate and all,
so what can you do?
Pop down the bookies
and put a line on for us.
Can you not go yourself?
I'm a fugitive from the law, and I can't
walk the fucking streets. You go.
Doncaster. 4:40. 5 to win. Bad Boy.
Buy some fucking beer and all.
Come on, Bad Boy. Come on, son.
Come on, son. Come on! Come on!
Yeah!
Yeah.
Bad Boy.
RENTON: Came in at 1 6-to-1 .
With the winnings,
we went out to celebrate.
(RAVE MUSIC PLAYING ON STEREO)
Diane was right. The world is changing.
Music is changing, drugs are changing,
even men and women are changing.
One thousand years from now, there'll be
no guys and no girls, just wankers.
Sounds great to me.
(BLOWING WHISTLE)
It's just a pity no one told Begbie.
Fuck! Fuck!
RENTON: If you ask me,
we're heterosexual by default,
not by decision.
It's just a question of who you fancy.
It's all about aesthetics
and it's fuck-all to do with morality.
Fuck!
But you try telling Begbie that.
Look, I'm not a fucking buftie
and that's the end of it.
Let's face it,
it could have been wonderful.
(SNARLING)
Fucking listen to me,
you piece of junkie shit.
A joke's a fucking joke,
you mention that again
and I'll cut you up.
You understand?
(DOORBELL BUZZING)
RENTON: Since I last saw him,
Sick Boy had reinvented himself
as a pimp and a pusher
and was here, he said,
to mix business and pleasure,
setting up contacts,
as he constantly informed me,
for the great skag deal
that was one day going to make him rich.
(BOTH SNORING)
Good chips.
I can't believe you did that.
I got a good price for it.
Rents, I need the money.
It was my fucking telly.
Oh, Christ! If I'd known you were
going to get so humpty about it,
I wouldn't have bothered.
Fucking rented anyway.
Are you going to eat that?
-Have you got a passport?
-Why?
I met this bloke who runs a hotel,
brothel. Loads of contacts.
He does a nice sideline in punting
British passports to foreigners.
Get you a good price.
Why would I want to sell my passport?
It was just an idea.
RENTON: I had to get rid of them.
Sick Boy didn't do his drug deal
and he didn't get rich.
Instead, he and Begbie just hung around
my bed-sit looking for things to steal.
I decided to put them
in the worst place in the world.
They weren't paying any rent.
So when my boss found
two desperate suckers who would,
Sick Boy and Begbie
were bound to feel threatened.
Lots of storage.
All mod cons, 320 quid a week.
(BOTH SCREAMING)
And that was that.
But by then we had another reason
to go back.
Tommy.
Tommy knew he'd got the virus,
but he never knew he'd gone full-blown.
What was it, pneumonia or cancer?
No, toxoplasmosis. It's like a stroke.
How's that?
He wanted to see Lizzy again.
She would not let him near the house.
So he bought her a present.
He bought her this kitten.
RENTON: But Lizzy told him
where to fucking stick it?
GAV: Exactly.
"I'm not wanting a cat," she says,
"Get to fuck, right."
So there's Tommy,
stuck with this kitten.
You can imagine what happened.
To those of us gathered here today,
Thomas McKenzie filled a number
of different roles in our lives.
Thomas was a son...
The thing was neglected,
pissing and shitting all over the place.
Tommy was lying about, fucked out
of his eyeballs on smack or downers.
He never knew you could get
toxoplasmosis from cat shit.
MINISTER: ...a loving man
who had a great lust for life.
A keen musician...
-Neither did I. What is it?
-Fucking horrible.
-It's like an abscess in your brain.
-Fucking hell!
Then what happened?
GAV: He starts getting these headaches,
so he just uses more smack,
for the pain.
Then he has a stroke. A fucking stroke.
Just like that.
He gets home from the hospital
and dies three weeks later.
He'd been dead for ages before the
neighbours complained about the smell
and got the police
to break down the door.
Tommy was lying face down
in a pool of vomit.
MINISTER: He has gone from us,
but we have many things
to remember him by.
The kitten was fine.
Would you all please rise now
for the committal?
SPUD: (SINGING)
Did you think I would leave you crying
When there's room on my horse for two?
Climb up here, Tommy, don't be dying
I can go just as fast with two
When we grow up, we'll both be soldiers
And our horses will not be toys
And I wonder if we'll remember
When we were two little boys
-Tommy.
Did you tell him yet?
On you go.
What?
SICK BOY: There's this
mate of Swanney's.
You know the guy, Mikey Forrester.
RENTON: Aye.
Well...
He's come into some gear.
-A lot of gear.
-How much gear?
About two kilos. So he tells me.
He got drunk in a pub
down by the docks last week
where he met two Russian sailors.
They're fucking carrying the stuff.
For sale there and then, like.
So, he wakes up next morning,
realises what he's done,
gets very fucking nervous.
He wants rid of this, right?
-So?
-So, he met me,
and I offered to take it off his hands
at a very reasonable price
with the intention of punting it
on myself to a guy I know in London.
(CHUCKLING) We've just come back
from Tommy's funeral
and you're talking about a skag deal?
Aye.
What was your price?
-4,000.
-You haven't got 4,000.
-We're 2,000 short.
-Well, that's tough.
Look, Mark, every cunt knows
you've been saving up down in London.
I'm sorry, boys, I do not have 2,000.
BEGBIE: Aye, you fucking do.
I've seen your bank statement.
For fuck's sake.
2,1 33.
Two kilos. What is that, ten years?
Mikey Forrester, Russian sailors,
what the fuck are you boys on?
Spud, you've already been to jail.
Do you like it so much,
you want to go back?
I just want the money, Mark.
If everybody keeps their fucking mouth
shut, there'll be no cunt going to jail.
RENTON: There were a lot of
possibilities running through my mind
about what might happen in London.
Things I didn't want to talk
to anyone about.
Ideas best kept to myself.
What no one told me
when we bought the skag,
some lucky punter
would have to try it out.
Begbie didn't trust Spud,
and Sick Boy was too careful these days.
So I rolled up my sleeve,
I spiked my vein,
and I did what had to be done.
It's good. Oh, it's really fucking good.
(RENTON MOANING)
Yeah, that hit was good.
I promised myself another one
before I got to London.
Just one, for old times' sake.
Just to piss Begbie off.
This was his nightmare.
The dodgiest scam
in a lifetime of dodgy scams.
Being perpetrated with three of the most
useless and unreliable fuckups in town.
I knew what was going on in his mind.
Any trouble in London,
and he would dump us immediately.
One way or another, he had to.
If he got caught
with a bag full of skag
on top of that armed robbery shit,
he was going down for 1 5 to 20.
Begbie was hard.
But not so hard that he didn't
shite it off 20 years in prison.
This was to be my final hit.
But let's be clear about this.
There are final hits and final hits.
What kind was this to be?
-Did you bring the cards?
-What?
The cards, the last thing I told you
was to mind the cards.
I've not brought them.
It's fucking boring after a while
without the cards.
I'm sorry.
-Bit fucking late.
-Why didn't you bring them?
'Cause I fucking told you to bring them,
you doss cunt.
Christ.
MAN: These are your friends, right?
SICK BOY: These are the guys
I told you about.
MAN: Okay.
-Well, is he here?
-Yeah, he's here.
-You didn't get followed, did you?
-We didn't get followed.
Okay.
-All right.
-Hi.
RENTON: Straightaway
he clocked us for what we were.
Small-time wasters
with an accidental big deal.
Excuse me, gentlemen.
(DOOR OPENING)
(SIGHS)
So...
How much would you like for this?
20,000.
(CHUCKLING)
I don't think it's worth
much more than 1 5,000.
RENTON: This was a real drag to him.
He didn't need to negotiate.
What the fuck were we going to do
with it if he didn't buy it?
Sell it on the streets? Fuck that.
-Well, 1 9,000.
-Terribly sorry, I can't go to 1 9,000.
Well, fucking 1 6,000 then.
(CHUCKLING)
Okay. Well, fucking 1 6,000 it is, then.
These, gentlemen, are 2,000 bundles.
That's two.
That's four.
RENTON: We settled on 1 6,000.
He had a lot more in the suitcase,
but it was better than nothing.
DEALER: ...make eight.
Thank you very much, gentlemen.
I'd like to say it's been a pleasure
haggling with you.
Fucking brand-new, by the way.
Okay?
ALL: Yes!
(ALL LAUGHING)
RENTON: Just for a moment,
it felt really great.
Like we were all in it together,
like friends, like it meant something.
A moment like that,
it can touch you deep inside.
That doesn't last long.
Not like 1 6,000.
What about you, Spud?
Any major investments on the horizon?
Going to buy yourself
an island in the sun?
For fucking 4,000?
One palm tree, a couple of rocks
and a fucking sewage outflow.
(ALL LAUGHING)
I don't know, man.
I'm going to get something for my ma.
Get some good speed, no bicarb.
Then get a girl, take her out,
treat her right.
-And shag her senseless?
-No, man, true love. True love.
But I could really handle some hot sex
with a Jewish princess tonight.
-You daft cunt.
-Or a Catholic.
If you're going to waste it on a bird,
you might as well leave it all to me.
-Now get the drinks in.
-I got a round already.
-I got the last one.
-It's your round, Franco.
Okay. Same again? Right.
SICK BOY: I'm off for a piss.
See when I get back
that money's still here.
The moment your back's turned
we're out the door.
I'll be right fucking after you.
You'll never catch us,
you flabby bastard.
By the way, see, when I get back...
We'll be halfway down the street
with the money.
-I'd fucking kill you.
-I thought you might, Franco.
Thought you might.
Are you game for it?
What?
Well?
Are you serious?
I don't know. What do you think?
-Still here, I see.
-We wouldn't run out on a mate.
Why not, I know I would.
Where's Franco?
-For fuck's sake!
-Sorry, mate. I'll buy you another one.
You've ruined my fucking suit,
you fucking idiots.
MAN: I'm sorry. I didn't mean it.
Sorry is not going to dry me off,
you cunt.
SPUD: Cool down, Franco.
The man says he's sorry.
Not sorry enough for being a fat cunt.
Fuck you.
If you can't hold a pint, you shouldn't
be in the pub. Now, fuck off.
(GROANING)
No, Frank, not that, man.
SPUD: Oh, fuck's sake.
SICK BOY: Fucking nice one, Franco.
BEGBIE: Shut it.
SPUD: You cut me, man.
BEGBIE: You were in my fucking way.
Help!
Anybody else want
to get in my fucking way?
You?
Hey, Rent-boy.
You bring me down a fucking smoke.
SICK BOY: I think we'd better go.
SPUD: I've got to go
to the hospital, man.
You're not going to any fucking
hospital. You're staying there.
You bring me down a fucking cigarette.
And the bag.
(BEGBIE SNORING)
RENTON: Now I've justified this
to myself in all sorts of ways.
It wasn't a big deal,
just a minor betrayal.
Or we'd outgrown each other,
you know, that sort of thing.
But let's face it, I ripped them off,
my so-called mates.
But, Begbie,
I couldn't give a shit about him.
Sick Boy would have done the same to me
if he'd only thought of it first.
And Spud, okay, I felt sorry for Spud.
He never hurt anybody.
BEGBIE: Bastard!
Bastard!
(GRUNTING)
(GLASS SHATTERING)
POLICEMAN: Open up! Open up now!
Bastard!
RENTON: So, why did I do it?
I could offer a million answers,
all false.
The truth is that I'm a bad person.
But that is going to change.
I'm going to change.
This is the last of that sort of thing.
Now I'm cleaning up and I'm moving on,
going straight and choosing life.
I'm looking forward to it already.
I'm going to be just like you.
The job, the family,
the fucking big television.
The washing machine, the car,
the compact disc,
an electrical tin opener, good health,
low cholesterol, dental insurance,
mortgage, starter home, leisure wear,
luggage, three-piece suite,
DIY, game shows, junk food, children,
walks in the park, 9:00 to 5:00,
good at golf, washing the car,
choice of sweaters, family Christmas,
indexed pension, tax exemption,
clearing gutters,