This is Berk.
It's 12 days north of hopeless and a
few degrees South of freezing to death.
It's located solidly on
the meridian of misery.
My village. In a word, sturdy.
It's been here for seven generations,
but every single building is new.
We have fishing, hunting and a
charming view of the sunsets.
The only problems are the pests.
You see, most places
have mice or mosquitoes.
We have...
dragons.
Most people would leave. Not us.
We're Vikings. We have
stubbornness issues.
My name is Hiccup.
Great name, I know. But
it's not the worst.
Parents believe a hideous name will
frighten off gnomes and trolls.
Like our charming Viking
demeanor wouldn't do that.
Morning!
- What are you doing here?!
- Get inside!
- What are you doing out?!
- Get back inside!
Hiccup! What is he doing? What
are you doing out?! Get inside!
That's Stoick the Vast,
chief of the tribe.
When he was a baby, he popped a
dragon's head clean off its shoulders.
Do I believe it? Yes, I do.
What have we got?
Gronckles. Nadders. Zipplebacks.
Hoark saw a Monstrous Nightmare.
- Any Night Furies?
- None so far.
Good.
Hoist the torches!
Nice of you to join the party! I
thought you'd been carried off!
Who, me? No, come on, I'm way
too muscular for their taste.
They wouldn't know what
to do with all this.
They need toothpicks,
don't they?
The meathead with attitude and
interchangeable hands is Gobber.
I've been his apprentice
since I was little.
Well, littler.
Move to the lower defenses. We'll
counterattack with the catapults.
Hurry!
See? Old village, lots
and lots of new houses.
Fire!
Let's go!
That's Fishlegs, Snotlout, the
twins: Ruff nut and Tuffnut...
and...
Astrid.
Their job is so much cooler.
Come on. Let me out, please.
I need to make my Mark.
You've made plenty of marks,
all in the wrong places.
Please, 2 minutes.
I'll kill a dragon.
My life will get infinitely better.
I might even get a date.
You can't lift a hammer.
You can't swing an axe.
You can't even throw
one of these!
OK, fine, but this
will throw it for me.
See? Now this right here
is what I'm talking about!
- Mild calibration issue...
- Hiccup!
If you ever want to get out
there to fight dragons...
you need to stop all this.
But you just pointed
to all of me.
Yes, that's it! Stop
being all of you.
Oh, yes.
You, sir, are playing
a dangerous game.
Keeping this much raw
Vikingness contained?
There will be consequences!
I'll take my chances. Sword.
Sharpen. Now.
One day, I'll get out there.
Because killing a dragon...
is everything around here.
A Nadder head is sure to
get me at least noticed.
Gronckles are tough.
Taking down one of those would
definitely get me a girlfriend.
A Zippleback?
Exotic. Two heads,
twice the status.
They found the sheep!
Concentrate fire
over the lower bank.
- Hurry up!
- Fire!
And then there's the
Monstrous Nightmare.
Only the best Vikings
go after those.
They have this nasty habit of
setting themselves on fire.
Reload! I'll take care of this.
But the ultimate prize is the
dragon no one's ever seen.
- We call it the...
- Night Fury!
Get down!
Jump!
This thing never steals food,
never shows itself and...
never misses.
No one has ever killed a Night Fury.
That's why I'm going to be the first.
Man the fort, Hiccup.
They need me out there.
Stay. Put. There.
You know what I mean.
- Where are you going?
- Yeah, I know!
- Hiccup!
- Be right back!
Let's get him!
Mind yourselves!
The devils still have
some juice in them!
Come on. Give me something to shoot at.
Give me something to shoot at.
I hit it. Yes, I hit it!
Did anybody see that?
Except for you.
- Do not let them escape!
- Right!
You're all out.
Oh, and there's one more
thing you need to know.
Sorry, Dad.
OK, but I hit a Night Fury.
It's not like the last few times, Dad!
I really, actually hit it!
You guys were busy. I
had a very clear shot.
It went down off Raven Point.
Let's get a search party...
Stop!
Just stop.
Every time you step
outside, disaster follows.
Can you not see that I
have bigger problems?
Winter is almost here and I
have an entire village to feed!
Between you and me, the village could
do with a little less feeding.
This isn't a joke, Hiccup!
Why can't you follow
the simplest orders?
I can't stop myself. I see a
dragon and I have to just kill it.
It's who I am, Dad.
You're many things, Hiccup. But a
dragon killer is not one of them.
Get back to the house.
Make sure he gets there.
I have his mess to clean up.
Quite the performance.
I've never seen anyone mess up that badly.
That helped.
Thank you, thank you.
I was trying.
- I really did hit one.
- Sure, Hiccup.
- He never listens.
- It runs in the family.
When he does, it's with
this disappointed scowl,
like someone skimped on
meat in his sandwich.
"Excuse me, barmaid. You brought
me the wrong offspring."
I ordered an extra-large boy with beefy
arms, extra guts and glory on the side.
"This here, this is a
talking fishbone."
You're thinking
about this wrong.
It's not so much what you look like,
it's what's inside that he can't stand.
Thank you for summing that up.
Look, the point is, stop trying so
hard to be something you're not.
I just want to be
one of you guys.
Either we finish them
or they'll finish us!
It's the only way
we'll be rid of them.
If we find the nest
and destroy it,
the dragons will leave.
They'll find another home!
One more search before
the ice sets in.
Those ships never come back.
We're Vikings. It's an occupational hazard.
Now who's with me?!
Count me out.
- Today's no good for me.
- I have to do my axe returns.
All right. Those who stay
will look after Hiccup.
- To the ships!
- I'm with you!
That's more like it.
I'll pack my undies.
No, I need you to stay and
train some new recruits.
Perfect. And, while I'm busy,
Hiccup can cover the stall.
Molten steel, razor-sharp blades,
lots of time to himself.
What could possibly go wrong?
What am I going to
do with him, Gobber?
Put him in training.
- No, I'm serious.
- So am I.
He'd be killed before the first
dragon is out of its cage.
- You don't know that.
- I do, actually.
- No, you don't.
- No, I do.
No, you don't.
Listen, you know what he's like.
From the time he could crawl,
he's been... different.
He doesn't listen. He has the
attention span of a sparrow.
I take him fishing and he
goes hunting for trolls!
Trolls exist. They
steal your socks.
But only the left ones.
What's with that?
- When I was a boy...
- Here we go.
My father told me to bang my
head against a rock and I did it.
I thought it was crazy, but
I didn't question him.
- And you know what happened?
- You got a headache.
That rock split in two.
It taught me what a
Viking could do, Gobber.
He could crush mountains,
level forests, tame seas!
Even as a boy, I knew what I
was, what I had to become.
Hiccup is not that boy.
You can't stop him, Stoick.
You can only prepare him.
I know it seems hopeless, but you won't
always be around to protect him.
He's going to get out there again.
He's probably out there now.
Oh, the gods hate me.
Some people lose their knife
or their mug. Not me.
I manage to lose
an entire dragon.
Oh, wow. I did it.
I did it. This fixes everything!
Yes!
I have brought down
this mighty beast!
I'm going to kill you, dragon.
Then I'll cut out your heart
and take it to my father.
I am a Viking. I am a Viking!
I did this.
Hiccup.
Dad...
I have to talk to you, Dad.
I need to speak
with you, too, son.
- I don't want to fight dragons.
- It's time you learn to fight dragons.
- What?
- You go first.
- No, you go first.
All right.
You get your wish. Dragon training...
you start in the morning.
Oh, man, I should
have gone first.
I was thinking, you know,
we have a surplus of
dragon-fighting Vikings,
but do we have enough bread-making
Vikings or small-home-repair Vikings?
You'll need this.
I don't want to fight dragons.
Come on. Yes, you do.
Rephrase. Dad, I
can't kill dragons.
But you will kill dragons.
No, I'm really very
extra-sure that I won't.
- It's time, Hiccup.
- Can you not hear me?
This is serious, son.
When you carry this axe, you
carry all of us with you.
Which means you walk like
us, you talk like us...
you think like us.
No more of... this.
You just gestured to all of me.
- Deal?
- This conversation is very one-sided.
Deal?
Deal.
Good.
Train hard.
I'll be back. Probably.
And I'll be here.
Maybe.
Welcome to dragon training!
No turning back.
I hope I get some serious burns.
I'm hoping for some mauling,
like on my shoulder or back.
Yeah, it's only fun if you
get a scar out of it.
Yeah, no kidding, right?
Pain. Love it.
Oh, great. Who let him in?
Let's get started! The
recruit who does best
will win the honor of
killing his first dragon
in front of the entire village.
Hiccup already killed a Night Fury,
so does that disqualify him?
Can I transfer to the class
with the cool Vikings?
Don't worry. You're small and weak...
that'll make you less of a target.
They'll see you
as sick or insane
and go after the more
Viking-like teens instead.
Behind these doors are just
a few of the many species
you will learn to fight!
- The Deadly Nadder!
- Speed 8, armor 16.
The Hideous Zippleback.
Plus 11 stealth. Times 2.
- The Monstrous Nightmare.
- Firepower 15.
- The Terrible Terror.
- Attack 8, venom 12.
Can you stop that?!
And the Gronckle.
Jaw strength 8.
Wait, aren't you gonna
teach us first?
I believe in
learning on the job.
Today is about survival.
If you get blasted...
you're dead!
What's the first
thing you'll need?
- A doctor?
- Plus 5 speed?
- A shield.
- Shields. Go!
Your most important piece of
equipment is your shield!
If you must choose between a sword
or a shield, take the shield!
- Let go of my shield!
- There are a million shields!
Take that one. It has a flower...
girls like flowers.
Oops, this one has blood on it.
- Tuffnut, Ruff nut! You're out!
- What?
Shields are good
for another thing.
Noise! Make lots of it to
throw off a dragon's aim!
All dragons have a
limited number of shots.
How many does a Gronckle have?
- 5?
- No, 6!
Correct, 6! That's
one for each of you!
Fishlegs, out!
Hiccup, get in there!
I moved into my parents' basement.
Come by sometime and work out.
You look like you work out.
Snotlout! You're done!
So it's just you and me, huh?
Nope, just you.
One shot left!
Hiccup!
And that's 6.
Go back to bed, you
overgrown sausage!
You'll get another
chance, don't you worry.
Remember, a dragon will always,
always go for the kill.
So... why didn't you?
This was stupid.
Why don't you just fly away?
All right, where did Astrid
go wrong in the ring today?
I mistimed my somersault dive.
It was sloppy.
- It threw off my reverse tumble.
- Yeah, we noticed.
No, no, you were great.
That was so "Astrid."
She's right. You have to
be tough on yourselves.
Where did Hiccup go wrong?
- He showed up.
- He didn't get eaten.
He's never where he should be.
Thank you, Astrid.
You need to live and breathe this stuff.
The dragon manual.
Everything we know about
every dragon we know of.
No attacks tonight. Study up.
Wait, you mean read?
While we're still alive?
Why read words when you
can just kill the stuff
the words tell you stuff about?
I've read it 7 times.
There's this water dragon
that sprays boiling water at your face.
And there's this other one...
Yeah. That sounds great.
- There was a chance I'd read it...
- But now...
You guys read. I'll
go kill stuff.
Another one has
spines like trees.
- So I guess we'll share?
- Read it.
All mine, then. Wow. So,
OK, I'll see you...
tomorrow.
Dragon classifications.
Strike class. Fear class.
Mystery class.
Thunderdrum. This reclusive dragon
inhabits sea caves and dark tide pools.
When startled, the Thunderdrum
produces a concussive sound
that can kill a man
at close range.
Extremely dangerous.
Kill on sight.
Timberjack. This gigantic
creature has razor-sharp wings
that can slice through
full-grown trees.
Extremely dangerous.
Kill on sight.
Scauldron. Sprays scalding
water at its victim.
Extremely dangerous.
Changewing. Even newly hatched dragons
can spray acid. Kill on sight.
Gronckle. Zippleback.
The Skrill.
Bone Knapper. Whispering Death.
Burns its victims.
Buries its victims.
Chokes its victims. Turns
its victims inside out.
Extremely dangerous.
Kill on sight. Kill on sight.
Kill on sight.
Night Fury.
Speed unknown. Size unknown.
The unholy offspring of
lightning and death itself.
Never engage this dragon.
Your only chance: Hide and
pray it does not find you.
I can almost smell them.
They're close.
Steady.
Take us in.
Hard to port. For
Helheim's Gate.
Hard to port!
Steady!
Hey, you know, I just happened to notice
the book had nothing on Night Furies.
Is there another book, or a sequel?
Maybe a Night Fury pamphlet?
Focus, Hiccup! You're
not even trying!
Today it's all about attack!
Nadders are quick and
light on their feet.
Your job is to be
quicker and lighter!
I'm really beginning to
question your teaching methods!
Look for its blind spot!
Every dragon has one.
Find it, hide in it and strike!
Do you ever bathe?
If you don't like it, then
just get your own blind spot.
How about I give you one?
Blind spot, yes. Deaf
spot, not so much.
Hey, so, how would one
sneak up on a Night Fury?
No one's ever met one and lived
to tell the tale. Get in there!
- I know, I know, but hypothetically...
- Hiccup!
Get down.
Watch out, babe. I'll
take care of this.
The sun was in my eyes, Astrid.
What do you want me to
do, block out the sun?
I could do that but
I don't have time!
They probably...
take the daytime off, right?
Like a cat.
Has anyone ever
seen one napping?
Hiccup!
Love on the battlefield.
She could do better.
Let me... Why don't you?
Well done, Astrid.
Is this some kind
of a joke to you?
Our parents' war is
about to become ours.
Figure out which side you're on.
Toothless.
I could have sworn you had...
teeth.
No, no, no.
I don't have any more!
And with one twist, he took my
hand and swallowed it whole!
I saw the look on his face...
I was delicious.
He must have passed the word,
because it wasn't a month before
another one of them took my leg.
Isn't it weird to think your
hand was inside a dragon?
Like if your mind was
still in control of it,
you could have killed the dragon
from inside by crushing his heart.
I swear, I'm so angry. I'll avenge your
beautiful hand and your beautiful foot.
I'll chop off the legs of every
dragon I fight, with my face.
It's the wings and the
tails you really want.
If it can't fly,
it can't get away.
A downed dragon
is a dead dragon.
All right, I'm off to bed.
You should be, too.
Tomorrow we get to the big
boys, slowly but surely
making our way up to the
Monstrous Nightmare.
But who'll win the
honor of killing it?
It's gonna be me. It's my destiny.
See?
Your Mom let you get a tattoo?
It's not a tattoo,
it's a birthmark.
OK, I've been stuck with you since
birth, and that was never there before.
Yes, it was. You've just never
seen me from the left side.
Hey, Toothless.
I brought breakfast. I hope...
I hope you're hungry.
OK, that's disgusting.
We've got some salmon,
some nice Icelandic COD...
and a whole smoked eel.
No, no, no, no, no!
No, it's OK.
Yeah, I don't really
like eel much, either.
That's it.
That's it. Just stick
with the good stuff.
And don't you mind me.
I'll just be back here,
minding my own business.
It's OK.
OK.
That's not too bad. It works.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no!
Oh, my! It's working!
Yes, yes! I did it!
Yeah!
Today is about teamwork.
Now, a wet dragon head
can't light its fire.
The Hideous Zippleback
is extra tricky.
One head breathes gas, the
other head lights it.
Your job is to know
which is which.
Razor-sharp serrated teeth that
inject venom for pre-digestion.
Prefers ambush attack,
crushing its victims...
Will you please stop that?!
If that dragon shows either
of his faces, I'm gonna...
There!
Hey, it's us, idiots!
Your butts are getting bigger.
We thought you were a dragon.
Not that there's anything wrong
with a dragonesque figure.
Wait.
Oh, I'm hurt! I am
very much hurt!
Chances of survival are
dwindling to single digits now.
Wrong head.
Fishlegs!
Now, Hiccup!
Oh, come on.
Hiccup!
Back, back, back!
Now, don't you make me tell you again!
Yes, that's right.
Back into your cage. Now think
about what you've done.
OK, so are we done? 'Cause I've
got some things I need to...
Yep, I'll see you tomorrow!
I've never seen a
Gronckle do that.
I left my axe back in the ring.
You guys go on ahead.
I'll catch up with you.
Meet the Terrible Terror.
It's like the size of my...
Get it off!
Oh, I'm hurt! I am
very much hurt!
Wow! He's better
than you ever were.
Oh, great.
Hiccup.
Hiccup? Are you in there?
Astrid. Hey.
Hi, Astrid. Hi, Astrid.
Hi, Astrid.
I normally don't care what people
do, but you're acting weird.
Well, weirder.
- I trust you found the nest, at least?
- Not even close.
Excellent.
I hope you had more
success than me.
Well, if by success, you mean that
your parenting troubles are over, yes.
Congratulations, Stoick!
Everyone is so relieved!
Out with the old and in
with the new, right?
- No one will miss that nuisance!
- We're throwing a party to celebrate!
- Come over here.
- Hurry!
He's gone?
Most afternoons, but who can blame him?
The life of a celebrity's rough.
He can barely walk through the village
without being swarmed by his new fans.
Hiccup?
Who would have thought it? He
has this way with the beasts.
OK, bud. We're gonna
take this nice and slow.
Here we go. Here we go.
Position...
3... no, 4.
All right, it's go time.
It's go time.
Come on, buddy! Come on, buddy!
Yes, it worked!
Sorry!
It was my fault.
Yeah, yeah, I'm on it.
Position 4.
3.
Yeah! Go, baby!
Yes!
Oh, this is amazing! The wind in my...
cheat sheet!
Stop!
No!
Oh, gosh! Oh, gods! Oh, no!
All right, OK, you've gotta
kind of angle yourself.
OK, no, no, no. Come back down towards me!
Come back down...
Yeah!
Come on.
No, thanks. I'm good.
Not so fireproof on
the inside, are you?
Here you go.
Everything we know about
you guys is wrong.
Dad! You're back!
Gobber's not here so...
I know.
- I came looking for you.
- You did?
You've been keeping secrets.
I have?
Just how long did you
think you could hide it?
I don't know what you're...
Nothing happens on this island
without me hearing about it.
So...
let's talk...
...about that dragon.
Oh, gods. Dad, I'm so sorry.
I was going to tell you.
I just didn't know how to...
You're not upset?
What?! I was hoping for this!
- You were?
- And believe me, it only gets better!
Wait till you spill a
Nadder's guts the first time!
And mount your first
Gronckle head on a spear!
What a feeling! You really
had me going there, son!
All those years of the worst
Viking Berk has ever seen.
Odin, it was rough. I
almost gave up on you.
And all the while you
were holding out on me!
Oh, Thor Almighty!
With you doing so
well in the ring...
we finally have
something to talk about.
Here, I brought you something,
to keep you safe in the ring.
Wow. Thanks.
Your mother would have
wanted you to have it.
It's half of her breastplate.
Matching set. It keeps
her close, you know.
Wear it proudly. You deserve it.
You've held up your end of the deal.
- I should really get to bed.
- Yes, good. OK, good talk.
- I'll see you back at the house. Great.
- We should do this again.
Thanks for stopping by...
- ...and for the breast hat.
- I hope you like the hat.
Well... Yep. Good night.
Stay out of my way! I'm
winning this thing.
Please, by all means.
This time, this time for sure!
No! No, son of a half-troll,
- rat-eating, munge-bucket!
- Wait, wait.
- So, later.
- Not so fast.
- I'm kind of late for...
- What?!
Late for what, exactly?
Quiet down! The
elder has decided.
You've done it, Hiccup! You
get to kill the dragon!
That's my boy!
Yeah. Yes. I can't wait.
I am so...
leaving! We're leaving.
Let's pack up. Looks like you and
me are taking a little vacation.
Forever.
Oh, man.
What the?! What are
you doing here?
I want to know what's going on.
No one just gets as good as you do.
Especially you.
Start talking! Are you
training with someone?
Training?
It better not involve this.
I know this looks really
bad, but you see...
You're right. You're right.
You're right.
I'm through with the lies. I've
been making outfits. So you got me.
It's time everyone knew. Drag
me back, go ahead. Here we go.
Why would you do that?!
That's for the lies. And
that's for everything else.
Oh, man.
Get down!
Run, run!
It's OK! It's OK.
She's a friend.
You just scared him.
I scared him?!
Who is "him"?
Astrid, Toothless.
Toothless, Astrid.
We're dead.
Where do you think you're going?
Oh, great Odin's ghost!
This is it!
Hiccup, get me down from here!
You have to give me a
chance to explain.
I am not listening to
anything you have to say!
Then I won't speak.
Just let me show you.
Please, Astrid.
Now get me down.
Toothless, down. Gently.
See? Nothing to be afraid of.
Toothless!
What is wrong with you?!
Bad dragon!
He's not usually like this.
Oh, no.
Toothless, what are you doing?
We need her to like us!
And now the spinning.
Thank you for nothing,
you useless reptile.
OK, I am sorry! I'm sorry.
Just get me off of this thing.
All right, I admit it.
This is pretty cool.
It's amazing.
He's amazing.
So what now?
Hiccup, your final
exam is tomorrow.
You know you'll have to kill...
kill a dragon.
Don't remind me.
Toothless, what's happening?
What is it?
Get down!
- What's going on?
- I don't know.
Toothless, you gotta get
us out of here, bud.
It looks like they're
hauling in their kill.
What does that make us?
What my Dad wouldn't
give to find this.
It's satisfying to know that all of
our food has been dumped down a hole.
They're not eating any of it.
What is that?
All right, bud, we got to
get out of here... now!
It totally makes sense.
It's like a giant beehive.
They're the workers and
that's their queen.
It controls them.
Let's find your Dad.
No! No.
No, not yet. They'll
kill Toothless.
We have to think this
through carefully.
Hiccup, we just discovered
the dragons' nest,
the thing we've been after since
Vikings first sailed here,
and you want to
keep it a secret?
To protect your pet dragon?
Are you serious?
Yes.
OK. Then what do we do?
Just give me until tomorrow.
I'll figure something out.
OK.
That's for kidnapping me.
That's for everything else.
What are you looking at?
Hiccup! Hiccup! Hiccup! Hiccup!
I can show my face
in public again!
If someone had told me
that in a few short weeks.
Hiccup would go from,
well, being Hiccup
to placing first in dragon training,
well, I would have tied him to a mast
and shipped him off for
fear he'd gone mad!
And you know it!
But here we are. And no
one is more surprised
or more proud than I am.
Today, my boy becomes a Viking.
Today, he becomes one of us!
Be careful with that dragon.
- It's not the dragon I'm worried about.
- What are you going to do?
Put an end to this.
I have to try.
Astrid, if something goes wrong,
just make sure they
don't find Toothless.
I will. Just promise
me it won't go wrong.
It's time, Hiccup.
Knock 'em dead.
Yeah! Show 'em how it's done.
Hiccup! Hiccup! Hiccup! Hiccup!
I would have gone
for the hammer.
I'm ready.
Go on, Hiccup. Give it to him!
What is he doing?
Hey, it's OK. It's OK.
I'm not one of them.
What's he thinking?
- Stop the fight.
- No!
I need you all to see this.
They're not what
we think they are.
We don't have to kill them.
I said, stop the fight!
Out of my way!
Hiccup!
This way!
Night Fury!
Toothless, go. Get out of here.
Go, go!
Stoick, no!
Dad, he won't hurt you!
No, don't! You're
only making it worse!
Toothless, stop!
No! No!
Get him!
No, no! Please just
don't hurt him!
Please don't hurt him.
Put it with the others.
I should have known. I
should have seen the signs.
- Dad?
- We had a deal!
I know we did. That was before...
It's all so messed up.
So everything in the ring, a trick?
A lie?
I screwed up. I should have
told you before now. I just...
Take this out on me, be mad at me, but
please, just don't hurt Toothless.
The dragon? That's what
you're worried about?
Not the people you
almost killed?
He was protecting me!
He's not dangerous.
They've killed hundreds of us!
And we've killed
thousands of them!
They defend themselves, that's all!
They raid us because they have to.
If they don't bring enough food
back, they'll be eaten themselves.
There's something else on their island.
It's a dragon like...
Their island? So you've
been to the nest?
- Did I say nest?
- How did you find it?
What? No, I didn't.
Toothless did.
Only a dragon can
find the island.
No, no, no. No, Dad. No, please,
it's not what you think.
You don't know what you're up against.
It's like nothing you've ever seen.
Dad, please. I promise you,
you can't win this one!
No, Dad. No.
For once in your life, would
you please just listen to me?!
You've thrown your lot in with them.
You're not a Viking.
You're not my son.
Ready the ships!
This way.
Set sail!
We head for Helheim's Gate.
Lead us home, devil.
It's a mess.
You must feel horrible.
You've lost everything:
Your father, your tribe,
your best friend.
Thank you for summing that up.
Why couldn't I have killed that
dragon when I found him in the woods?
- Would have been better for everyone.
- Yep. The rest of us would've done it.
So why didn't you?
- Why didn't you?
- I don't know.
- I couldn't.
- That's not an answer.
Why is this so important
to you all of a sudden?
Because I want to remember
what you say right now.
For the love of... I was a coward.
I was weak.
I wouldn't kill a dragon.
You said "wouldn't".
Whatever! I wouldn't!
Three hundred years and I'm the first
Viking who wouldn't kill a dragon.
First one to ride one, though.
So?
I wouldn't kill him because he
looked as frightened as I was.
I looked at him
and I saw myself.
I bet he's really frightened now.
What are you going to do about it?
- Probably something stupid.
- Good, but you've already done that.
Then something crazy.
That's more like it.
Sound your positions.
Stay within earshot.
- Here!
- One length to your stern.
Listen, Stoick, I was overhearing some
of the men and, well, some of them
are wondering what it is we're up to here.
Not me, of course.
I know you're always the man
with the plan. But some,
not me, are wondering if there
is in fact a plan at all
- and what it might be.
- Find the nest and take it.
Of course. Send them running.
The old Viking fallback.
Nice and simple.
Step aside.
Bear to port.
If you're planning on getting eaten,
I'd definitely go with the Gronckle.
You were wise to seek help from
the world's most deadly weapon.
It's me.
- I love this plan.
- I didn't...
You're crazy. I like that.
So, what is the plan?
That's not really encouraging.
I was wondering where that went.
Stay low and ready your weapons.
We're here.
- Wait! What are you?
- Relax.
It's OK. It's OK.
Where are you going?
You'll need something
to help you hold on.
When we crack this Mountain open,
all hell is going to break loose.
In my undies. Good thing
I brought extras.
No matter how this
ends, it ends today.
Is that it?
We've done it!
This isn't over! Form your ranks!
Hold together!
Get clear!
Beard of Thor! What is that?!
Odin help us.
Catapults!
- Get to the ships!
- No! No!
- Smart, that one.
- I was a fool.
Lead the men to the far
side of the island!
Gobber, go with the men!
I think I'll stay, in case your
thinking of doing something crazy.
I can buy them a few minutes if I
give that thing someone to hunt!
Then I can double that time.
- Here!
- Oh, no! Here!
Come on! Fight me!
No, me!
Ruff, Tuff! Watch your backs!
Move, Fishlegs!
Look at us! We're on a dragon.
We're on dragons! All of us!
Up! Let's move it!
Every bit the boar-headed
stubborn Viking you ever were!
- Fishlegs, break it down!
- OK.
Heavily armored skull and tail
made for bashing and crushing!
Steer clear of both. Small
eyes, large nostrils!
Relies on hearing and smell!
OK, Lout, Legs! Hang in its blind
spot, make noise, keep it confused!
Ruff, Tuff, find out if it has
a shot limit! Make it mad!
That's my specialty!
Since when?! Everyone knows
I'm more irritating! See.
Just do what I told you! I'll
be back as soon as I can!
- Don't worry! We got it covered!
- Yeah!
- Troll!
- Butt elf!
Bride of Grendel!
This thing doesn't
have a blind spot!
There!
Go help the others!
OK, hold on. Hold on.
- It's working!
- Yeah, it's working!
I've lost power on the Gronckle!
Snotlout, do something!
I'm OK!
Less OK!
I can't miss! What's wrong, buddy?
Something in your eye?
Yeah! You're the Viking!
Dad?
You got it, bud.
Hiccup!
I'm sorry... for everything.
Yeah. Me, too.
You don't have to go up there.
We're Vikings. It's an
occupational hazard.
I'm proud to call you my son.
Thanks, Dad.
He's up!
Get Snotlout out of there.
- I'm on it!
- I'm on it first!
- Hey, let me drive!
- I'm ahead of you.
No, this way.
- Don't push me!
- I'll take your teeth out!
I can't believe that worked!
Night Fury!
Get down!
Did you get her?
Go.
That thing has wings. OK,
let's see if it can use them!
You think that did it?
Well, he can fly.
OK, Toothless,
time to disappear.
Come on, bud!
Here it comes!
Watch out!
OK, time's up! Let's
see if this works.
Come on! Is that the
best you can do?!
Stay with me, buddy.
Just a bit longer.
Hold, Toothless.
Now!
No.
No!
Hiccup!
Son!
Hiccup.
Oh, son.
I did this.
Oh, son, I'm so sorry.
Hiccup!
He's alive. You brought
him back alive.
Thank you for saving my son.
Well, you know... most of him.
Hey, Toothless.
I'm happy to see you, too.
I'm in my house.
You're in my house.
Does my Dad know you're here?
What? OK, OK.
Toothless, no. No, Toothless.
Toothless! Oh, come on.
OK. Thanks, bud.
- Toothless, stay here.
- Come on, guys. Get ready!
Hold on tight! Here we go!
What?
I knew it. I'm dead.
No, but you gave it your best shot.
So, what do you think?
Hey, look, it's Hiccup!
It's Hiccup!
Turns out all we needed was
a little more of this.
You just gestured to all of me.
Well, most of you. That
bit's my handiwork.
With a little Hiccup flair thrown in.
You think it'll do?
I might make a few tweaks.
That's for scaring me.
What is it always going to be this way?
'Cause...
I could get used to it.
Welcome home.
- Night Fury!
- Get down!
You ready?
This is Berk.
It snows 9 months of the
year and hails the other three.
Any food that grows here
is tough and tasteless.
The people that grow
here are even more so.
The only upsides are the pets.
While other places have
ponies or parrots...
we have...
dragons.