The things you're saying are not
enough reasons to get a divorce.
- If you have other reasons,
lets hear them. - Like what other reasons?
Like your husban being an addict, or beating you
or not giving you pocket money.
No, he's neither an addict nor does he have any issues;
in fact he's a very nice and decent person.
Then why do you want to get a divorce?
Becuase he doesn't want to come with me.
If he said he'd come with me,
I'll withdraw my claim right now.
- Are you willing to come?
- No, I'm not.
- Why not, Judge? Tell me why he won't.
- You know the reason already.
No, I do not know.
Please explain it one more time.
Let her give me one reason why in this situation
we should leave for abroad.
- Show me a good reason why we should stay.
- I'll give you a thousand reasons.
- Tell me just one.
- My dad. I can't leave him.
Do I need to give more?
But you can leave your wife?
- When did I ever leave you?
You brought me here.
- What did you do?
- You were the one who applied for the divorce.
When you tell your wife and kid to go,
is that not leaving?
Did he not just say you can go if you want to?
Yes, and I'll say it again.
When you don't want to live with me,
I'm not going to force you to. Just Go.
- Calm down. Keep your voices down.
Someday day you wanted to live witn me;
now you don't want to.
- When you prefer to go over there...
- What do you mean "prefer"?
This is something that we both started.
Judge, after a year and a half of running around
and all the costs, we finally got our visas.
It's been six months that they've come,
and they'll expire in 40 days.
Why should we lose this opportunity?
You don't want to miss this opportunity, OK;
Lets hear your proposal.
You know our situation now,
Tell us what we should do.
Judge, what should we do?
This reason he's using as an excuse right now: his father...
- I didn't use it as an excuse...
- You said give me one reason...
- Excuse me, I'm talking.
His father is suffering from Alzheimer's.
He's not aware that he is his son. Or who's arround him.
- What difference does it make to him?
Whether it's you or someone else?
- Why do you say that? it matters.
Does he understand that you're his son?
But I know he is my father.
Is you daughter not imprtant to you?
Her future is not important to you?
- Who said this is about our daughter?
- All these other children...
- Why do you think it's only important to you?
All these other children living in this country,
Do none of them have a future, Ma'am?
I'd prefer that my child didn't grow up under these
circumstances. As a mother, I have this right.
Under what conditions?
Which conditions, Ma'am?
Is it better growing up here with both parents, or
growing up over there with no father?
That's exactly why I want him to come with us.
I'm not in a situation that I could come.
How many times do I have to repeat this?
Did I need to say again?
So he doesn't have the conditions.
What will happen to me now?
Nothing.
Return to your life.
If we could, I wouldn't have applied for divoce.
Ma'am, he also has to approve of this divorce.
It has to be mutual.
- But, he is saying he's willing.
Isn't he saying that he's ok right now?
- Sir, are you willing to divorce?
If she prefers going abroad to leaving the father of her child,
then I'm ok.
Ok, so he's fine.
What about my daughter?
Everything has to be agreed upon.
How old is your daughter?
She'll be 11 in two weeks.
If her father doesn't give permission,
she can't come with you, Ma'am.
Her father doen't allow.
That's between you two.
Please sign here and have a good day.
Judge, I've come here so you can
solve my problem.
You too please.
Come sign here.
- Where do I sign?
- Here.
I'll give up everything.
Just give me my daughter.
Your daughter is emotionaly attached to me.
She doesn't even want to come with you.
- She doesn't understand.
- Why do you say she doesn't understand?
She's 11. Why doesn't she understand?
Please sign here,
and don't take up the time of the court.
- No one understands but you.
- No, it's just you that understands evertyhing...
- Please don't take up the court's time.
Judge, what do I do?
I only have 40 days left.
Ma'am, you can just come here everytime
you have a small issue and want to get divorce.
Small issue?
My problem is not small.
- My problem is not small.
- Thank you
- The problem is my daughter.
- Ma'am, it's his daughter too.
He has rights too.
I'm the judge and I'm saying that your issue is small.
Sign here please and have a good day.
Separation of Nader from Simin
A film by Asghar Farhadi
- Ma'am, you said second floor.
- This IS the second floor, Sir.
Then what's the lower floor?
This is ground, this is first,
and that would be the second floor.
Our price was for two floors.
- You're getting paid by the buyer, anyway.
- But only for two floors though.
I don't understand what you're saying, Sir.
Then call the buyer to see what we have to do.
This isn't right, this is three floors.
I'll pay for the extra floor.
Just open the way for me.
Excuse me, Ma'am?
Go tell your dad that they're late.
Why don't you tell him yourself?
- What did I say?
- What was our deal?
I'm studying.
- Hello.
- Hello, Ma'am.
I'll be right with you.
Ma'am, I do not know how much you're aware of this, but,
it's for taking care of my father
that I'm bothering you with.
It'll be some home job too,
but the real issue is that you
have to give him the meds on time.
... doesn't use the stove, doesn't open this door,
so he'd go out and get lost. Doesn't open the window.
I'll have to go to work at 7:30 am.
You should be here then so I can leave right after.
7:30 is too early.
If I were to come then,
I'd have to leave home around 5:00 - 5:30am
- Can you do eight?
- Come on up
- I don't know about 8.
- It'd be fine if you could get here by 8:00.
Ring our neighbour's house, they'll open
the front door. I'll leave the keys here.
- OK?
- OK.
- Can you get to it? - Yes
- Sorry, what's the monthly rate?
Just one sec...
- 300,000 per month, Ma'am.
- That's too little.
No, it's around that price, ask around.
My commute is too far.
I have to change a couple of buses to get here.
Look, this is what I can afford.
Now, you know better whether you'd like to take the offer.
Give these books to her, she might need them.
- I don't have change, Ma'am.
- So let me know by this afternoon so
I can let someone else know.
So if you couldn't do it, I'd wouldn't lose them.
OK.
Termeh! Your clothes!
Not coming?
- Why are you taking your books?
- I want them.
All this for only two weeks?
- Thank you.
- You're welcome.
- Usually, what does she put it on?
- Should I go ask her?
You want to make me look bad before your mom's even left?
- Simin, where are you going?
- I'll be back soon.
- Where are you going?
- Going up the street.
I have something to do; be right back.
I'll be back.
I have an appointment.
- I say put it on Four.
- Why four?
Because it's most faded.
See, mom must have use that number most
since its color has faded so much.
OK, we'll do four then; who cares...
In fact, from now on we'll put
all the settings of this house on four.
She's really going.
- She'll be back, dear.
- Termeh!
Come here to Grandpa.
Dad?
Honey, go to your room.
Dad, get up.
Let go of her hand.
Get up, I want to take you to the toilet.
Get up dad.
Where are you taking me?
The toilet and then I want to
go buy you newspaper.
Honey, I said go to your room.
I told you to go, dear.
- Where are you taking me?
- Come on.
Don't put your hand there.
I'm taking this Shajarian CD.
- Take whichever you want.
- No, just this one.
Good-bye.
I thought you were living there too.
No, I'll be moving into my mother's for a while.
It's a bit difficult.
Look, I fully trust him in those cases.
He's a devoted man. Don't worry about him.
Plus, he won't even be home.
In the morning when you get there,
he'll be off to work.
The same in afternoon.
Your daughter will be there too.
That way my daughter won't be alone either.
They'll play together.
Where are you going?
What is this?
- Oxygen.
What is oxygen?
Get away.
or he'll wake up.
I can't hear anything.
What is he doing?
Hello.
Did you want to go somewhere?
- I wanna buy a newspaper.
- What?
I want to buy a newspaper.
There is newspaper in your room.
Come.
Come, let me take you to your room.
I want to take you to your room,
then give you something to eat.
Mom!
He's peed his pants.
Sit on the bed.
What is this?
Where are you going? Get inside.
Go wear a shoes.
You see it's all Najes (unclean) here.
He'd say if he had to pee.
Look, take him into the bathroom...
I can't come now.
I have classes til 12:00.
Call my husband. Have you called him?
Do you have his number?
Write it then.
Pen's right there by the phone.
If I brouhgt you a pants, could you change yourself?
Your clothing. If I brought your cloth,
could you change yourself?
- Simin?
- Can you wash yourself?
- Wash yourself?
- Simin?
I'm leaving your clothe here. Ok?
Wash yourself, then wear these clothes.
I'm putting your towel here.
- Understand?
- Yes.
Wash yourself so you won't be uncomfortable.
Put your pants in there.
Can you?
Your pants! Tkae them off.
And wear the one I gave you.
OK?
Simin...
Hello.
I have a question.
I've come here to this house for work.
I have to look after an elderly man.
I wanted to ask...
Excuse me, but he peed his pants.
I was wondering if I changed him myself,
Would it be a sin? would it not?
No one's here.
old man, 70 or 80 years of age with dementia ...
The urine...
He's been sitting here for half an hour now.
Can I?
I won't tell dad.
My dear.
Get up.
Open your legs.
OK, now remove your pants.
Card!
- Everybody is looking.
- That's ok, let them look.
- How much?
- 37.5
- Did you get the rest?
- He didn't give.
- You asked and he didn't give?
- That was his tip.
Tip?
A second, sir!
Tip is for when he's doing the job.
Go take the money.
- Dad!
- Quick!
Wait, Sir, wait.
- Here.
- It's yours.
Really?
- Hello.
- Hello, Termeh.
Hello, Ma'am.
- Hello, how are you?
- I'm fine, thank you.
- I'll just bring my books.
- Bring the test results as well.
- How are you, Mrs. Qahraei?
- I'm fine, thanks, you?
I'm fine, thank you.
Sorry we're late.
No problem.
How's your wife?
- Well, thank you.
- Great.
- Hello, Sir.
- Hello.
How are you doing, Dad?
- Hello, pretty lady.
- Hello.
Here's the newspaper.
Are you reading him the newspaper or is he to you?
Son ...
Ali got married.
- who's Ali?
- Ali.
Yeah, Ali got married.
Termeh, quick.
Ma'm, you hadn't closed his oxygen valve very tight.
I did in the morning, he probably opened it himself.
Could you tighten it a bit more from
tomorrow so he can't open it.
I'm sorry but...
I don't think I can come tomorrow.
Didn't you say you'd come every day?
I did but my distance is too far. I can't come.
Ma'am, I had to turned someone
else away yesterday because of you.
It's 4 in the afternoon.
Where would I find someone else for tomorrow?
I swear, it's really difficult for me.
I really can't.
The job is very heavy, I can't do.
Please, could you come here?
- Somayeh, where is your scarf?
- it's here.
Maybe you got tired cause it's the first day.
No.
You've been here yourself... seen those few minutes.
Somayeh, come get your bag.
Sorry, if you could give me that number...
They also have ultrasound.
- Today he was moving alot.
- So it's a boy.
This morning he was kicking my mom's belly so much...
Well, he wants to be born sooner...
To play with me.
Could you write here, please?
Tell them Qahraei sent you.
Her secretary knows me.
- Is it a man or a women?
- It's a women.
Do call in advance.
You should have told me about this yesterday, Ma'am.
How can I leave him alone in the house tomorrow?
- Termeh, where did your mom leave the tea bags?
- I don't know.
You should have also told me
that I have to clean him too.
What cleaning?
This morning he peed his pants.
It's not correct for me to clean him.
Could you pay me for today,
So I can go.
Always told us when he had to pee.
If you call these companies, they can
send you male caregivers too.
Ma'am, I can't just trust anybody.
Here.
You can count if you'd like.
Sorry, I'm only saying this
causue of the religious issues.
No problem.
- Thank you.
- You're welcome.
- Good-bye.
- Bye-bye.
Yes?
Sorry, I was wondering if I can
give your number to my husband,
saying I found you in the newspaper...
For these household chores and for your father.
You can describe the job, and if he
agrees to come ...
I don't want to tell him that I know you.
I didn't tell him that I was coming here for work.
So, tell him to call me or just
tell him to come here tonight.
I think it'll be too late for tonight.
So, I'll come in tomorrow myself.
If you could just not give the job to someone else.
And you know better about the rate...
Don't worry about that. Have him call me
and I will setup to meet him.
- Thank you.
- You're welcome, bye.
And thanks.
Mr Lavasani?
There.
Hello. I'm Samadi.
- I called for the job.
- Yes, how are you?
I'm sorry I'm late.
No problem.
Where did you say you worked before?
Shoe repair.
So, you don't have any issue with cleaning him?
What?
I said, he can't hold since yesterday.
No, it's okay, he's like my own father.
So, since you're going to be alone with him,
with no one else, you have to be very careful.
Will the family not be there?
No, I'm single now.
Excuse me, but 300,000
for this job, is itn't too little?
How much did you have in mind?
- Perhaps 400,000 at least
- I really can't do 400.
I'll come in a few of days for test...
If you liked, add something to it.
- If you weren't satisfied
then just don't pay.
If you want I could start today.
No, I have someone today.
Bring an identification card and start tomorrow.
- Like what?
- A picture ID is sufficient.
- Religiosity?
- Believer.
- Arid?
- Sand pile.
- The desert?
- The desert.
- A riot?
- Rebellion.
The door-bell?
- Razieh.
- No.
- Her husband.
- Yes.
Give the farsi version of the following words:
- Model?
- Nemunak.
- Compost?
- Khoshaab.
- Warranty?
- Compensation, zemanat.
That's Arabic, not farsi.
My teacher said so.
Don't tell that again.
What is wrong is wrong.
No matter who says or where it's written.
- For "warranty", you can write...
- If I write anything else, they'll take points off.
That's ok, let them.
... Write "Poshtvaneh".
Poshtvaneh.
Hello.
- Hello.
What happened? I thought your husband
was supposed to come from today.
Sorry, he couldn't come today.
What about tomorrow?
I do not know.
If not, I'll come myself.
Ma'am, is he going to come one day
and not show up another...
No, the poor man wanted to come.
Last night one of the lenders came with the
police and took him away.
In any case, if he can't make it, I need to know
a couple of days in advance.
No, he'll definitely come.
Tonight, I want to go to this lender,
beg him so he'd let him come out.
Please lock the door behind me.
- Sure - Bye.
Hi.
Don't step on it, it's Najes.
Go take the trash out.
Are you able to?
Yeah, I can.
Where the hell do I find you clothes now?
Take off the top one.
Take it off.
Mom...
He's not in his room.
- What?
- He's not in his room.
Go see if he's in the toilet.
Put your hand here.
Don't move it, okay?
The ball won't get pass here...
Nice going dad.
- Grandpa , which side are you on?
- He's the manager, sitting on the side-bench.
Did you see that?
What happened?
Sit down.
Are you all right?
Where have you been, girl?
The poor man's been waiting for you for half an hour.
I have a long commute, I swear.
Hello.
Also, if you could take the trash
in the trash bin.
The wetness of the bags get on
the stairs, making them dirty.
Yesterday I got dizzy and
dropped the bag. It got ripped open.
I'll clean the stairs today.
- OK
- Get in.
Move your hand away.
Let me close the door.
- Ma'am?
- Not here?
- What was her child's name?
- Somayeh.
Don't sit there, it's wet. You see...
Somayeh!
Ring the bell.
Ms. Khalani!
Keep knocking.
Somayeh! Grandpa!
Ms. Khalani!
Yes.
- Hi, how are you?
- I'm fine, thank you.
- Have you seen the lady who works with us?
- She was cleaning the stairs.
- When?
- Morning.
- She's not home?
- No. Thank you.
You wait here.
I'll go get the keys out of the car.
What happened?
Dad?
Get the feet, Honey.
Dad, get up, look at Termeh.
Dad!
He's breathing.
Don't worry, he's breathing.
Do your arms hurt?
Take his shirt off.
Move your arms.
Does it hurt?
Get up.
Walk a little.
Come on.
Come on, let's go get a newspaper.
Move your leg.
Does it hurt?
Let me see what happened?
Who did this to you, dad?
I want to make sure your legs are ok, dad!
Let me...
Honey, can you go outside.
- Is something wrong?
- No, you it's fine. Go out.
She's gone, daddy.
Let me take them off.
Dad! I want to make sure your legs are ok.
Come on, remove it.
Bastard
- Honey, did you take some money
from the drawer? - No.
Go to the kitchen.
Honey, dear, I told you to go to the kitchen.
Didn't you see it was nothing?
Come on ... Close the door.
Hello.
Come here.
Mom, I'm thirsty.
You look at him.
Hello.
Where were you?
I had something to do; I went away
for a moment and came back.
The hell you went away for a moment...
- He was asleep.
- So, you had to lock the door on him and leave?
I came back quickly...
Came back quickly?
How can you look into my eyes and lie?
He was dying when I got here!
He always sleeps this time ...
So you do this everyday then?
You lock the door and
get on to your own business?
No, I swear. I had to do it today.
- Why did you tie his hand?
- Go wait outside.
Was this our agreement? Was it?
I had to.
I had something I had to do.
Thank you very much!
Our agreement was to tie this poor mans hand
and lock the door and go on to your life?
- Now, what's happned to him? is he okay?
- Thank you very much.
You wait outside, honey.
Go make sure grandpa doesn't need anything.
What'd you need in that
room over there?
Which room?
The room you took money from its drawer.
I've taken money from your drawer?
- I've taken money from your drawer?
- You haven't taken money?
I swear I did not!
- I swear I would never do such thing!
- Come on, come on, Get out.
Sir, to our martyrs
I swear.
You're saying I took money? ...
Well, here's my bag. Look.
If I'd taken money then
it'd have to be in here.
Here, honey take his bag.
Where are you taking the bag, Sir?
Give it back.
I'm swearing to Emam Zaman...
- Here's my bag.
- Ma'am, why are you doing this?
I'm saying I swear to Emam Zaman...
I'm saying I swear to Emam Zaman if I've
steped one inch from here.
- Get out.
- You say... What have I done?
Don't touch me, SIR!
OK, I won't touch.
Just get out yourself.
- GET OUT!
I won't go until I get my money.
You deserve to be kicked/thrown out of here.
- WHAT have I done?
- Look at me. It's for her
sake I'm letting you go easy. Understand?
Get out.
- I'm being nice to you to just throw you out.
- Tell me what happened to him.
Ma'am, this is my home,
I want you to get out of here.
- Ok I'll get out.
But this is not right.
- But this is not right.
- Please get out!
That's it.
Dad?
Open the door. It's me.
I want to get in ...
Is this how your looking after him?
Dad, open the door.
See what's over there.
Take a look.
Open the door!
Why are you shouting?
He won't understand.
When I tell to be careful, it's for this.
Maybe his leg hurs and can't get up.
Grandpa ...
Dad, open the door.
Open the door, please.
Dad, I'm gonna push the door to get in.
It'll hit you, dad.
Move over.
I'm gonna push the door to get in.
Why are you doing this yourself?
Who told you to enter in?
- I wanted to see what happened to him.
- Give me the keys and get out!
- I did not steal anything from you.
- Ma'am, you're really getting me angry!
I did not steal.
- Don't explain! Don't explain!
- I wasn't here, Sir.
Get out.
Give me my money for today and I'll go.
Havent you already taken it!
haven't you?
I'v been here since 5:30 in the morning with my daughter...
Somayeh.
- Get out! Get out!
Sir, stop! stop!
- Out!
- I swear if I stole anything.
Get outta here, I said.
What happened?
Sit down.
What happened, Ma'am?
Mom, be careful.
Tell her to work on your english.
Good-bye, Grandpa.
Dad, Termeh said goodbye.
Be careful.
OK.
- What happened?
- Mom says come in.
Tell her grandpa's in the car,
I can't come.
Says it's important.
You've stopped keeping up with us,
even before divorcing your wife...
I'm really busy, mother.
People divorce their wives to
become less busy.
Ma'am, I can get these channels,
They probably have parazit (static).
Dear, just fix the ones that work.
- Come, sit down.
- Thank you. Simin?
- Hello.
Where's Termeh?
- With my dad in the car.
- Well, bring your dad in too.
No, he's tired.
It's his sleep time.
What?
Did you fight with that lady today?
- She came to you?
- Her sister in law called me.
Shameless!
What'd she do?
Tied the old man to bed,
locked the door, left the house...
If I had come in 10 min later,
it'd be done.
- Is he ok?
- He'd fallen out of bed.
Who knows how how long he was like that.
- Where was she?
- I don't know where the hell she went.
- She said you hit her.
- I hit her?
- Nonsense.
- So why have they taken her to the hospital?
- Hospital? Why? What happend to her?
- You're asking me?
- I just pushed so she'd get out of the house.
- Her sister in law called and scolded me.
- What she say? - That if she dies, the blood
will be on your hands.
Things like that.
- Did she say what happened?
- I hung up. She started to curse.
This is what happends when you just
find random people.
Don't blame me.
I told you even then that I only know
the sister in law.
Did she say which hospital?
- Hi Ma'am.
- Yes?
Please wait.
A women with the name "Razieh"
was brough in this evening.
- What was the last name?
- We don't know;
She must have been brought in early evening.
Why was she brought in?
- We were just told...
- That she had gotten sick.
I'll call you.
Bye.
If I'm not mistaking,
her husband's name is Samadi.
- Razieh Asnaqi?
- Is she about thirty?
She's had an surgery and now
she's in post-operative care.
What surgery?
She had a miscarriage.
- Is she ok now?
- Hello? Wait. She's fine.
Excuse me, is there any family member here?
- They'd be downstairs.
- Thank you
What did you do to her?
What did I do?
Hello, Sir.
- How are you?
- We're fine, thank you.
Hello, Ma'am.
- How is she?
- Who?
Your wife.
Under care.
Did you know her?
- I did.
- My wife did.
- Didn't have any sandwiches.
- Hello, Ma'am.
- Can we visit her?
- Where did you know her from?
- Your sister had introduced her
to us for household chores.
- Thank you very much.
- She came to your house for work?
- A few days she came, yes.
You were busy apparently,
so she came in for you.
Sit down and eat something.
You mean she came to look after your father?
Only a few days.
Two or three days.
Then why didn't you tell me that in the bank
the other day?
I thought she would have told you already.
Now, why did you come here?
- We thought we'd come to see
if there is anything we could do.
- What work?
- Any help... we were worried.
She fell down?
Look, come with me so I can explain.
Let me explain... Come with me.
I really understand your situation.
You've killed his child,
now you've come to bring it back to life?
- I'm really sorry.
- Sorry won't become her child, Ma'am.
Tell me one thing only.
Why didn't you tell me that day?
I thought she...
Sir, my friened!
You're single... my wife...
Let go of my hand...
Let him go
Let it go.
Calm down. Please...
This is a hospital.
Come on.
Stop, Sir! Stop!
Why did you come here?
Let me see.
- You had to tell me this tonight?
- I'm so sorry.
- Let me see.
- I'm sorry.
Come out here.
Come out, I wanna talk to you.
Please, I beg you, Hojjat!
- Do you want me to lower your seat?
- No.
I'll leave you home, then I'll go
pick up my father.
No.
What you do mean no?
You want to go to your parents
looking this way?
It's done.
Tonight you come back home.
I don't want to.
Where're you going, Sir?
Leave it there.
Did you hear her accusation?
Do you agree?
It's was the 13th, sir.
I'm sorry for her and I got very sad
when I heard about it...
- I went to the hospital.
- So you agree that you did it?
Did you get this the same day
from the medical examiner?
The night she was in hospital,
we took the report for the ...
We took it to the examiner.
Four and a half months, boy.
So, please explain.
I agree,
I got a bit rough with her.
What do you mean rough,
Did you push her?
No, I didn't push her.
I just tried to get her out of the house.
No, please explain more clearly, Sir.
You are accused of murder right now.
The kid was 4.5 months,
hence is considered a complete human.
I didn't approach her with
the intention of pushing her.
I just wanted her to get out
so I could close the door.
- You didn't push me?
- Madam, please.
If I had known she was pregnant ...
I wounldn't have even done as much as I did.
I just wanted to close the door.
Do you agree with his words, Ma'am?
He didn't push me, he grabbed me here
and then threw me; I fell down the stairs.
No, I didn't throw you.
I just said, I just wanted to
get her out of my home.
- Who throws a pregnant woman out his house?
- I didn't know she was pregnant.
- Why are you lying?
- I just learned this in the hospital.
Judge, you're like my older brother.
How can someone not figure out from
the look of a pregnant woman?
- A 4.5 month pregnant lady.
- Ma'am, when did I even got to see you?
By the time you showed up,
I was either gone or about to go to work.
And when I returned, she was always like this,
with the chador on.
How could anyone figure out she was pregnant?
He could claim not to have known
from your physical apperance.
Plus, I never even imagined a
pregnant women would do such a work.
Judge, I spoke about my pregnancy in front
of him, his doaugher and her teacher.
- I swear they all heard.
- When? I don't remember.
- Of course you wouldn't remember...
- Who says this is about my knowledge of this anyway?
Of course it is.
If they can prove that you
knew she was prenant...
... The court will give you
1 to 3 years in jail.
- So?
- What?
- No, I did not know.
- Your daughter's teacher can testify.
Can she come tomorrow?
Sir, I don't even want to ger her involved.
It's not good for my kid.
Asshole, you killed my kid.
Now it's bad for your kid?
Your kid is just important?
Our kids are animals?
Don't insult, Sir.
I'm insulting? or is he?
When he takes my pregnant wife for stupid work ...
Be quiet or I'll send you to jail for three days.
- Please, he just gets angry too quick.
- Ma'am, did I make you do this?
I should really be complaining from her for why she
would go work for this guy without my knowledge.
When you go to work in a single man's house,
and you don't even know who he is...
I wanted to help with the bills.
Judge, he's been umemployed for a couple fo months.
In any case, the teacher has to come as a witness.
Either call her yourself or give us the contacts...
Judge, I am here today
just for one thing.
I lost my kid, but I didn't get as disheartened ...
As when this guy accused me of stealing.
We're thieves?
- Please sit down.
If we were thieves, would
we come clean your father's ass?
- Do you have proof that she's stolen?
- Sir, I didn't say she stole.
I looked in the drawer, and saw
that there was money missing;
Exactly the amount she was gonna get.
- Is that why you got into a fight?
- He accused her of theft.
Judge, my father is suffering from Alzheimer's.
This women tied him to bed and locks the door
and leaves the house.
That day I came home early.
I saw him tied to the bed, in a terrible situation...
I thought he was dead at first.
She came back and in that situation
I can't say I wasn't angry. I was angry.
I told her to get out of the house,
but she wouldn't get out.
Where was I suppose to go?
This guy accused me of theft.
If I hadn't requested that he pay
me and just left, he would have
thought I had stolen the money.
- Sit down.
- Was your father injured?
- Yes, he was injured a bit.
- What injury?
If he had injury then this
guy would have to be the one complaning.
Yes, he was injured.
- Where are you going, Ma'am?
- Sorry, my kid is outside,
just going to have a look at her.
Come back soon.
And close the door.
Where'd you go? Why aren't you coming back?
I'm not feeling good.
You go, I'll come.
He's saying you locked his
father in the house and left.
What can I say?
What do you mean?
If the complaint goes though,
they'll have a ruling against you.
- Where's Somayeh?
- There.
You go, I'll bring her.
Lets go.
Yes?
He was asleep. I locked the
door so he wouldn't get out.
This guy himself locked the door these couple of days,
and left the key for me.
I saw that he was doing it himself...
He says you tied him to the bed.
I was afraid if he woke up,
He'd get out of the bed and do something to himself.
- Judge, I swear I did it cause I cared.
- Ma'am, the real issue is why did you leave the house?
- She left; you have to hit her?
- Quiet!
Who even let you touch my wife?
Sir, get out.
Sir, if they don't care abut honor,
I care.
- Sir, please don't insult.
- Please leave the room.
Sir, I want to make a complaint against this woman now.
Write the complaint and bring to me.
Take your father to the medical examiner
and have them write a report.
- Excuse me, what happenes to our complaint?
- You just sign here and get out.
Call someone for the bail.
What bail?
Your accused of murder.
I can't just let you leave.
40 million is blood money.
Sign here.
Judge, Where can I find bail?
I'm living in my father's house.
And he has Alzheimer's.
If you can't, you'll go to jail.
My father can't come here with his sickness.
Sir, don't write please...
Please. I beg.
I can't go to jail.
I've left my dad at home to come here.
I really don't have the bail.
- It's not in my hand, it's the law.
Wait a bit. Let me...
My father, what do I do with him?
I've left my dad at home, locked him inside.
My daughter will be coming from school...
Please, don't write?
- What are writing?
- Why are wasting your time?
go make the call.
I can't go to jail.
I won't go. You can write...
- Go get a soldier.
For what? Don't.
I'm begging you Sir.
Please don't write.
I swear my life will be ruined.
Don't waste your time.
Go make the call.
Termeh Hello, I've gotten tied down here.
They're keeping me tonight.
Don't you worry, it's nothing.
Just that you'll be alone tonight.
Keep an eye on everything.
Remember to take Grandpa to the toilet.
Take care of yourself.
I will call tomorrow.
Hello.
If you hadn't left,
Dad wouldn't have been in jail now.
Your father isn't in jail because of me.
- He hit a pregnant lady.
- Cause you left that this women came here.
And how worried was your dad that I was leaving...
He knew that you wouldn't really go.
- Did you tell him?
- No, he figured out himself.
Tell me the truth.
Did you tell him?
Go get your stuff so we
can go to grandma's house.
- What about grandpa?
- We'll take him.
I have homework.
I'm not coming.
- I'll be leave you here alone!
- OK.
If you call me saying come get me,
You know what happens.
Didn't even once say:
"Don't do it", "don't go",
"I won't divorce you".
Not as if we've lived together
for 14 years.
Dad!
What're you doing here, dear?
Who brought you here?
- Don't you have school? a test today?
- No, that's tomorrow.
Now, who brought you here?
Hello.
Shouldn't you call us, if you get into trouble?
... So we can bring you the house title as bail?
I didn't want to trouble you.
Silly man.
- Sit down.
- No Ma'am, I have to take him
for question/answer.
- Where is grandpa?
- In safe hands. Don't worry.
What is their issue? saying: 'my child, my child'?
They say 'my child' as if it was their
18 year-old son who was stabbed to death.
- Did you talk with them?
- Well, you can't even talk to the guy.
I told the women: my dear, you're both young.
Next year, another child. Seriosly...
What happened?
- I have to get someone to value the home.
- OK, go.
- Hello.
- I'll be back.
- We'll be here. You Go.
Thank you.
- Hello, Mrs. Lavasani.
- Hi, how are you?
I'm fine, you?
- I'm sorry for your trouble.
- What trouble? It's good I saw you here...
What happend? Is it true that your husband...?
Yes, unfortunately, he pushed her
and she fell; then she had a miscarriage.
So, what do I have to answer?
I do not know what they're going to ask.
So, if they asked something that
was disadvantages to your husband...?
In my opinion, you should tell them the truth.
- Ma'am, Please don't stop here.
- Where was he?
- Mr. Lavasani was in the kitchen.
- Any reactions to the conversation?
- If he did, I did not notice.
- How did you know she was pregnant?
- She told me herself, I think.
You asked, Ma'am.
Why would I say anything?
Aha.
Her daughter was drawing; a man and a women.
She said, this is my mother and my father.
I said: your mom's not that fat?
She said that she was pregnant.
- So you didn't figure out based on her appearance?
- No.
Why are you lying, my sister?
You are a woman.
You really can't tell from the apperance
of someone if they are pregnant?
Imagin I did figure out,
What difference does it make to Mr. Lavasani?
Judge, this woman is his daughter's teacher.
They've worked on their story together, I swear.
- Why are you insulting this lady?
- No one was talking to you.
When did I even have the opportunity
to get my story staight with her?
I was arrested here last night.
It's not very complicated.
Right now as I speak to you ...
That guy over there, even if he didn't want to,
could hear us, am I correct?
Ma'am, I didn't hear.
My mind was distracted with my own issues and problems.
Why would I listen to your private conversation?
- Do I have to swear on anything?
- As if you believe in God!
No, God is just for you people.
Please, open that window.
Judge, he is an honorable man.
I've been going to his house to teach his daughter for a year.
He'd never do such things.
I want to know: why would this
women hide her pregnancy from me?
If I had known she was pregnant,
I wouldn't have even hired her.
Why would you hired her when you know she hasn't
gotten permission from her husband?
Alright...
Thank you. You can go to.
Thank you.
In the Sassanid's time,
people were divided into two classes ...
... Privileged upper class and
the normal class.
"the normal folks".
What did they ask, Ma'am?
They wanted to know if your dad knew
Somayeh's mom was pregnant or not.
We're really sorry for your trouble.
Sure, no problem. I haven't done anyting.
Honey, what happend to your mom?
- She had a stomach ache.
- Why?
Did your father have a fight with her?
Why would they fight?
Maybe saying: why didn't you tell me
that you were working at someone's house?
- Did he hit her?
- My parents don't fight.
Then, why the day that you were drawing,
your parents were fighting?
- You showed it to me yourself.
- They don't fight anymore.
They haven't fought anymore?
Are you sure?
Yesterday he said 'I didn't know she was pregnant'...
Today he's saying 'I didn't even push her'.
And you just stand there quietly
and look at me.
Honestly, didn't you push me? Seriously...
- Haven't I already said it...
- Listen, Sir ...
Stop the 'I didn't push her but I
got her out of the house' montra...
How far away is the door from the stairs,
two-three meters?
In this period, what else could have
happend to have cause her injury?
The hallway in our house ...
- Look ...
- I'm talking, Sir!
You should't be talking, you should be answering.
Just answer!
Be quiet!
- Did I jump into your...
You've come here to just answer.
- I have a question I want to ask you.
You just answer one question.
- OK.
- Judge, I want to ask him...
- Just go ahead and ask me directly...
If you havn't done anything wrong..
then why did you run to the hospital
to see what happened to my wife?
- I came as a gesture of kindness.
Where was your kindness when you were hitting her?
Was anybody else there
when you had the fight?
- Yeah, the neighbors were there.
- Ok, I'll send someone for investigation.
Judge, they too, will be like the teacher.
They're all toghether.
Judge, he's been insulting from the very beginning.
Am I lying?
- I'll be one saying who is telling the truth
and who is lying.
You be quite!
Sir, his wife that he's trying to get a
divorce from has brought the bail.
My God!
Ma'am, do you have someone
that'll be your guarantor?
What do you mean?
Like a civil servant, a business owner...
- No one. And my husband is unemployed.
- Why do we need a guarantor?
- You have to have a guarantor. She's now been charged.
- What is she charged with?
According to his application for a complaint ...
He has no right to.
She accepted that she tied his father to bed,
locked the door and left.
- I already explained ...
- Judge, her child died....
Keep your voice down.
Aren't you ashamed?
Are you a man?
- I said be quiet.
For God's sake, listen to us once.
He's distorting everything.
He's must have beaten up my wife
that the kid was...
What's more clear than this?
Why are you being unjust towards us?
Listen to me for once...
I've told you once; if you distrupt this meeting,
I will send you to jail for 3 days.
I've lost everything I have, Sir.
You're scaring me of jail?
Go Fear God.
Mr. Izadi, call someone to come take this guy.
I'm begging, please don't call anyone.
- No, let me them come.
- Ok, get out of here and don't make noise.
Why should I be quite?
Should I be quite so they can take my rights?
Get out, Sir.
- What's your problem? I'm going...
- OK, get out.
Let me take my helmet.
He's going.
Judge, I worked 10 years in a shoe repair shop.
In the end, they throw me out like a dog.
Saying the law will give you your right.
I complained, it took a whole year.
In the end, nothing happend.
Go sit at home, they said.
But this time I won't let it happen again.
This time is different.
I have nothing to lose.
My problem is that I can't talk like this guy.
I get angry really quick.
I can't talk like him.
- Don't do that!
- Hojjat?
- I don't feel good.
Go sit down for minute.
- Let's go!
- What do you want from him? He just gotten calm.
- We have to take him.
I want to talk to him for a sec.
Don't you move, OK?
Judge, I beg you.
Give me one second, Sir.
Sir, he's just under a lot of stress, I swear.
I tried not to say anything for two days...
He's been in jail every other day in the last month, I swear.
All the lenders have been after him.
I've begged them all to let him out.
Sir, I'm begging you.
Look...
Look at these...
Sir, can I ask that you let go this time?
Sir, I swear he takes a whole bunch of these everyday.
I swear I'm not lying.
- Judge, Please.
Sir, since he's gotten unemployed,
he's become depressed. I swear, he can't control it.
Sir, you're like his older brother.
Go tell him to go find you a guarantor. Quick.
God bless. God bless you.
And don't leave the building.
No, I'll wait for him to return.
- Hello Sir.
Will you tell her?
She'll think now that she's brought me bail,
I'm askig her to come back.
So let her think that way.
Dad ... please.
OK.
Promise me.
Why are you promising?
Dad ...
Yes?
You didn't know Razieh was pregnant?
No.
- Why?
- Nothing.
Then why'd you ask?
Last night mom said you knew.
Where was your mom to know whether I knew or not?
She said that night in the hospital,
when they said Razieh's baby had died ...
... You didn't say anything.
You didn't ask whether she was pregnant.
You weren't surprised.
In these situations, people would ask:
did she have a baby?
As if you knew.
Your mom wants to make me look bad to you.
Will you tell her?
I couldn't, dear.
Didn't you promise?
I'm sorry.
- Which stair was she on?
- That one.
- This?
- This stair.
Can you take granpa in?
I'll be right in.
- Are you mad at me?
- No.
Did you go upstairs?
Yeah, I went to Mrs. Kalani's.
For what?
I told her that they'll be coming in for investigation tomotrow.
So she should be careful.
Careful for what?
Just be careful that they're coming in for investigation.
That's it.
Is that a problem?
If she's suppose to tell the truth,
why should she be careful?
- Termeh ...
- Yes?
Come with me.
- I have homeworl.
- Leave the homework. Come with me...
Come, assume you're that women.
See.
Is that right?
When someone gets thrown, they'll hit somewhere like this.
It won't be like this, then hit here,
then come here, and spin around and hit here and fall here.
Right?
If I had thrown her...
... she would have either fallen on those stairs ...
... Or would have hit this directly.
You can't fall down here.
Assume that you got thrown, try it out.
- Then how did she fall over there?
- I don't know.
I'm just saying she wasn't thrown into these staires.
That's it.
You come here...
- Then why don't you  just tell them these things?
- Never mind them.
I want you to know.
Go on.
- He threw in this direction?
- No, right down the staires.
Look yourself! This door wouldn't even allow me.
I couldn't even if I wanted to.
It's not possible.
Where did you fall?
- On top of these stairs.
- Which one?
I think that one.
Do you think or are you sure?
I'm not sure.
Ma'am,
Did you find her right here?
I didn't see her getting thrown.
When I arrived, she was on that stair.
Why don't you tell them anything?
Go show them how he threw you.
I was so sick, I swear I didn't
even know what happened.
Look, I'll stand right here.
Sir, please stand right here,
push me with all your force.
I'm saying it's impossible to fall there.
Of course you won't fall.
She's was a pregnant woman; she'd
fall if you had just touched her.
Then you come.
Choose anybody you want to push you.
I'm saying it's not possible.
If you push from here,
You won't fall on that stair.
Which stair?
She's saying herself it's this stair.
Sir, everyone is saying they saw her on that stair.
Ma'am, did you see her getting thrown?
Yes. From above there, I couldn't see the house door,
but I could see the stairs that she fell on.
Can you show me where you were seeing this?
Maybe she got dizzy and fell.
How often did you use these stairs?
Why hadn't she gotten dizzy before?
Excuse me, Sir.
That morning when I saw her in the stairs ...
I asked her why there was trash on the stairs,
She said she had gotten dizzy
and dropped the trash bag.
Is that not correct, Ma'am?
- My kid took the trash.
- You said you had gotten dizzy.
Ms. Kalani,
Didn't she wash the stairs that day?
They would have been wet.
She might have slipped and fell on the ground.
You asshole pushed her that
she slipped.
Be respectful!
I'm not saying anything in front of your familty.
- You shouldn't be saying anything, you bastard!
- Sir, no cursing!
Take him outside.
This neighbors lives with them.
She won't say anything that's bad for him
You can go file a complaint if you
have a reason to think they are lying
So do you're saying they are telling the truth?
F@*k me that I've spent all my time here today.
Excuse me. Could you give my kid's bag back?
Here you go.
Come on. Don't you want your coloring book?
Honey, don't you be sad if I'm fighting with your parents.
Here, let me put it into your bag.
- My mom didn't take money.
- I know.
And I wasn't fighting because of that, anyway.
Then what was it for?
I too get sad to see when she leaves my dad.
Well, she had gone to a doctor.
Go on, honey.
Careful of the stairs.
According to Court's request, I'll
examined him and write whatever I see.
Doctor, You can see that
he no longer speaks.
Didn't you say he has Alzheimer's disease?
Yes, but before this incident he spoke a little bit.
This is a doctor's office. Not a court.
Go prove that there.
- Does he have any bruises?
- Yes, a little bit.
What happened?
I'm not sure the bruises are from the fall from the bed.
Don't run. Slow.
Mom, open the window.
There's been a fight.
This is a girls' school.
Can't you see?
I just have a question from this lady.
You can't sit here.
If you want to fight, go get the police.
I don't want to fight, Ma'am.
I just want to talk to her.
I have nothing to say to you, Sir.
I don't know either you nor that women's husband.
- Then why did you lie in court?
- What lies?
- She knows which lie.
- Ms. Safaei, call the police.
- Don't scare me from the police.
- You're fighting someone else, what does she have to do with it?
Then why does she try to talk to my daughter?
What did I have anything to do with your daughter?
You're a teacher in this country.
Aren't you ashamed...?
Why did you tell her
'your dad hit your mom and killed the baby'?
When did I ever say that?
Aren't you ashamed to be basing all this
on a 4 year old child's drawings?
Is that a reason?
I didn't say such a thing, Sir.
Why is that when you look at us, you think
we are beating our wives like animals all day?
I swear on this Quran,
we're human beings like you, too.
- Come on and go.
- Sir!
Ma'am, I have nothing to lose in life.
Tell your husband to not do something that'll
get both us in big trouble.
- Ok sir, go on.
Ma'am, I'll be waiting outside...
- Good god Sir, go on.
I am unemployed so I can wait there all day.
You'll eventually come out.
Either you come to court and say you lied
or I'll look into what's going on between
you and her husband.
Be shamefull.
What are you talking about?
I've tried not to say anything so far ...
- Then why are you protecting him?
- They call from the court, they asked a couple of questions
and I told the truth.
- You told the truth?
- Yes!
Here is a Qur'an. Put your hand and swear on it.
Sir, why the swearing?
What does it have anything to do with her?
It's ok, I'm not afraid.
What do I need to say?
You said her husband didn't know my wife
was pregnant. Is that right?
- Yes.
- Then say that.
I swear to this Qur'an,
that the day I was in their house ...
... her husband didn't hear our converation.
He was in the kitchen.
Is that OK?
Or is there something else I need to say?
He's crazy.
Where are going now?
Call your husband.
Don't go alone.
No, I don't want him to know about this.
- I'm so sorry Mrs. Qahraei.
Why are you standing there?
Hello?
Hello, Mrs. Qahraei.
I left you a message before.
Could you pick up the phone please?
This woman that came for nursing to our house,
Apperently got a gynecologists phone number from you.
I was wondering if you could give me that number.
So I could I call them to see if she did indeed go to see them.
And if she did, what her issue was.
I'd appreciate if you could call me back.
Thank you.
What do you want to do?
What?
You want this to continue?
Fighting everyday?
Why? What happend?
Today, he went to her school and started
yelling in front of everyone...
What'd he say?
Shouted in front of everyone:
"His father killed my child".
How will she be able to go back to that school anymore?
Do you realize what you're doing?
What am I doing?
- He's threatning.
- The hell he is.
Termeh, go to your room.
What if tomorrow he killed your kid?
What do you want me to do?
Take everything and go abroad?
The hell with abroad.
Why aren't you talking normally?
I'm talking to you about Termeh.
What sort of situation is this that
you're creating for her?
Did I create this situation?
I like how you can look me in
the eye and say this?
Who left the house?
Who asked for a divorce?
- You said you can go whenever you want.
- Yeah, I'll say it again. Why'd you come back?
I didn't come back.
I came to figure out my child's situation.
The situation is clear.
- You have two options ...
- Don't you try to threaten me.
What threat?
Either you will resolved the situation with this guy ...
- I'll know what to do with that.
- Didn't you hit her?
Didn't you throw her into the staires?
Didn't her child die?
Yeah!
I killed her child!
Then why are you being so stubborn?
Pay the blood money, so it gets over with.
- I won't be forced to pay.
- What do you mean forced?
Just put yourself into these
misfortunate people's place for one sec.
- Am I responsible for their misfortunes?
- They're child is dead!
My father was also injured.
Go look, he can't even utter one word now.
How much did he talk before?
Just those 4 words.
I was happy with just those 4 words.
You're comparing this to you killing their child?
- Where the hell were you to see I hit her?
- Then how did her child die?
- I don't know. Just imagine for one sec
that maybe the husband hit her...
And now they're trying to accuse me.
You know what her child said the other day?
She said, they had gone to the doctor.
What could have happened to her that
she couldn't wait 2 hours.
Why did she have to lock this old man and leave?
Inspection officer has said that the
baby had died becuase of an impact.
Lets say an impact.
Who's to say I was responsible for this impact?
I will not accept it
until it's proven to me.
Ok, then let me take Termeh.
Shame on you.
Under these curcumstances, you've
come here to put me under more pressure?
I'm worried about her.
Your child wants to stay here
and she has to be here to learn.
Learn what?
Stubbornness and confrontation?
No, to learn not be a coward like you.
Or not to get scared as soon as someone threatened her.
And he know who to come to threaten.
Why doesn't he come threaten me?
Yes, I am a coward.
You know what your problem is?
In your life, instead of staying and solving your issues ...
... You've either ran away or you've surrendered.
- Is that so?
Just tell me why you want to leave this country?
You're afraid to stay.
Excuse me, one week I was gone,
and see what you've done in this house.
I couldn't?
Then I'm responsible.
Let me take Termeh,
Then you can do whatever you want.
Termeh, honey,
You don't have to stay here.
Go wherever you're more comfortable.
Don't you want to come, still?
They sell it for 2000 rial per killo.
If they use 270 killo every day,
Write 270.
Ok, then how much is his revenue?
Meaning how much will his profit be.
So, how would you solve this?
Did you lie?
What?
About what?
That you didn't know she was pregnant.
Why?
You said you couldn't hear what Ms. Qahraei
and Razieh were talking about.
Yeah.
Then how'd you know Ms. Qahraei gave
her the doctor's phone number?
She didn't say anyhting then.
Very well.
If you want to calculate the profit ...
Yeah, I knew.
Your mother was telling the truth.
I could hear everything from the kitchen.
So why did you say that didn't know?
Do you know what would have happned if I had said so?
They would have taken me to prison form 1 to 3 years.
I just thought at that moment what
would happen to you in that situation.
... With whom would you stay with.
So I said I didn't know.
If you knew, then why did you hit her?
Look, I knew she was pregnant,
but I didn't know at that moment.
I had forgotten.
I wasn't paying attention.
Then why don't you just tell them this stuff?
Dear, the law doesn't care about this stuff.
They say you either knew or you didn't.
Look at me.
If you tell me to go tell them right now,
I will.
- Hello.
- Hello dear.
Didn't I tell you not to come in front of the school?
Ms. Qahraei!
What do you want from her?
Ms. Qahraei, wait one min ...
If you just stop one second,
I want to explain something to you. That's all.
Please let me ...
Why...
Dad!
Who's responsible for my child's safty right now?
I can't do anything without a witness.
Now, what am I suppose to do if I don't have a witness?
Should wait till he kills my child, then come to you?
- How can I know you're tellig the truth?
- Why would I lie?
Would I bring my father and child here to lie to you?
- Is your daughter here right now?
- Yes, she's outside.
You can ask yourself.
I'm afraid to take her to school.
I'm afraid to leave my father at home.
- Is the plaintiff here?
- I can't leave my dad at home alone...
- Are you done writing?
Almost done Sir.
- Quick.
So you didn't know that this man's wife is pregnant, right?
No, I didn't know.
You didn't hear them when she was talking
about it to you're kids teacher?
- No I didn't
You didn't hear, huh?
I'm saying if anybody wants to go arround threaten ...
Then why did the teacher come and withdrew her statement?
Saying you knew.
- She came here saying I knew?
- Yes, she came yesterday.
Well, he's gone to the school and threatened her...
Answer me:
Did you hear her or not?
I said no.
Then where did you know she had given her the phone number?
- My daughter told me.
- What did she say?
Just that she had gotten the number from her teacher.
Tell her to come inside.
Right now?
- Yes.
And you wait outside.
What question?
What is he goning to ask?
I don't know.
Give that to me.
So, what do you have to say?
You haven't asked anythig yet.
Didn't your father tell you what I'm going to ask you?
- No.
- Which grade are you in?
Sixth.
And the day that lady came to talk about
the phone number and the pregnancy...
... You were there?
I wasn't there at that moment.
I had gone to get my books.
Then how'd you know that your teacher
had given her the doctor's phone number?
Cause she gave her the number later.
When she was leaving...
- In front of you?
- Yes.
Then why didn't you tell this to your dad earlier?
What?
That the lady had gotten the doctor's
number from your teacher.
I didn't think it would be important to my father.
So then, did you tell your dad or did he hear himself?
That she had gotten the number?
I told him.
- You told him?
- Yes.
OK.
You can go.
- What crime have I commited?
- Nothing. You're right.
Well, you're husband dosn't accept responsibility.
I can accepted that he's responsible,
but in the end, what's suppose to happen?
Go to court for one or two years,
to maybe get the blood money in payments of, what,
Lets say 100,000 per month
- Why do you...
Why do you think it's about the money
that I'm going to court?
When did I say such a thing?
You think I'm a bum,
I have nothing to do...
- No!
And we don't understand anything?
- I never said such a thing.
- Let's listen to what she has to say.
There is no other way.
Neither will your child come back,
Nor will they hang my husband.
And her husband didn't do it intentionally.
They're good people, I swear.
They're offering you a good solution.
Take the money and end it all.
You're unemployed, take it and
use it for something you need.
Right now we can determine an amount,
I'll get my husband to agree.
Now, he has to agree.
For God's sake, leave us alone.
Are you saying this based on anger?
- Look at yourself for a sec.
- Don't let him go, Ali agha.
Wait a minute.
I wanna to talk to you.
- Hello.
Are you staying?
Mom ...
Let us have our talk.
Come, sit down.
I want to talk to you.
I can hear you.
Today I went to talk with her husband.
Sit down for one min.
I talked to him. After a whole lot of trouble,
I got him to agree to take 15 million instead of 40 million...
With three 5 million checks.
Who let you promise him money?
- I can't keep being under stress about my child's safety.
- No, you didn't understand me.
Even now that you had gotten late, I was dying.
I'm saying, why are you getting involved in this?
I havn't come here to fight.
God, what do I have to do
so she can understand me?
Didn't you say you were responsible?
Didn't you say I introduced her?
... Didn't you say if I hadn't gone,
none of this would have happened?
But I tell him I'm willing to pay, that'd
mean I've accpeted I'm responsible.
If you pay now, it means that I'm accepting responsibilty.
- But he'll drop the case...
- You think he'll leave us alone?
- You think he'll leave us if you don't pay?
- Why would I pay blackmail?
Think of it as my dowry.
I will get that money if I have to find it under a ...
If I have to, I'll go beg, borrow to get that for you.
But I neither have nor will I pay unjust money.
You're child going through puberty.
She'd being tortured in this situation.
So you understand the sensitivity
of the age of puberty?
She wouldn't have stayed if she was being tortured.
Why do you think she's staying with you?
You think she's chosen you?
She's staying with you so we don't get seperated.
She knows I won't go anywhere without her.
She's being tortured, but she doesn't show it.
Call them right now, tell them my husband won't agree ...
... until it's proven to him that he's responsible.
I'll sell my car.
- I don't want you to sell your car for me.
- It's not for you.
When your child is not imporatnt enought to you
to pay 15 million...
What the hell are you talking about?
Who says it's about the money?
I can't sit around til my child's safety is guaranteed.
Look at me, You have no right to do anything else.
Do you understand?
Had I done nothing,
You'd be in jail.
Go get your mom's house title back.
I don't want to be out with the bail you got me.
Get up, Termeh.
Get up, lets go.
Get up, I tell you.
Mother, please.
- I don't want you to stay here for one more second.
- No, mom, I won't let you.
If 15 million is more important to you than your child...
I won't let you do this.
If his child is not important enough ...
Mother, please listen,
why are you doing this?
You said you would stay.
- The HELL I did! The HELL I did!
- Mom, please!
- I'll be waiting in the car.
It's ok dear, go there til the end of exams.
Grandma and grandpa will be there, too.
You'll be more comfortable.
Didn't you say this isn't serious?
It got serious.
Termeh ...
Honey ...
I'll cry too if you cry.
Why don't you go pay these people so mom would come back?
Whether your mom comes back has nothing to do with it.
Yes, it does.
She had come to stay.
Her stuff was in the back of the car, I saw myself.
If you think I'm responsible,
Go tell your mom to come back.
We'll call and setup a time with these people to go pay them.
I have doubts.
Didn't he throw you?
Yes.
Did something happen at home?
No. Even before it,
my child didn't move.
Before he threw you?
So the child had already died?
- I do not know. Maybe.
- What happened before?
I'm not sure, but I had
pains the previous night.
- Have you had a miscarriage before?
- No.
I was hit by a car.
His dad had left to go outside.
So I went after him.
He was crossing the steert.
I ran to get him so he wouldn't get hit by a car,
but a car hit me.
The pain began that night.
Does your husband know about this?
Why don't you go talk about this in the court?
My husband would kill himself if he
found out I came here and said these things.
He's been waiting since yesterday,
when he told about it to the lenders.
What does my husband have to do with this?
Go look what's happend to our life.
It's my own fault.
Whe you called him yesterday about the money...
... I got really scared.
I called a few people.
They said if you have doubts,
It'd be a great sin to take the money.
It has to be proven that my husband is innocent,
so we wouldn't have to pay the money.
No please.
I beg you not to take these words outside here.
But your husband's not letting go.
I fear for my child.
I fear too if I take the money;
Something might happen to my kid
So now what can I do?
Don't pay this money.
Don't.
Will your husband let it go?
Give that to me.
Go bring some plates.
Don't worry.
Nothing will happen.
Whenever you withdrew your complaint,
We'll give you these three checks right there.
God bless.
Hojjat, go bring a pen and paper,
Write all these down.
I just wanted to say something before...
- Lets just end it.
- I accepted, but...
- There's no need for...
Sure, I just wanted to say something in the
presence of my daughter and his wife.
Why isn't she coming?
Thank you, Ma'am.
Could you call my daughter too, please.
Little girl,
your father needs you.
Termeh, come sit here.
Excuse me.
- No problem.
Look ...
I wrote the checks and I'll give them to you.
No problem.
Done.
I had a favor to ask, though.
Ma'am, you're a religious woman.
Please swear on a Quran that I was
the casue of your miscarriage.
Please bring a Quran.
Go bring it yourself.
Come back soon, or they'll get suspicious.
Lenders are here for the money.
Don't make us look bad, I beg you.
I won't swear.
Didn't you say the car hit you
when you went after his father?
- Why aren't you coming?
- She's afraid to swear.
- What do you mean?
- I... I have doubts.
Oh God ...
Azam, you go be with them.
Why are you saying this now?
I swear I told Azam.
Tell me exactly what happened.
The day before it, a car hit me.
And I had a lot of pain that night.
- Let's go, I'll take responsibility for the sin.
- No.
It's a sin. I asked.
What sin? He himself agreed to give.
Let's go.
I'm scared.
I swear to god, we'll become hapless.
More hapless than this?
Look at my situation for one second.
Have mercy on me.
Have mercy to your child.
I'm afraid something would happen to our child.
Why are you doing this?
- Let's go.
- I can not.
I swear I can't.
- Come on, I'm hapless, let's go.
Lady, why'd come you here tonight?
Didn't I tell you not to come?
Didn't I say we don't want this money?
How can I live in this house anymore?
Why did you do this to my life?
Come on, honey.
Honey, Let's go.
- Hello.
- Hello. Come on in.
So, what's the decision?
Your parents have left the decision to
you now that they are seperating.
Which do you prefer to live with?
Your dad or your mom?
- Have you made your decision yet?
- Yes.
- Yeah?
- Have you made your decision, or not?
- Yes.
So what's it going to be, my dear?
Do I have to say it now?
- If you havn't thought about it ...
- Yes, I have.
- If you havn't thought about it yet...
- Yes, I've made my mind.
So?
If it's too hard for you,
do you want them to go outside?
Can they?
Sir, wait outside for a minute.
You too please, Ma'am.
Translation by: DHARMA EDASIA