(FOX FANFARE)
(THEME MUSIC PLAYING)
(TIE FIGHTERS ROARING LOUDLY)
MAN: Command
station, this is...
ST-321. Code
clearance blue.
We're starting
our approach.
Deactivate the
security shield.
The security deflector...
shield will be deactivated
when we have
confirmation...
of your code transmission.
Stand by.
- You are clear to proceed.
- We're starting our approach.
(ROARING CONTINUES)
(ALARM BLARING INDISTINCTLY)
Inform the
commander that...
Lord Vader's shuttle
has arrived.
Sir.
(DARTH VADER THEME PLAYING)
Lord Vader, this is an
unexpected pleasure.
We're honored by
your presence.
DARTH VADER: You
may dispense...
with the pleasantries,
Commander.
I'm here to put...
you back on schedule.
I assure you, Lord
Vader, my men...
are working as
fast as they can.
Perhaps I can find new...
ways to motivate them.
I tell you this
station will...
be operational, as planned.
The emperor does not...
share your optimistic...
appraisal of the situation.
But he asks the impossible.
I need more men.
Then perhaps you
can tell...
him when he arrives.
The emperor's coming here?
That is correct, Commander.
And he is most...
displeased with your...
apparent lack of progress.
We shall double our efforts.
I hope so, Commander...
for your sake.
The emperor is not as...
forgiving as I am.
- (R2-D2 BEEPS RAPIDLY)
- C-3PO: Of course I'm worried.
And you should be, too.
Lando Calrissian and
poor Chewbacca...
never returned from
this awful place.
(R2-D2 BEEPING)
Don't be so sure.
If I told you half
the things I've...
heard about this
Jabba the Hutt,
- you'd probably short-circuit.
- (R2-D2 WHINING)
(R2-D2 WHISTLING)
R2, are you sure this
is the right place?
(WHISTLES, BEEPS)
I'd better knock, I suppose.
There doesn't seem
to be anyone here.
Let's go back and
tell Master Luke.
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
- Goodness gracious me!
- (SPEAKING HUTTESE)
R2...
D-Toa.
(BEEPING)
(HUTTESE)
C-3POA.
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
(JABBA LAUGHS)
I don't think they're...
going to let us in, R2.
- (BEEPING)
- We'd better go.
(DOOR CREAKING)
(R2-D2 BEEPING)
C-3PO: R2, Wait!
Oh, dear! R2!
R2, I really don't
think we...
should rush into all this.
Oh, R2!
R2, wait for me!
(WHISTLES, BEEPS)
(GROWLS)
(R2-D2 BEEPS)
(GROWLING)
Just you deliver
Master Luke's...
message and get
us out of here.
- Oh, my! Oh!
- (GROWLING)
- Oh, no!
- (HUTTESE)
Oh, my.
(C-3PO SPEAKS HUTTESE)
(R2-D2 BEEPS)
We bring a message
to your...
master Jabba the Hutt.
- (HUTTESE)
- (R2-D2 BEEPING)
(WHISTLING)
- And a gift.
- (BEEPS)
- Gift? What gift?
- (BEEPS, WHISTLES)
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
(R2-D2 BEEPING)
He says that our
instructions...
are to give it only to...
Jabba himself.
(R2-D2 WHISTLING)
(GROWLING)
I'm terribly sorry.
I'm afraid he's ever so...
stubborn about these
sort of things.
C-3PO: R2.
I have a bad feeling
about this.
Oh.
(BARKING)
JABBA: Oh.
(R2-D2 WHINING)
Ohh!
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
- Good morning.
- (R2-D2 WHIMPERS)
(HUTTESE)
- The message, R2. The message.
- (BEEPS)
Oohh shoodah.
(R2-D2 BEEPING)
LUKE: Greetings, Exalted One.
- Allow me to introduce myself.
- Ohh.
I am Luke Skywalker,
Jedi knight...
and friend to Captain Solo.
LUKE: I know
that you are...
powerful, mighty Jabba,
and that your anger with...
Solo must be
equally powerful.
I seek an audience
with Your
Greatness to bargain
for Solo's life.
(JABBA LAUGHING)
LUKE: With your widsom...
I'm sure that we can
work out an arrangement
which will be
mutually beneficial
and enable us to avoid
any unpleasant confrontation.
As a token of
my goodwill...
I present to you a gift...
these two droids.
- What did he say?
- (BEEPS)
Both are hardworking...
and will serve you well.
This can't be. R2, your...
playing the wrong message.
(LAUGHS)
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
Aah!
(HUTTESE)
- We're doomed.
- Mmm.
Solo.
R2, look...
Captain Solo.
C-3PO: And he's still...
frozen in carbonite.
(R2-D2 WHISTLES)
(LAUGHING)
What could possibly have...
come over Master Luke?
Was it something I did?
He never expressed any...
unhappiness with my work.
Ohh! How horrid!
Ohh!
(GROWLING)
(WHISTLING)
(WHINING)
(DROID YELLING)
(SCREAMING)
Ah, good.
New acquisitions.
You are a protocol...
droid, are you not?
I am C-3PO...
Yes or no will do.
Oh. Well, yes.
How many languages...
do you speak?
I am fluent in over
six million forms
of communication and can...
Splendid.
We have been without
an interpreter
since our master got...
angry with our last
protocol droid and...
disintegrated him.
- Disintegrated?
- (SCREAMS)
Oh.
Guard!
This protocol droid...
might be useful.
Fit him with a
restraining...
bolt and take him back
up to His Excellency's...
main audience chamber.
R2, don't leave me!
(EXCLAIMS)
(WHISTLES, BEEPING)
You're a feisty little one,
but you'll soon...
learn some respect.
I have need for you on...
the master's sail barge,
and I think you'll...
fill in nicely.
No! No! No!
(SCREAMING)
(HUTTESE MUSIC PLAYING)
No, no, no! Ah, lower!
(COUNTS IN HUTTESE)
(SINGING IN HUTTESE)
(SCREAMING)
- Whoops! Uh-oh!
- (SCREAMING CONTINUES)
(WHOOPING)
(BANGING)
- (CREAKING)
- (GASPS)
- (GROWLING)
- (SCREAMING)
(SQUEALS)
- (ZAPS)
- (HUTTESE)
Oh!
(YELLS)
(HUTTESE)
(GROANS)
- (CHEWIE EXCLAIMS)
- (HUTTESE)
No, Chewbacca!
(GROWLS)
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
C-3PO: Yes, I am here...
Your Worshipfulness.
Yes?
(HUTTESE)
The illustrious Jabba...
bids you welcome
and will gladly pay you...
the reward of 25,000.
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
- 50,000. No less.
- (YELLS)
(C-3PO SCREAMS)
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
What did I say?
(HUTTESE)
The mighty Jabba asks...
why he must pay 50,000.
(SPEAKING ALIEN DIALECT)
Because he's holding...
a thermal detonator!
(SCREAMING)
(CHEWIE GROWLING)
(LAUGHING)
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
Jabba offers the...
sum of 35...
and I do suggest you take it.
(GROWLS)
(SPEAKING UBESE)
He agrees!
(CHEWIE HOWLS)
(ROARING)
(FESTIVE TUNE PLAYING)
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
(CHEWIE ROARS)
(ROARING CONTINUES)
(GROWLING)
(BELCHES)
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYS)
(CLINKING)
(THUDS)
Just relax...
for a moment.
You're free...
of the carbonite.
(SHUSHES)
You have...
hibernation sickness.
I can't see.
Your eyesight will...
return in time.
- Where am I?
- Jabba's Palace.
Who are you?
- Someone who loves you.
- Leia.
I got to get you out of here.
(JABBA LAUGHING)
What's that?
- (LAUGHING CONTINUES)
- I know that laugh.
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
Hey, Jabba... Look,
Jabba, I was...
just on my way
to pay you back,
and I got a little
sidetracked.
- It's not my fault.
- (HUTTESE)
(LAUGHING)
Look.
Jabba, I'll pay you triple.
You're throwing
away a fortune!
Don't be a fool!
LEIA: We have
powerful friends.
You're going to
regret this.
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
(GROANS)
Oh, I can't bear to watch.
(LAUGHING)
HAN: Chewie?
- (GROWLS)
- Chewie, is that you?
- Chew. Chewie!
- (CHEWIE GROWLS)
I can't see, pal.
What's going on?
(CHEWIE GRUMBLING)
Luke? Luke's crazy.
Can't even take
care of himself...
much less rescue anybody.
(GROWLS)
(STAMMERS)
A Jedi knight?
I'm out of it for a little
while, everybody...
gets delusions of grandeur.
(GRUMBLES)
I'm all right, pal.
I'm all right.
(DOOR CREAKING)
(GROWLS)
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
LUKE: I must speak
with Jabba.
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
You will take me
to Jabba now.
You serve your master well.
And you will be rewarded.
At last! Master Luke's...
come to rescue me.
- Master.
- Ohh!
Luke Skywalker, Jedi Knight.
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
I must be allow to speak.
You will bring
Captain Solo...
and the Wookie to me.
(LAUGHING)
Nevertheless,
I'm taking Captain Solo...
and his friends.
You can either profit...
by this or be destroyed.
It's your choice,
but I warn you...
not to underestimate
my powers.
Master Luke, you're
standing on...
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
(LAUGHING)
- (YELLS)
- (SCREAMING)
(LAUGHING)
JABBA: Tibi Jedi!
Tibi Jedi!
(CREAKING)
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
Oh, no! The rancor!
(BEAST ROARING)
(SHRIEKING)
(CRUNCHES)
(ROARING)
- (ROARING)
- (GRUNTS)
Whoo-hoo!
(ROARING)
(ROARING CONTINUES)
(GROANS)
(YELLS IN HUTTESE)
(WHINING)
(SIGHS)
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
(SOBBING)
- LUKE: Han!
- HAN: Luke!
- Are you all right?
- Fine.
Together again, huh?
- Wouldn't miss it.
- How are we doing?
- Same as always.
- That bad, huh?
- Where's Leia?
- LEIA: I'm here!
(SPEAKS HUTTESE)
C-3PO: Oh, dear.
His High
Exaltedness, the...
great Jabba the Hutt,
has decreed that
you are to...
be terminated immediately.
Good. I hate long waits.
(LAUGHING)
You will therefore be...
taken to the Dune Sea...
and cast into the...
Pit of Carkoon,
the nesting place of the...
all-powerful Sarlacc.
Doesn't sound so bad.
In his belly, you
will find a new...
definition of pain
and suffering,
as you are slowly
digested...
over a thousand years.
(GROWLS)
On second thought,
let's pass on that.
You should have
bargained, Jabba.
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
That's the last mistake
you'll ever make.
(LAUGHING)
(ALL CLAMORING)
(BELLOWING)
(BAND FESTIVE TUNE PLAYS)
(BEEPING)
(CHEWIE GROWLS)
HAN: I think my eyes
are getting better.
Instead of a big
dark blur...
I see a big light blur.
There's nothing to see.
I used to live
here, you know.
You're going to die
Convenient.
Just stick close to
Chewie and Lando.
I've taken care
of everything.
Oh. Great.
Aah! Ow!
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
I'm terribly sorry.
R2, what are you doing here?
(BEEPS)
Well, I can see
you're serving...
drinks, but this
place is dangerous.
They're going to
execute Master Luke...
and, if we're not
careful, us, too.
(R2-D2 CHIRPING)
Hmm, I wish I had
your confidence.
(SHRIEKS)
(SPEAKING HUTTESE)
C-3PO: Victims of the...
almighty Sarlacc,
His Excellency
hopes that...
you will die honorably.
But should any of you...
wish to beg for mercy,
the great Jabba the Hutt...
will now listen
to your pleas.
(R2-D2 BEEPING)
JABBA: Tibi Jedi!
3PO!
You tell that
slimy piece...
of worm-ridden filth...
he'll get no such...
pleasure from us! Right?
- (CHEWIE GROWLS)
- (R2-D2 BEEPS)
LUKE: Jabba.
This is your last chance.
Free us, or die.
(LAUGHS)
(SPEAKS HUTTESE)
(SHRIEKS)
(GRUNTS)
(CHEWIE GROWLS)
(THRILLING MUSIC PLAYING)
(LIGHTSABER ACTIVATING)
(YELLING)
(EXCLAIMS)
(SCREAMING)
(CHEWIE YELPING RAPIDLY)
LUKE: Easy, Chewie.
(YELLING ANGRILY)
LANDO: Whoa! Whoa! Whoa!
LANDO: Help!
(SCREAMS, GROANS)
HAN: Chewie, you're hit?
Where is it?
(CHEWIE EXCLAIMING IN PAIN)
- (SCREAMS)
- LANDO: Han! Chewie!
Lando!
Boba Fett?
HAN: Boba Fett? Where?
What the-
(SCREAMING)
(GROANS)
(MEN CLAMORING INDISTINCTLY)
(BELCHES)
(EXCLAIMING IN HUTTESE)
(GRUNTS)
(SCREAMING)
(JABBA GROANING HARDLY)
- Lando, grab it!
- LANDO: Lower it!
HAN: I'm trying!
(JABBA SCREAMING)
(LEIA GRUNTS)
(GROANING SOFTLY)
- HAN: Whoa!
- LANDO: Whoa! Whoa!
(EXCLAIMING)
- Grab it, Chewie!
- I'm slipping!
Come on, grab it!
(SCREAMS)
HAN: Grab it, almost!
You almost got it!
- LANDO: Whoa!
- (LIGHTSABER ACTIVATING)
(CHEWIE GRUNTS)
Gently, now. All right.
Easy, easy. Hold
me, Chewie.
(LANDO SCREAMING)
- Chewie!
- (EXCLAIMING)
HAN: Chewie, give me the gun!
Don't move, Lando!
Oh, wait! I thought
you were blind!
It's all right! I can see a lot better!
Don't move!
Just a little higher!
(SHRIEKING)
Chewie, pull us up!
- (CHEWIE GRUNTING GENTLY)
- HAN: Up, Chewie! Up!
(WHISTLES GENTLY)
Come on, we gotta
get out of here.
Not my eyes! R2, help!
- C-3PO: Quickly, R2!
- (SCREAMS)
Beast!
Get the gun!
Point in the deck! (SCREAMS)
LUKE: Point in the deck!
(SCREAMS)
R2, where are we going?
I couldn't possibly go...
(C-3PO SCREAMING)
(R2-D2 WHISTLES EXCITEDLY)
Come on!
(CRUMPLING EXPLOSIONS)
Let's go. And don't
forget the droids.
We're on our way.
(R2-D2 BEEPING THEN WHISTLES)
(BEEPING CONTINUES)
(CRUMPLING EXPLOSIONS)
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
I'll meet you back
at the fleet.
LEIA: Hurry. The
Alliance...
should be assembled by now.
I will.
HAN: Hey, Luke. Thanks.
Thanks for coming after me.
I owe you one.
- (SCOFFS SOFTLY)
- (R2-D2 BEEPS RAPIDLY)
That's right, R2. We're going
to the Dagobah system.
(R2-D2 BEEPING)
We'll promise to keep.
An old friend.
(TIE FIGHTERS ROARING LOUDLY)
(DARTH VADER THEME PLAYING)
(STEAM HISSING)
EMPEROR: Rise, my friend.
(DARTH VADER BREATHING)
DARTH VADER: The Death
Star will be...
completed on schedule.
You've done well, Lord Vader.
And now I sense you...
wish to continue
your search for...
young Skywalker.
Yes, my master.
Patience, my friend.
In time...
he will seek you out.
And when he does...
you must bring...
him before me.
He has grown strong.
Only together can...
we turn him...
to the dark side...
of the Force.
As you wish.
Everything is proceeding
as I have foreseen.
(EMPEROR LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
(BEEPS, WHISTLES)
Hmm. Hmm.
YODA: That face you make...
Look I so old...
to young eyes?
No. Of course not.
I do.
(COUGHING SOFTLY)
Yes, I do.
Sick have I become.
Hmm, old and weak.
When 900 years old...
you reach, look as good...
you will not, hmm?
(YODA LAUGHING RAPIDLY)
Soon will I rest.
Yes.
Forever sleep.
Hmm. Ahh...
earned it I have.
Master Yoda, you can't die.
Strong am I...
with the Force,
but not that strong.
Twilight is upon me,
and soon...
night must fall.
That is the way of things...
the way of the Force.
But I need your help.
LUKE: I've come back to...
complete the training.
No more training
do you require.
Already know you...
that which you need.
(SIGHS)
Then I am a Jedi.
Oh.
(LAUGHS, COUGHS)
Not yet.
One thing remains...
Vader.
You must confront Vader.
Then, only then,
a Jedi will you be.
And confront him you will.
Master Yoda.
Is Darth Vader my father?
Rest I need.
Yes.
Rest.
Yoda, I must know.
Your father he is.
Told you, did he?
Yes.
Unexpected this is.
And unfortunate.
Unfortunate that I
know the truth?
YODA: No.
Unfortunate...
that you rushed to face him,
that incomplete was...
your training,
that not ready for
the burden were you.
I'm sorry.
YODA: Remember...
a Jedi's strength...
flows from the Force.
But beware...
Anger...
fear...
aggression...
the dark side...
are they.
Once you start down
the dark path,
forever will it...
dominate your destiny.
Luke.
Do not...
do not...
underestimate the...
powers of the emperor,
or suffer your father's...
fate you will.
Luke, when gone am I,
the last of the
Jedi will you be.
Luke...
the Force runs strong...
in your family.
Pass on what you...
have learned.
Luke...
there is...
another...
Sky...
walker.
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYS)
(R2-D2 BEEPS SOFTLY)
(BEEPING CONTINUES)
I can't do it, R2.
(BEEPS, WHISTLES)
I can't go it alone.
OBI-WAN: Yoda will...
always be with you.
Obi-Wan.
Why didn't you tell me?
You told me Vader
betrayed...
and murdered my father.
Your father...
was seduced by the...
dark side of the Force.
He ceased to be...
Anakin Skywalker...
and became Darth Vader.
When that happened,
the good man
who was your father...
was destroyed.
So what I told
you was true...
from a certain point of view.
A certain point of view?
Luke, you're
going to find...
that many of the truths
we cling to
depend greatly...
on our own point of view.
OBI-WAN: Anakin was...
a good friend.
When I first knew him,
your father was...
already a great pilot,
but I was amazed
how strongly...
the Force was with him.
I took it upon myself...
to train him as a Jedi.
I thought that I
could instruct...
him just as well as Yoda.
I was wrong.
There is still good in him.
He's more machine...
now than man,
twisted and evil.
I can't do it, Ben.
OBI-WAN: You cannot...
escape your destiny.
You must face...
Darth Vader again.
I can't kill my own father.
Then the emperor...
has already won.
You were our only hope.
Yoda spoke of another.
The other he spoke of
is your twin sister.
- But I have no sister.
- Hmm.
To protect you both
from the emperor,
you were hidden
from your...
father when you were born.
The emperor knew, as I did,
if Anakin were to...
have any offspring,
they would be a
threat to him.
That is the reason...
why your sister remains...
safely anonymous.
Leia.
Leia's my sister.
Your insight serves you well.
Bury your feelings...
deep down, Luke.
They do you credit...
but they could be made...
to serve the emperor.
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
Well, look at you.
A general, huh?
Ah, someone must have
told them about my....
little maneuver at the
Battle of Tanaab.
Well, don't look
at me, pal.
I just said you
were a fair pilot.
I didn't know they
were looking for...
somebody to lead
this crazy attack.
I'm surprised they
didn't ask you to do it.
Well, who says they didn't?
But I ain't crazy.
You're the respectable
one, remember?
(BELL CHIMES)
MON: The emperor's
made a critical error,
and the time for our
attack has come.
The data brought
to us by the
Bothan spies pinpoint the...
exact location of the...
emperor's new
battle station.
We also know that
the weapon...
systems of this
Death Star...
are not yet operational.
With the imperial
fleet spread...
throughout the galaxy,
in a vain effort
to engage us,
it is relatively unprotected.
But most important of all,
we've learned that
the emperor...
himself is personally
overseeing...
the final stages of the...
construction of
this Death Star.
Many Bothans died...
to bring us this information.
Admiral Ackbar, please.
ACKBAR: You can see here...
the Death Star...
orbiting the forest moon...
of Endor.
Although the
weapon systems...
on this Death Star...
are not yet operational,
the Death Star does have...
a strong defense mechanism.
It is protected by...
an energy shield...
which is generated
from the...
nearby forest
moon of Endor.
(BEEPING)
The shield must
be deactivated...
if any attack is
to be attempted.
Once the shield is down...
our cruisers will...
create a perimeter...
while the fighters fly...
into the superstructure...
and attempt to knock out...
the main reactor.
General Calrissian.
Has volunteered to lead
the fighter attack.
Good luck.
You're gonna need it.
General Madine.
MADINE: We have stolen a...
small imperial shuttle.
Disguised as a
cargo ship and...
using a secret
imperial code,
a strike team will
land on the moon
and deactivate the
shield generator.
C-3PO: Sounds dangerous.
I wonder who they found
to pull that off.
General Solo, is your...
strike team assembled?
Uh, my team's ready.
I don't have a
command crew...
for the shuttle.
- (CHEWIE GROWLS)
- That's gonna be rough, pal.
I didn't wanna speak for you.
(GROWLS)
- That's one.
- General.
- Count me in.
- LUKE: I'm with you, too.
- What is it?
- Ask me again sometime.
- Luke.
- Hi, Han. Chewie.
(R2-D2 WHISTLES)
"Exciting" is hardly the
word I would choose.
(THRILLING MUSIC PLAYING)
HAN: Look.
I want you to take her.
I mean it. Take her.
You need all the
help you can get.
She's the fastest
ship in the fleet.
All right, old buddy.
I know what she means to you.
I'll take good care of her.
She won't get a scratch.
All right?
Right.
I got your promise.
Not a scratch.
(CHUCKLES) Would you
get going, you pirate?
- Good luck.
- You too.
- Got her warmed?
- She's coming up.
(CHEWIE GRUNTS)
Yeah, well, I don't
think the...
Empire had Wookiees in mind...
when they designed
her, Chewie.
Hey, you awake?
Yeah. I just got a
funny feeling...
like I'm not gonna
see her again.
(GROWLS)
Come on, General, let's move.
Right. Chewie...
let's see what this
piece of junk can do.
- Ready, everybody?
- All set.
(R2-D2 BEEPING)
Here we go again.
HAN: All right. Hang on.
(THRUSTERS FIRES)
(TIE FIGHTERS ROARING)
DARTH VADER: What
is thy bidding...
my master?
Send the fleet to the...
far side of Endor.
There it will stay...
until called for.
What of the reports...
of the rebel fleet...
massing near Sullust?
EMPEROR: It is of no concern.
Soon the rebellion
will be crushed and
young Skywalker
will be one of us.
Your work here is
finished, my friend.
Go out to the command...
ship and await my orders.
Yes, my master.
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
If they don't go for
this, we're gonna have
to get out of here
pretty quick, Chewie.
MAN: (ON RADIO) We have
you on our screen now.
Please identify.
Shuttle Tydirium...
requesting deactivation...
of the deflector shield.
Shuttle Tydirium...
transmit the
clearance code...
for shield passage.
(CHEWIE GROWLS)
Transmission commencing.
Now we find out
if that code...
is worth the price we paid.
It'll work.
Vader's on that ship.
HAN: Now, don't get
jittery, Luke.
- There a lot of command ships.
- (CHEWIE GRUNTS)
Keep your distance,
though, Chewie, but don't
look like you're trying
to keep your distance.
- (CHEWIE GRUMBLES)
- HAN: I don't know.
Fly casual.
Where is that shuttle going?
Shuttle Tydirium...
what is your cargo
and destination?
HAN: Parts and technical
crew for the forest moon.
Do they have a
code clearance?
It's an older code,
sir, but it checks out.
I was about to clear them.
I'm endangering
the mission.
I shouldn't have come.
That's your imagination, kid.
Come on. Let's keep a
little optimism here.
Shall I hold them?
No.
Leave them to me.
I will deal with them myself.
As you wish, my lord.
Carry on.
They're not going
for it, Chewie.
(CHEWIE GRUNTS)
Shuttle Tydirium,
deactivation of
the shield...
will commence immediately.
- Follow your present course.
- (CHEWIE GROWLS)
Okay.
I told you it was
going to work.
No problem.
C-3PO: Oh, I told you
it was dangerous here!
(GROWLS)
LEIA: Should we try
and go around?
LUKE: I'll take time.
HAN: This whole
party will be...
for nothing if they see us.
(GROWLS)
Chewie and I will
take care of this.
You stay here.
Quietly. There might be...
more of them out there.
Hey, it's me.
(SIGHS)
Go for help! Go!
LUKE: Great! Come on!
(YELLS)
(GRUNTING)
Over there! Two more of them!
I see them! Wait!
Leia!
HAN: Hey, wait!
(ENGINES REVVING)
Quick! Jam their comlink!
Center switch!
Move closer!
Get alongside that one!
- (EXCLAIMS)
- (GRUNTS)
(SCREAMING)
(EXCLAIMS)
Keep on that one!
I'll take these two!
(EXPLODING)
(ENGINE REVVING)
(GASPS)
(LEIA SCREAMS)
(SCREAMING)
(EXPLODING)
(ENGINES REVVING)
(LUKE GRUNTS)
(LIGHTSABER ACTIVATES)
(EXPLODING)
(SIGHS)
(LIGHTSABER DEACTIVATING)
(R2-D2 BEEPING)
Oh, General Solo.
Somebody's coming.
(CHEWIE GROWLS SOFTLY)
Oh!
- Luke!
- (CHEWIE GROWLS)
Where's Leia?
What? She didn't come back?
- I thought she was with you.
- We got separated.
We better go look for her.
Take the squad ahead.
We'll meet...
at the shield
generator at 0300.
Come on, R2, we'll
need your scanners.
(R2-D2 BEEPS)
C-3PO: Don't worry,
Master Luke.
We know what to do.
(CHEWIE GROWLS)
And you said it
was pretty here.
(WHISTLES)
Eek!
- Eek!
- LEIA: Cut it out!
(EWOK GROWLS)
(SIGHS)
(GRUNTS)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(GROWLING)
I'm not gonna hurt you.
(GROANS)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
Well, looks like...
I'm stuck here.
Trouble is, I don't
know where here is.
LEIA: Maybe you can help me.
Come on. Sit down.
I promise I won't hurt you.
Now come here.
(GROWLING)
All right. You want
something to eat?
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
That's right.
- Come on. Hmm?
- (SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(SNIFFLES)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(SCREAMING)
Look, it's a hat.
It's not gonna hurt you.
Look.
(GROWLS)
You're a jittery little
thing, aren't you?
Ooh?
- What is it?
- (SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
- (SCREAMS)
- (GASPS)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
- Freeze!
- (GASPS)
Come on, get up.
(GROWLING)
Go get your ride. Take
her back to base.
Yes, sir.
- (EWOKESE)
- What the...
(LEIA YELLS)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
LEIA: Come on. Let's
get out of here.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(TIE FIGHTERS ROARING)
EMPEROR: I told
you to remain...
on the command ship.
DARTH VADER: A small
rebel force...
has penetrated
the shield...
and landed on Endor.
Yes, I know.
My son is with them.
EMPEROR: Are you sure?
I have felt him...
my master.
Strange that I have not.
I wonder if your...
feelings on this matter...
are clear, Lord Vader.
They are clear, my master.
Then you must go to the...
sanctuary moon and
wait for him.
He will come to me?
I have foreseen it.
His compassion for you...
will be his undoing.
He will come to you...
and then you will...
bring him before me.
As you wish.
HAN: Luke! Luke!
Oh, Master Luke.
(ROARS SOFTLY)
There's two more wrecked
speeders back there.
And I found this.
I'm afraid that
R2's sensors...
can find no trace
of Princess Leia.
I hope she's all right.
(CHEWIE GROWLS LOUDLY)
- What, Chewie?
- (CHEWIE GROWLS)
HAN: What, Chewie?
(CHEWIE GRUMBLING RAPIDLY)
Hey, I don't get it.
It's just a dead
animal, Chewie.
LUKE: Chewie, wait! Don't!
(ALL SCREAMING)
- Nice work.
- (CHEWIE HOWLING LOUDLY)
HAN: Great, Chewie. Great.
Always thinking
with your stomach.
LUKE: You take it easy.
Let's just...
figure a way to get
out of this thing.
- Han, can you reach my lightsaber?
- Yeah! Sure!
(R2-D2 WHISTLES)
R2, I'm not sure that's...
such a good idea.
It's a very long...
- drop!
- (ALL GROAN)
(HAN GROANS SOFTLY)
Ah.
(R2-D2 WHINING SADLY)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(CHEWIE GROWLS SADLY)
What...
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
Hey! Point that thing...
someplace else.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
- Hey!
- Han, don't. It'll be all right.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
LUKE: Chewie, give
them your crossbow.
(CHEWIE EXCLAIMS)
(GROANS) My head.
Oh, my goodness.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(CHANTING IN EWOKESE)
(C-3PO SPEAKING EWOKESE)
Do you understand
anything they're saying?
Oh, yes, Master Luke.
Remember that I
am fluent...
in over six
million forms...
What are you telling them?
Hello, I think.
I could be mistaken.
They're using a very
primitive dialect.
I do believe they think...
I am some sort of god.
(R2-D2 BEEPS RAPIDLY)
(CHEWIE GROWLS LOUDLY)
Well, why don't you use...
your divine influence...
and get us out of this?
I beg your pardon,
General Solo...
but that just
wouldn't be proper.
Proper?
It's against my
programming...
to impersonate a deity.
Why, you...
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
My mistake.
He's an old friend of mine.
Jabba jabba jabba.
(SCREAMING IN EWOKESE)
Ow! Hey.
(SQUEAKS)
(CHEWIE GRUMBLES SADLY)
I have a really bad
feeling about this.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
What did he say?
C-3PO: I'm rather
embarrassed, General Solo,
but it appears you
are to be the...
main course at a
banquet in my honor.
(CHEWIE EXCLAIMS)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
- Leia!
Your Royal Highness.
But these are my friends.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
3PO, tell them they...
must be set free.
(CHEWIE GRUMBLES ANGRILY)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
Somehow I got the
feeling that...
didn't help us very much.
3PO.
Tell them if they
don't do as you wish,
you'll become angry
and use your magic.
But, Master Luke,
what magic?
I couldn't possibly.
Just tell them.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
Boom!
You see, Master Luke?
They didn't believe
me, just as...
I said they wouldn't.
Wait, wait. (BLOWS)
(EWOKS WHOOPING INDISTINCTLY)
(SCREAMING)
Put me down! Help!
Somebody!
Somebody, help!
Master Luke! R2, R2, quickly!
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
- (BEEPS, GROANS)
- (THUDS)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(R2-D2 BEEPING)
(SCREAMS)
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh.
Thank goodness.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(R2-D2 CHIRPS SOFTLY)
LUKE: Thanks, 3PO.
I never knew I had it in me.
C-3PO: Woochana makawartas,
woochana makawartas.
Nervrenda bootootoo Tatooine.
Faraway, mana quitoo.
Princess Leia wasay wapa R2.
Oos batata rundi...
Darth Vader!
(DARTH VADER BREATHING)
Un Chenko baskimo...
quertonto Death Star.
(TIE FIGHTER ROARS)
(ZAPS)
Wos michi un Jedi,
Obi-Wan Kenobi.
Ee manu machi Vader konyono.
(LIGHTSABER ACTIVATING)
(R2-D2 BEEPING)
Yes, R2, I was just
coming to that.
Torron togosh.
(FEET STOMPING)
Master Luke
ahchiminie choodoo.
(SPACESHIP ROARS)
(ZAPPING)
(SCREAMS)
Uta Millennium Falcon...
ahchiminie Cloud City.
(ENGINES ROARING)
Oos nooch Vader.
(DARTH VADER BREATHING)
- Han Solo.
- (CHEWIE GROWLS SOFTLY)
Tiklo carbon!
Un dekochna gooboo Sarlacc.
(LIGHTSABER CRACKLING)
Haonna keenie chetoo...
toomoo maneta.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
What's going on?
I don't know.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(DRUM ROLLING)
Wonderful. We are now...
a part of the tribe.
Just what I always wanted.
(LAUGHS SOFTLY)
(R2-D2 BEEPING RAPIDLY)
Well, the short help's better...
than no help at all, Chewie.
He says the scouts are
going to show us...
the quickest way to
the shield generator.
Good. How far is it? Ask him.
We need some fresh
supplies, too.
- (SPEAKING EWOKESE)
- Try and get our weapons back.
Hurry up, will you?
I haven't got all day.
LEIA: Luke, what's wrong?
Leia.
Do you remember
your mother...
your real mother?
Just a little bit.
She died when I
was very young.
What do you remember?
Just images, really.
Feelings.
Tell me.
(SIGHS) She was...
Very beautiful.
Kind...
but sad.
Why are you asking me this?
I have no memory
of my mother.
I never knew her.
Luke, tell me, what's
troubling you?
Vader's here.
Now, on this moon.
How do you know?
I felt his presence.
He's come for me.
He can feel when I'm near.
That's why I have to go.
As long as I stay,
I'm endangering...
the group and our
mission here.
- I have to face him.
- Why?
He's my father.
Your father?
It won't be easy for you...
to hear it, but you must.
If I don't make it back, you're
the only hope for the Alliance.
Luke, don't talk that way.
You have a power...
I don't understand...
and could never have.
You're wrong, Leia.
You have that power, too.
In time, you'll learn...
to use it as I have.
The Force is strong
in my family.
My father has it.
I have it.
And...
my sister has it.
Yes.
It's you, Leia.
I know.
Somehow...
I've always known.
Then you know why I
have to face him.
No!
Luke, run away. Far away.
If he can feel
your presence...
then leave this place.
I wish I could go with you.
No, you don't.
You've always been strong.
But why must you
confront him?
Because... there is...
good in him. I've felt it.
He won't turn me
over to the emperor.
I can save him.
I can turn...
him back to the good side.
I have to try.
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
HAN: Hey, what's going on?
Nothing. I just
want to be...
alone for a little while.
Nothing?
Come on, tell me.
What's going on?
(STAMMERS) I can't tell you.
Could you tell Luke? Is
that who you could tell?
I...
Ahh.
HAN: I'm sorry.
Hold me.
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
This is the rebel that
surrendered to us.
Although he denies it.
I believe there may
be more of them,
and I request
permission to conduct
a further search of the area.
He was armed...
only with this.
DARTH VADER: Good
work, Commander.
Leave us.
Conduct your search and...
bring his companions to me.
Yes, my lord.
The emperor has
been expecting you.
I know, Father.
So, you have...
accepted the truth.
I've accepted the
truth that you...
were once Anakin
Skywalker, my father.
That name no longer...
has any meaning for me.
It is the name of
your true self.
You've only forgotten.
LUKE: I know there
is good in you.
The emperor hasn't driven
it from you fully.
That was why you
couldn't destroy me.
That's why you
won't bring...
me to your emperor now.
(LIGHTSABER ACTIVATING)
I see you have
constructed...
the new lightsaber.
Your skills...
are complete.
(LIGHTSABER DEACTIVATING)
Indeed you are powerful...
as the emperor...
has foreseen.
Come with me.
Obi-Wan once thought...
as you do.
You don't know...
the power of...
the dark side.
I must obey...
my master.
I will not turn.
And you'll be
forced to kill me.
If that is your destiny.
Search your feelings, Father.
You can't do this.
I feel the conflict
within you.
Let go of your hate.
It is too late...
for me, son.
The emperor will show you...
the true nature...
of the Force.
He is your master, now.
Then my father is truly dead.
(CHEWIE GRUNTS)
LEIA: The main entrance
to the control bunker
is on the far side of
that landing platform.
This isn't going to be easy.
HAN: Hey, don't worry.
Chewie and me got
into a lot of...
places more heavily
guarded than this.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
LEIA: What's he saying?
He says there's a
secret entrance...
on the other side
of the ridge.
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
Admiral, we're in position.
All fighters accounted for.
Proceed with the countdown.
All groups assume...
attack coordinates.
(SPEAKING ALIEN LANGUAGE)
Don't worry.
My friend's down there.
He'll have that
shield down on time.
(SPEAKING ALIEN LANGUAGE)
Or this will be the...
shortest offensive
of all time.
All craft.
Prepare to jump into...
hyperspace on my mark.
LANDO: All right, stand by.
(THRUSTERS FIRING)
(WHISTLING)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
Back door, huh? Good idea.
It's only a few guards.
This shouldn't be
too much trouble.
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
It only takes one
to sound the alarm.
Then we'll do it
real quiet like.
Oh, my!
Princess Leia!
I'm afraid our furry
companion has
gone and done...
something rather rash.
- (CHEWIE EXCLAIMS)
- LEIA: Oh, no.
(HAN SIGHS)
There goes our
surprise attack.
- (ENGINE STARTS)
- Look, over there! Stop him!
(SCREAMING)
Not bad for a
little furball.
There's only one left.
You stay here.
We'll take care of this.
(EWOKESE)
I have decided that...
we shall stay here.
Whoo-hoo!
Whoo! Whoo!
Hey!
- (BLASTER FIRES)
- (CHEWIE GROWLS LOUDLY)
(DARTH VADER THEME PLAYING)
EMPEROR: Welcome...
Young Skywalker.
I have been expecting you.
You no longer need those.
(CLATTERS)
Guards, leave us.
I'm looking forward to...
completing your training.
In time, you...
will call me...
master.
You're gravely mistaken.
You won't convert me...
as you did my father.
Oh, no.
My young Jedi.
You will find...
it is you...
who are mistaken...
about a great...
many things.
DARTH VADER: His lightsaber.
Ah, yes.
A Jedi's weapon.
Much like your father's.
By now you must know...
your father can
never be turned...
from the dark side.
So will it be with you.
You're wrong.
Soon I'll be dead,
and you with me.
(LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
Perhaps you refer to...
the imminent attack...
of your rebel fleet.
Yes.
I assure you...
we are quite safe...
from your friends here.
Your overconfidence
is your weakness.
Your faith in your...
friends is yours.
It is pointless...
to resist, my son.
Everything that...
has transpired...
has done so according...
to my design.
Your friends up there on...
the sanctuary moon are
walking into a trap...
as is your rebel fleet.
It was I who allowed...
the Alliance to know...
the location of...
the shield generator.
It is quite safe from...
your pitiful little band.
An entire legion of my...
best troops awaits them.
Oh...
I'm afraid the...
deflector shield...
will be quite...
operational...
when your friends arrive.
All right!
Up! Move! Come on!
Quickly, quickly.
- Chewie!
- (GROWLS RAPIDLY)
(GROANS)
LEIA: Han, hurry!
The fleet will be
here any moment.
- Charges, come on! Come on!
- (CHEWIE ROARS)
Oh, my! They'll be captured!
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
Wait! Wait! Come back!
- R2, stay with me.
- (BEEPS SOFTLY)
Freeze!
- (HAN GRUNTS)
- (SCREAMING)
You rebel scum!
(CHEWIE EXCLAIMING)
(HOWLING ANGRILY)
(THRILLING MUSIC PLAYING)
All wings report in.
Red leader standing by.
Gray leader standing by.
Green leader standing by.
Lock S-Foils in
attack positions.
May the Force be with us.
(SPEAKING ALIEN LANGUAGE)
We've gotta be able
to get some kind...
of reading on that
shield, up or down.
(SPEAKING ALIEN LANGUAGE)
How could they be jamming
us if they don't know...
if we're coming.
LANDO: Break off the attack!
The shield is still up.
I get no reading. You sure?
LANDO: Pull up! All
craft, pull up!
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
Take evasive action.
Green Group, stick to...
Holding Sector MV-7.
Admiral, we have enemy...
ships in Sector 47.
It's a trap.
Fighters, coming in!
There's too many of them!
Accerate to attack speed!
Draw their fire away
from the cruisers.
Copy, Gold Leader.
EMPEROR: Come, boy.
See for youself.
From here, you
will witness...
the final destruction...
of the Alliance...
and the end of your...
insignificant rebellion.
You want this...
don't you?
The hate is swelling...
in you now.
Take your Jedi weapon.
Use it.
I am unarmed.
Strike me down with it.
Give in to your anger.
With each passing moment...
you make yourself...
more my servant.
No.
It is unavoidable.
It is your destiny.
You, like your father,
are now...
Mine.
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
STORMTROOPER: All
right, move it!
Keep moving. Come on.
C-3PO: Hello! I
say over there!
Were you looking for me?
(CHEWIE GRUNTS)
Bring those two down here.
Well, they're on their way.
R2, are you sure this
was a good idea?
- Freeze!
- (EXCLAIMS)
- Don't move!
- We surrender.
(EWOKS YELLING LOUDLY)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(GROWLS RAPIDLY)
(EWOKESE)
- (SCREAMS)
- (GROWLS)
- (GRUNTS)
- (GROANS)
(SCREAMING)
(SCREAMS)
(MEN CLAMORING INDISTINCTLY)
(EWOKS SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
(GROANS)
- (EWOKS YELLING)
- (STORMTROOPER SCREAMING)
(YELLING INDISTINCTLY)
(SCREAMING)
(YELLING)
(SCREAMING CONTINUES)
(SCREAMING)
(GROANS)
(SCREAMS)
The code's changed!
We need R2!
Here's the terminal!
R2, where are you?
We need you at the
bunker right away.
(GROANS)
What do you mean,
you're going?
(R2-D2 BEEPING EXCITEDLY)
Going where, R2?
No, wait! R2!
Oh, this is no
time for heroics!
Come back!
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
Watch yourself, Wedge.
Three from above.
- Red Three, Red Two, pull in.
- Got it.
Three of them coming
in, twenty degrees.
Cut to the left. I'll
take the leader.
They're heading for
the medical frigate.
- Pressure steady.
- (SPEAKING ALIEN LANGUAGE)
Only the fighters are attacking.
I wonder...
what those Stardestroyers
are waiting for.
We're in attack
position, sir.
Hold here.
We're not going to attack?
I have my orders from
the emperor himself.
He has something special
planned for them.
We only need to keep
them from escaping.
EMPEROR: As you can see...
my young apprentice,
your friends...
have failed.
Now witness...
the firepower...
of this fully armed...
and operational...
battle station.
Fire at will, Commander.
Fire!
Oh, oh!
That blast came from
the Death Star!
LANDO: That thing
is operational!
Home One, this
is Gold Leader.
We saw it. All craft
prepare to retreat.
You won't get another
chance at this, Admiral.
We have no choice...
General Calrissian.
Our cruisers can't repel...
firepower of
that magnitude.
Han will have
that shield down.
We've got to give
him more time!
(SCREAMING)
(GROANS)
- (YELLING)
- (GROANS)
(GROANING)
(R2-D2 BEEPS)
We're coming.
- (SCREAMS)
- (BEEPING)
Come on, come on!
(BEEPING)
Oh, R2! Hurry!
- (R2-D2 SCREAMING)
- Oh, my goodness!
(BEEPING CONTINUES)
R2, Why did you have
to be so brave?
(R2-D2 GROANS SADLY)
Well, I suppose I could...
hot-wire this thing.
LEIA: I'll cover you.
(SCREAMING)
(GROANING)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(GROANING CONTINUES)
(SCREAMING)
LANDO: Yes, I said closer!
Move as close as you can...
and engage those
Stardestroyers...
at point-blank range!
At that close range,
we won't last...
long against those
Stardestroyers.
We'll last longer
than we...
will against
that Death Star!
And we might just take
a few of them with us!
She's gonna blow!
I'm hit!
EMPEROR: Your fleet is lost.
And your friends on the...
Endor moon will
not survive.
There is no escape....
my young apprentice.
The Alliance...
will die...
as will your friends.
Good.
I can feel...
your anger.
I am defenseless.
Take your weapon.
Strike me down with...
all of your hatred...
and your journey...
towards the dark side...
will be complete!
(LIGHTSABERS ACTIVATING)
- (LIGHTSABER CRACKLING)
- (EMPEROR LAUGHING)
(EWOKS SHOUTING)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(CHEWIE GROWLS LOUDLY)
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
(CHEWIE YELLING)
Look! Get him off of there!
Whoa!
- (SCREAMING)
- (GROANS)
(EWOK SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(CHEWIE ROARS)
(ROARING EXCITEDLY)
(ROARING CONTINUES)
Yahoo!
Yee-haa!
(CHEWIE EXCLAIMS HAPPILY)
Yahoo!
Yee-ha! Yee-ha!
(CHEWIE GROWLING)
Yee-ha-ha!
(CHEWIE GROWLS RAPIDLY)
(GROANS)
(SCREAMS)
(SCREAMING)
Get down! Get down!
(GROANS)
Yee-ha!
(YELLS IN EWOKESE)
HAN: I think I got it!
I got it!
(LEIA SCREAMS)
(GROANING)
Princess Leia, are
you all right?
- Let's see.
- It's not bad.
- Freeze!
- Oh, dear.
Don't move!
- I love you.
- I know.
STORMTROOPER: Hands up!
Stand up!
Stay back.
- (CHEWIE GROWLS)
- Chewie!
(GROWLS LOUDLY)
Get down here! She's wounded!
No, wait!
I got an idea.
(LIGHTSABER CRACKLING)
(CRACKLING CONTINUES)
(GROANS, SCREAMS)
(EMPEROR LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
Good.
Use your aggressive...
feelings, boy.
Let the hate...
flow through you.
(EMPEROR LAUGHS SOFTLY)
(LIGHTSABER DEACTIVATING)
Obi-Wan as...
taught you well.
I will not fight you, Father.
- You are unwise to lower your defenses.
- (LIGHTSABER ACTIVATING)
(LIGHTSABER CRACKLING)
(CRACKLING CONTINUES)
Your thoughts
betray you, Father.
I feel the good in you...
the conflict.
There is...
no conflict.
You couldn't bring yourself
to kill me before.
I don't believe you'll
destroy me now.
You underestimate the...
power of the dark side.
DARTH VADER: If you
will not fight, then...
you will meet your destiny.
(THRILLING MUSIC PLAYING)
(LAUGHING RAPIDLY)
EMPEROR: Good.
Good!
(LIGHTSABER ACTIVATING)
Watch out! Squad at Point 06.
I'm on it, Gold Leader.
Good shot, Red Two!
We're sure in the
middle of it now.
Come on, Han, old buddy...
don't let me down.
HAN: It's over, Commander.
The rebels have
been routed.
They're fleeing
into the woods.
We need reinforcements...
to continue the pursuit.
Send three squads to help.
- Open the back door.
- Sir.
(EWOKS CHEERING)
Throw me another charge!
(CHEWIE GROWLS SOFTLY)
DARTH VADER: You cannot...
hide forever, Luke.
LUKE: I will not fight you.
Give yourself to...
the dark side.
It is the only way you...
can save your friends.
Yes.
Your thoughts betray you.
Your feelings for...
them are strong,
especially for...
sister.
So...
you have...
a twin sister.
Your feelings have now...
betrayed her, too.
Obi-Wan was wise...
to hide her from me.
Now his failure...
is complete.
If you will not turn...
to the dark side...
then perhaps...
she will.
- (LIGHTSABER ACTIVATES)
- Never!
(LIGHTSABER CRACKLING)
(CRACKLING CONTINUES)
(GRUNTS)
(GROANS, SCREAMS)
(GROANING)
(EMPEROR LAUGHING EXCITEDLY)
Good!
(LAUGHING CONTINUES)
Your hate has...
made you powerful.
Now...
fulfill your destiny...
and take your father's...
place at my side!
(LIGHTSABER HUMMING)
(SIZZLING)
(LIGHTSABER DEACTIVATING)
Never.
(CLATTERS)
I'll never turn
to the dark side.
You failed, Your Highness.
I am a Jedi...
like my father before me.
(PANTING SOFTLY)
So be it...
Jedi.
- (DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
- HAN: Move! Move!
(CRUMPLING EXPLOSIONS)
The shield is down!
Commence attack on the...
Death Star's main reactor!
LANDO: We're on our way!
Red Group, Gold Group!
All fighters, follow me!
(LAUGHING) I told
you they'd do it!
(LAUGHING HAPPILY)
If you will not be turned...
you will be...
destroyed.
(ELECTRICITY CRACKLING)
(LUKE GROANING)
Young fool.
Only now, and the end.
Do you understand?
- (CRACKLING)
- (LUKE GROANS)
- (CRACKLING CONTINUES)
- (GROANING CONTINUES)
(GRUNTING)
Your feeble skills...
are no match for
the power...
of the dark side.
(SCREAMS, GROANS)
You have paid the price...
for your lack of vision.
(SCREAMS)
Father, please!
(SCREAMING)
Help, me!
(SCREAMING CONTINUES)
(LUKE SCREAMING)
Now, Young Skywalker.
You will die.
(GROANING SOFTLY)
(LUKE SCREAMING)
(SCREAMING CONTINUES)
(ELECTRICITY CRACKLING)
- Father!
- No!
No!
(SCREAMING)
(SCREAMING CONTINUES)
(LABORED BREATHING)
(LASER FIRING)
I'm going in!
- (SPEAKING ALIEN LANGUAGE)
- Here goes nothing.
(TIE FIGHTERS ROARING LOUDLY)
Now lock onto the
strongest power source.
It should be the
power generator.
Form up.
WEDGE: Stay alert.
We could...
run out of space real fast.
(SCREAMING)
Split up and head
back to the surface.
See if you can
get a few of...
those TIE fighters
to follow you.
Copy, Gold Leader.
What? Like that?
- (GROANS)
- That was too close.
We've got to give those...
fighters more time.
Concentrate all fire on...
that Super Stardestroyer.
(EXPLODING)
Sir, we've lost our
bridge deflector shields.
Intensify the
forward batteries!
I don't want anything
to get through!
Intensify forward firepower!
(SCREAMING)
Too late!
(CHEERING)
(CRUMPLING EXPLOSIONS)
(ALARM BLARING)
(LUKE GRUNTS)
(MEN SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
Luke...
help me take...
this mask off.
But you'll die.
Nothing...
can stop that now.
Just for once.
Let me...
look on you...
with my own eyes.
(DARTH VADER BREATHES)
Now...
go, my son.
Leave me!
No. You're coming with me.
I'll not leave you here.
I've got to save you.
You already...
have, Luke.
You were right.
You were right about me.
Tell your sister...
you were right.
Father.
I won't leave you.
(THRILLING MUSIC PLAYING)
WEDGE: There it is.
All right, Wedge,
go for the power...
regulator on the
north tower.
Copy, Gold Leader.
I'm already on my way out.
(EXPLODING)
ACKBAR: Move the fleet...
away from the Death Star.
(MEN CLAMORING INDISTINCTLY)
(SIGHS SOFTLY)
- Yee-ha!
- (LAUGHING HAPPILY)
(CRUMPLING EXPLOSIONS)
(EWOKS CHEERING)
- (CHEWIE HOWLING LOUDLY)
- (R2-D2 BEEPING RAPIDLY)
They did it!
(CHEERING CONTINUES)
I'm sure Luke wasn't on...
that thing when it blew.
He wasn't.
I can feel it.
You love him.
Don't you?
Yes.
All right.
I understand.
Fine.
When he comes back...
I won't get in the way.
(SIGHS)
It's not like that at all.
He's my brother.
(DRAMATIC MUSIC PLAYING)
(SPEAKING EWOKESE)
(THRILLING MUSIC PLAYING)
(FIRE CRACKLING)
(CRACKLING CONTINUES)
(FIREWORKS CRACKLING)
(ALL CHEERING)
Wesa free!
(BELL TOLLING)
(MAN SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY)
MAN: Whoo!
(MAN SCREAMING)
(CRASH)
(CELEBRATION MUSIC PLAYING)
(SINGING IN EWOKESE)
(FIRE CRACKLING)
(EWOK YELLING)
(LANDO LAUGHING HAPPILY)
(R2-D2 BEEPING EXCITEDLY)
- (CHEWIE GROWLING RAPIDLY)
- (EWOKS YELLING)
(CHORUS VOCALIZING)
(VOCALIZING CONTINUES)
(THEME MUSIC PLAYING)