Hold positions!
Fire the arrows!
Tinúviel the elven-fair
Immortal maiden elven-wise
About him cast her night-dark hair
And arms like silver glimmering.
I am Arwen - I've come to help you.
Hear my voice...come back to the light.
Stay with the Hobbits,
I'll send horses for you.
I'm the faster rider, I'll take him.
The Road is too dangerous.
Frodo is dying.
If I can get across the river...
...the power of my people
will protect him.
As you wish.
Ride fast Asfaloth!
Waters of the Misty Mountains,
listen to the great word.
Flow waters of loudwater
against the ringwraiths
Waters of the Misty Mountains,
listen to the great word.
Flow waters of loudwater
against the ringwraiths
Hear my voice...
come back to the light.
The shadow does not hold sway yet, Aragorn
Not over you, not over me.
Do you remember when we first met?
I thought I had strayed into a dream.
Long years have passed.
You did not wear the
troubles you carry now.
Do you remember what I told you?
"One ring to rule them all...
...One ring to find them...
...One ring to bring them all...
...and in the darkness bind them."
Sit down, Legolas.
One ring to rule them all...
...One ring to find them...
She wanted to protect her child.
She thought in Rivendell
you would be safe.
Wake up cruel Redhorn!
May your horn be bloodstained!
Sleep Caradhras, be still,
lie still, hold your wrath!
Wake up cruel Redhorn!
May your bloodstained horn...
...fall upon enemy heads!
Gate of the elves, open now for me!
...listen to the word of my tongue.
Gate of elves...
...listen to my word..
...threshold of dwarves...
Doorway of the dwarf-folk...
Welcome, Legolas son of Thranduil.
Our fellowship stands in your debt,
Haldir of Lórien.
Oh, Aragorn of the Dúnedain...
...you are known to us.
I spit upon your grave!
We need your protection.
The road is fell!
I wish we may come with you.
Please, understand, we need your support!
The road is very dangerous.
You are being tracked.
For her love...
...I fear the grace of
Arwen Evenstar will diminish.
I would have her leave these shores...
...and be with her people.
I would have her take
the ship to Valinor.
Farewell.
There is much you have yet to do.
We shall not meet again, Elessar.
They will fall.