It's small!
No, please. No! Please!
Davey!
Come running, lad!
Stop!
Brand you like a damn steer, bitch!
No. Please!
- Hold the bitch! Go on, hold her!
Hold her, damn it,
I'll cut her tits off!
Go get Skinny! Quick!
- Ah!
Mike, don't!
Skinny!
Think it's funny?
Skinny, get the gun!
The gun, Skinny!
Get off of her, cowboy.
Wouldn't let you settle it?
You know Skinny.
He says he'll shoot them.
I says, "You can't."
He says, "Get Little Bill."
I says, "He's sleeping."
He says he don't care.
He'll shoot them boys soon.
She gonna die?
She's gonna live.
She didn't steal nothing
or touch his poke.
When she seen
his teensy little pecker...
...she giggled.
She didn't know no better.
You can hang them, Little Bill.
Clyde...
...step over to the office
and get the bullwhip.
A whipping's all they get
after what they done?
- It ain't no little thing, Alice.
- But what they done...
Alice! Shut up!
- Whipping ain't gonna settle this.
- No?
Here's a contract between me
and Delilah Fitzgerald, the cut whore.
I brought her from Boston,
paid her expenses and all.
I got a contract that represents
an investment of capital.
Property.
Damaged property.
Like if I hamstrung
one of their ponies.
You think nobody'll fuck her now?
Hell, no!
Won't pay to do it.
She can clean, but nobody's gonna pay
good money for a cut-up whore!
You boys are off the Bar T.
Got your own string of ponies?
Yeah, I got four.
Six.
You just as soon
not have a trial, no fuss?
No, sir.
All right.
You did the cutting.
Come the fall, you bring in
five ponies to Skinny here.
Five?
And you!
You bring in two.
You give them over, hear?
- Yes, sir.
Here's the bullwhip, Bill.
Maybe we don't need this now.
Let me tell you, come the spring,
Skinny don't have those ponies...
- I'll come looking for you.
- You ain't whipping them?
I fined them instead, Alice.
Skinny gets some ponies and that's it?!
That ain't fair.
That ain't fair!
Haven't you seen
enough blood tonight?
Hell, Alice!
It ain't like they was tramps or
loafers or bad men. They were just...
...hardworking boys that was foolish.
- If they was given over to wickedness...
- Like whores?
Alice? Tend to Delilah.
Go ahead.
I got $85.
I don't know.
If Delilah doesn't care,
why are we so riled up?
Just because we let them fools
ride us like horses...
...don't mean we let them
brand us like horses.
Maybe we ain't nothing but whores,
but, by God, we ain't horses!
I got $112.
That's everything.
How about you, Faith?
Two hundred.
Two hundred and forty dollars.
Jesus, Faith!
What you been doing?
Been giving Skinny something special?
She laughed.
With what Kate got, and Silky,
me and Little Sue...
It ain't enough.
Not yet, maybe.
You don't look like no
rootin'-tootin'...
...son of a bitching
cold-blooded assassin.
Say what?
My guess is you're calling yourself
Mr. William Munny.
You have me confused with
someone else, mister.
The same one who shot Charlie Pepper
in Lake County?
Pa! Hey, Pa!
What's up, son?
Two more hogs got the fever.
You shot Charlie Pepper.
You killed William Harvey
and robbed that train in Missouri.
Hold on, mister.
Son, get those hogs separated there.
Penny, help your brother.
That one's sick too?
Yeah.
We'll talk inside.
So you're Pete Sothow's nephew?
I thought you'd come to kill me for
something I'd done in the old days.
I could have. Easy.
I guess maybe so.
You don't look like no meaner-than-hell,
cold-blooded damn killer.
Maybe I ain't.
Uncle Pete says you was the meanest
goddamn son of a bitch alive.
And if I wanted a partner
for a killing, you were the worst one.
Meaning the best.
On account as
you're as cold as snow...
...and don't have no
weak nerve nor fear.
Pete said that?
Yeah, he did.
I'm a killer myself, except...
...I ain't killed as many as you
because of my youth.
Schofield Kid,
that's what they call me.
Why?
You from Schofield?
No, it's on account...
...of my Schofield model
Smith & Wesson pistol.
How about it, Will?
How about what?
How about being my partner?
I'm heading north through Niobrara
to Wyoming to kill two no-good cowboys.
For what?
For cutting up a lady.
Cut up her face.
Cut her eyes out,
cut her ears off.
They even cut her teats.
Jesus.
$1000 reward, Will.
500 apiece.
Pa?
I can't move those damn pigs!
Watch your cussing, will you?
Do the best you can with it.
Then go to the pump
and get cleaned up. Come on.
I ain't like that anymore, Kid.
It was whiskey done it as
much as anything else.
I ain't had a drop in over 10 years.
My wife, she cured me of that.
Cured me of drinking and wickedness.
You don't look so prosperous.
You could buy her a new dress
with your half.
- If we kill them, you can buy your...
- She's passed on.
What?
- Been gone near 3 years now.
- Oh.
Don't tell no one about the reward.
I don't need other gunmen collecting.
- We don't see no one out here.
- Yeah.
If you was to change your mind,
I'll be riding due west...
...for the trail into Wyoming.
Come on, let's separate those hogs.
Two others.
I think they got the fever.
Took you boys a while.
A few more days and I was
gonna call on the sheriff.
How about that?
The river was all swelled up.
Couldn't cross it.
I bet. Sleepy,
get them horses to the livery.
Neil, take that one
over around the back.
Yeah. Come on. Get them in there.
Come on.
Now there's a beauty.
You got two of mine.
This here one ain't yours.
We'll see about that.
Bastards! Get out of town!
Sick sons of bitches!
Whoa! Whoa! Whoa!
Don't come back, butcher!
- This here pony...
...I brung for the lady my partner cut.
Whoa. Whoa.
She's the best.
Better than the ones I gave him.
She can sell her...
...or do what she wants.
A pony? She ain't got no face left,
you give her a mangy pony?
She ain't mangy!
Get out of here!
Whoa! Whoa!
We don't need your damn charity!
Get out of our town
and don't come back!
Get out of our town!
Did Pa used to kill folks?
I could tell your ma liked
those flowers I gave her.
He ain't a saddle horse no more.
Ain't used to the feel.
Take care of your sister, son.
Kill a few chickens if you must.
Keep those hogs with the fever separate.
If you have any problem, go see
Sally Two Trees at Ned Logan's.
Whoa, whoa.
Ain't been in the saddle myself
in a while.
She's getting even with me
for the sins of my youth.
In my youth before I met
your dear departed ma...
...I used to be weak
and given to mistreating animals.
This horse
and those hogs over there...
...are getting even
for the cruelty I inflicted.
I used to be able to cuss...
...and whip a horse, but your ma
showed me the error of my ways.
I'll be back in two weeks.
Remember the spirit of your dear
departed ma watches over you.
Where'd you get the money?
We ain't got any!
- You told them cowboys you had!
- We was lying!
Lying?
What'll you do
if somebody comes to collect?
You going to hump them
a thousand times?
The kind of people who come for it
won't tolerate you not having it!
They won't just cut up your face!
You stupid bitches.
You stupid bitches!
Shit!
Damn it! Jesus!
Hit your finger?
Hello, Skinny.
Damn, you snuck up on me.
What do you think of her?
I heard you done the roof yourself.
Roof? Jesus, I did practically
the whole damn thing myself.
The Roberts boy carried wood for me,
but that's all.
What is all that wood?
I'm building a porch
so I can sit of an evening...
...and smoke my pipe and drink coffee
and watch the sunset.
Came out here just
to take a look at her?
Oh, them whores...
Yeah?
Been humping them cowboys
who been in town the last two weeks.
Shit, Skinny.
We got railroad barons.
We got cattle barons.
You'll be the first billiard baron.
They been humping and telling
every bowlegged one of them...
...they'll pay $1000 to whoever...
...kills the two boys
that cut up Delilah.
Those cowboys are riding that beef
down to Kansas and Cheyenne?
Yeah.
All week long?
I didn't hear till last night myself.
The word's probably got
all the way to Texas by now.
Nobody'll come clear from Texas.
You sure they got that money?
Women can lie. Asked where the
money is, they say they got none.
But those five could have
squirreled it away. Maybe.
That much?
You could run off them two cowboys.
I could run off them whores.
They'll just up and
run anyhow, them two.
Nope. They'll stay out at the Bar T.
Close to their friends.
Shit, could be nobody
won't come at all.
Got to go.
I like your house.
Well, I'll be...
It's Will!
Hey, Will.
Come in the house out of the sun.
Ned.
- Sally...
- ...see to Will's horse.
- Sally.
What are you doing here?
Just thought I'd drop in on you.
We ain't bad men no more.
We're farmers.
Should be easy killing them,
if they don't go on down to Texas.
How long since you fired a gun
at a man? Nine, ten years?
Eleven.
Easy, huh?
I don't know it was
all that easy even back then.
And we was young and full of beans.
If you was mad at them...
...over some wrong,
I could see shooting them.
We done stuff for money before.
Yeah.
We thought we did.
What'd these fellows do?
Cheat at cards?
Steal some strays?
Spit on a rich fellow? What?
They cut up a woman.
What?
Cut up her face, cut her eyes out,
cut her fingers off, cut her tits.
Everything but her cunny,
I suppose.
I'll be dogged.
Guess they got it coming.
Of course, Will...
...if Claudia was alive,
you wouldn't do this.
Could you look in on my youngsters
next week?
They got some hogs
they're trying to separate.
Will?
How long you reckon you're gonna be?
Two weeks, I guess.
Will?
Um...
What's this Kid like?
Three ways?
I see you still have
that Spencer rifle.
Yeah.
And I can still knock the
eye out of a bird flying too.
Jesus, Will!
He must be moving right along.
We'll come across him
tomorrow, I reckon.
Kind of got used to my bed.
This ain't going to be like no home.
That ain't the only thing I'll miss.
Boy, I'm gonna...
Hell, I'm sorry.
Don't fret it.
It ain't nothing.
She don't like it much,
you riding off with me.
- Sally?
- Gave me the evil eye.
You know, Sally's injun...
...and injuns ain't over-friendly.
I don't blame her.
I won't hold it against her.
She knew me back then.
She knew what a...
...no-good son of a bitch I was.
She ain't allowing that I changed.
She don't realize I ain't
like that no more.
- You know, Will...
- I ain't the same.
Claudia straightened me up.
Cleared me of drinking whiskey and all.
Going on this killing...
...don't mean I'll go back
to the way I was.
Just need the money.
- Get a new start for them youngsters.
- Yeah. Yeah.
Remember that drover
I shot in the mouth...
...and his teeth came
out the back of his head?
- Yeah.
- I think about him now and again.
He didn't do anything
to deserve to get shot.
At least nothing I remembered
when I sobered up.
You was one crazy son of a bitch.
No one liked me,
and the boys all thought...
...I'd shoot them
out of pure meanness.
You ain't like that no more.
Eagle, he hated my guts.
Bonaparte didn't think too much of me.
Quincy neither, I reckon.
Quincy used to just watch
all the time...
...scared.
Like I said...
...you ain't like that no more.
That's right.
I'm just a fellow now.
I ain't no different
than anyone else...
...no more.
What son of a bitch shot him?
Was it one of them John Bulls?
No, the would-be assassin
is a gentleman of French ancestry.
Or so it seems.
I don't wish to give offense...
...but the French are known
to be a race of assassins...
...who can't shoot worth a damn.
Any Frenchmen present
are excluded, of course.
Says here a fellow by the name
of Guiteau. G-U-I-T...
Sure as hell sounds
like a John Bull to me.
Again, I don't wish to give offense
when I suggest this country select...
...a king or even a queen,
rather than a president.
One isn't that quick
to shoot a king or a queen.
The majesty of royalty, you see.
Maybe you don't wish
to give offense, sir...
...but you are giving it pretty thick.
This country don't need
no queens whatsoever.
- When I heard about queens...
Shut up, Joe.
What's wrong with you, Thirsty?
This dude...
Might be that this dude
is English Bob.
Works for the railroad
shooting Chinamen.
Might be he's waiting
for some cowboy to touch his pistol...
...so he can shoot him.
Is that a fact, mister?
You English Bob?
Pheasants.
Let's shoot some pheasants.
Ten shots.
At, let's say, $1 a pheasant.
I'll shoot for the queen, and you...
...for whomever.
That's eight for me and one for you.
That comes to seven American dollars.
Pretty damn good shooting...
...for a John Bull.
No doubt your aim was
affected by your grief...
...over the injury to your president.
Come on, yeah!
It's the climate that does it.
And the infernal distances.
Does what?
Induces people to shoot
persons in high places.
- Yeah, uh...
It's a savage country.
That's the second one
shot in 20 years.
It's uncivilized shooting
persons of substance.
Come on.
Whoa. Whoa.
Thank you.
Pardon me, gentlemen.
The law obliges you to surrender
sidearms to the proper authorities.
Proper authority?
I assure you that neither my companion
or I carry firearms on our person.
We rely upon the goodwill
of our fellow man...
...and the forbearance of reptiles.
Unarmed, my ass!
Christ, it's hot!
If I'm going to get shot,
I'd rather it was hot than cold.
Everything hurts more when it's cold.
You know how if you hit...
Shut up, Fatty!
- I only say that...
- Clyde's back.
With Little Bill?
- No.
Shit!
- You clean my Remington?
- Cleaned and loaded.
Where's Little Bill?
Building his damn porch.
Building his porch?
If you got shot,
would you want it to be hot or cold?
I ain't gonna get shot.
He's coming?
Of course he's coming.
I just loaded that.
I don't trust nobody loading my guns
before a shooting.
What'd he say?
Little Bill said
he was building his porch.
- You seen that thing?
- It was all loaded.
Clyde, you got three pistols
and you only got one arm!
I don't want to get killed
for lack of shooting back.
He don't have a straight
angle on that whole porch!
Or the whole house, for that matter!
He is the worst damn carpenter.
He didn't say nothing?
Asked what they looked like.
Maybe he's tough, but he
sure ain't no carpenter.
Maybe he ain't so tough.
Seem like he was scared?
Little Bill? Him scared?
We never seen him up
against any like these ones.
Killers.
Little Bill come out of
Kansas and Texas, boys.
He worked them tough towns.
Just wondered.
Anybody could be scared.
He wasn't scared, boys.
He just ain't no carpenter.
There's a dignity in royalty...
...which precludes
the likelihood of assassination.
Uh-huh.
- If you pointed a pistol...
...at a monarch,
your hands would shake as if palsied.
I wouldn't point no pistol at nobody.
That's a wise policy.
But if you did, I assure you,
the sight of royalty...
...would cause you to dismiss thoughts
of bloodshed.
Right.
- You would stand...
How shall I put it?
In awe.
A president...
Why not shoot a president?
- Keep the change.
Thank you.
This Strawberry Alice
person, tell me again.
Down the street to Greely's Beer
Garden and Billiards Parlor.
Say you want a game of billiards.
- Billiards?
- Uh-huh.
Even though
I don't really wish to play?
No matter. They burned the
table in '78 for firewood.
Quite right.
Mr. Beauchamp,
I think a cup of tea...
Hello, Bob.
Boys, this here is English Bob.
Shit and fried eggs.
Been a long time.
Run out of Chinamen?
I thought that you were dead.
You've shaved your chin whiskers off.
I was tasting the soup
two hours after I ate it.
Actually, what I heard was,
you fell off your horse...
...drunk, of course.
And that you broke your bloody neck.
I heard that one myself, Bob.
Hell, I even thought I was dead.
Till I found out
I was just in Nebraska.
Who's he?
- W.W. Beauchamp.
- Beauchamp.
This is Little Bill Daggett.
- And friends, of course.
- Daggett?
From Newton, Hays? From Abilene?
In person.
You work for the railroads too?
No. I write.
Letters?
Books, Bill. Books.
Actually...
...he's my biographer.
I wouldn't do that if I were you.
It's only a book.
A book?
That means you boys can read.
That means you saw the signs outside
town saying surrender your firearms.
But like you told young Andy...
...you're not armed, are you?
Not really, Bill.
Got a Peacemaker, but that
wouldn't worry you, would it?
If you don't see it.
Or better, if you don't hear it.
I'm afraid so, Bob.
I don't like firearms around.
Be very careful with it, sonny.
Charley?
See what kind of books
Mr. Beauchamp is packing.
Make sure you don't get wet.
No shit.
All he's got is writing
stuff and this book.
The Duck of Death?
Duke.
"The Duke."
Good afternoon, gentlemen.
I'll have that .32, Bob.
Now, Little Bill...
...you will leave me at
the mercy of my enemies.
Enemies?
You been talking about the queen again?
On Independence Day?
Easy. Easy. Easy.
I guess you think I'm kicking you.
But it ain't so!
What I'm doing is talking!
You hear?!
Talking to all those goons down there in Kansas!
To all those villains in Missouri!
And those villains...
...down in Cheyenne!
I'm saying there ain't no whore's gold!
Even if there was,
they wouldn't want to come for it...
...anyhow!
What are you looking at?!
Go on!
Scoot!
Mind your own business!
Hey, Will.
Ever go into town?
On occasion.
To sell a hog, pick up supplies.
No, no, I mean...
I mean, get yourself a woman.
No, I never go into town for that.
A man like me?
Only woman I could get is
one I'd have to pay for.
That ain't right, buying flesh.
Claudia, rest her soul,
wouldn't want me doing that...
...me being a father.
So...
You just use your hand?
I don't miss it all that much.
Will!
Goddamn!
Somebody's shooting at us!
- Yeah.
- Shit. Did it hit you?
I bumped my head
falling off my horse.
Ain't shooting at us no more.
Shooting way over yonder.
What the hell's he shooting at?
Beats the hell out of me.
Reckon we in somebody's field?
I didn't see nothing planted.
Shooting at us again.
He's shooting at the whole horizon.
- Hey!
- Wait! You'll mark us!
Hey, Kid!
- That's the Kid shooting at us?
- Kid, it's me! Will Munny!
What's he shooting at us for?
Is that you?
Yeah, it's me!
Don't go shooting at us
no more! You hear me?
Who the hell you got with you, Will?
It's Ned Logan, my old partner!
Don't go shooting at us, you hear?
We'll get our horses
and come on over there.
You ain't going to shoot, are you?
No, I ain't!
- Chased that horse a damn mile.
- What was you shooting at us for?
I thought you was following me.
- We was.
- You said if I changed my mind...
Nothing said about no partner.
This here's Ned Logan.
He's the Schofield Kid,
nephew to Pete Sothow.
I seen two fellows following me.
My guess is, you come to kill me.
We never talked about no other fellow.
There's two cowboys. Better there's
three of us, if they got friends.
I can take care of them two myself.
It don't take three.
Ned's an awful good shot with a rifle.
Hit a bird in the eye flying.
Better than you, anyhow.
You wasn't even close.
Get your damn hands off my rifle!
Thought I'd check it for you.
Maybe something's bent.
It ain't bent.
- You were shooting all over!
- You'll share your half with him?
I figure three ways.
You figured wrong.
Sorry I wasted your time, Ned.
You going back with him?
He's my partner.
He don't go, I don't go.
What's it come to, three ways?
Shit!
- What are you pissing on about?
- What?
- What are you looking at, anyhow?
- Looking at?
Clouds, Kid.
Looking at them on account of
we got a storm riding up our ass.
Hell, I seen them.
You was smart to change your mind.
- Yeah?
- Yeah.
I'm a real good shot with this rifle.
See that hawk?
I could hit it with one shot.
Hell, I could hit it too.
If I didn't mind wasting a shot.
There ain't no hawk, Kid.
You can't see for shit, can you?
See your canteen?
How far can you see?
- Far enough.
- We ain't shooting canteens! How far?
- 100 yards?
- More.
- See that scrub oak tree yonder?
- Fuck you.
- He's blind!
- I ain't blind, you asshole!
Hold it!
How far can you see, Kid?
50 yards?
You bet your ass
I can see 50 yards, Will.
I can see well enough
to shoot this son of a bitch.
Hold on.
Hear that, Ned?
Kid can see 50 yards. Fine.
Jesus!
50 yards'll do just fine.
Now let's move out.
They look like real hard cases, Bob.
Did you kill all seven of them?
Or just wing some of them?
That you here, Bob, on the cover?
"The Duck of Death"?
It's the Duke.
"Duke of Death."
Duke, yeah.
You always were the hell in Jesus
with a pistol, but seven of them?
Protecting that woman.
How do you do that?
Uh, you see, uh...
It's desirable in the publishing
business to take a certain...
...liberty when depicting
the cover scene.
For reasons involving the marketplace...
From what I read, the writing's not
that much different than the picture.
I can assure you, Mr. Daggett...
...that the events described are
from eyewitness accounts.
- Eyewitnesses?
- Yes, sir.
Like the Duck himself, I guess.
The Duke.
Duck, I says.
"'You have insulted the honor of
this beautiful woman, Corcoran...'
...said the Duck.
'You must apologize.'
But Two-Gun Corcoran
would have none of it.
He reached for his
pistols and would have killed him...
...but the Duck was faster and hot lead
blazed from his smoking six-guns."
I consider that an accurate
depiction of events.
There is a certain poetry to the
language which I couldn't resist.
Mr. Beauchamp.
I was in the Blue Bottle
Saloon in Wichita...
...the night English Bob
killed Corky Corcoran.
I didn't see you there.
Nor no woman.
Nor two-gun shooters.
- Nor none of this.
- You were there?
Yeah, I was there.
First off...
...Corky never carried two guns,
though he should have.
He was called Two-Gun Corcoran.
A lot of folks did call him Two-Gun,
but not because he had two pistols.
It was because his dick...
...was longer than the barrel
on his Walker Colt.
Only insulting he did was stick it
into a French lady Bob was sweet on.
When Corky walked into the Blue Bottle
and before he knew what's what...
...Bob takes a shot at him!
And misses, he's so damn drunk.
That bullet whizzing by panicked Corky.
He did the wrong thing.
He hurried
and shot his damn toe off.
Meantime, Bob here...
...aims real good
and squeezes off another...
...but he misses, he's still so drunk!
Hits a $1000 mirror over the bar.
The Duck of Death is as good as dead
because Corky does it right.
He aims real careful.
- No hurry.
- And?
Bam!
That Walker Colt blew up in his hand,
a failing common to that model.
If Corky'd had two guns instead of
a big dick, he would've been there...
...to defend himself to the end.
Wait a minute.
English Bob killed him when
he didn't even have...
Bob wasn't going to wait
for Corky to grow a new hand.
No, he just
walked over there real slow...
...because he was drunk...
...and shot him
through the liver.
Don't like rocks
on my dadgum back!
- I sure do miss my bed.
- You said that last night.
Last night I said I missed my wife.
Tonight I just miss my dadgum bed!
You'll miss your dadgum
roof next, I suppose.
Shit!
Say, Will?
Hm?
That business up in Jackson County,
that really happen?
- The way they say it happened?
- What business?
There's two deputies up close
pointing their rifles right at you.
Got you dead to rights.
You pulled out your pistol
and blew them to hell.
Only took a scratch yourself.
Uncle Pete never seen
nothing like it...
...shooting your way out
of that scrape.
Yeah. I don't recollect.
You don't recollect?
That's right.
Ned...
...how many men you killed?
Ain't you gonna answer?
What the hell's that to you?
To know the kind of fellow I'm riding
with, in case we get into a scrape.
- How many men you killed, Kid?
- Five.
How many?
Five!
I done killed five of them.
That's including a Mexican.
He come after me with a knife.
Why don't you shut up?
Get some rest.
You boys are as crotchety
as a couple of old hens.
Actually, then, Mr. Corcoran was faster
on the draw than the Duck...
Than English Bob?
Faster?
Faster was his mistake.
If he hadn't rushed, he wouldn't have
shot himself in the toe.
He would've killed old Bob.
Look, son.
Being a good shot,
being quick with a pistol...
...don't do no harm, but it don't mean
much next to being cool-headed.
A man who'll keep his head,
not get rattled under fire...
...like as not he'll kill you.
- But if the other fellow is quicker...
- Then he'll hurry and he'll miss.
Look here.
That's as fast as I can draw, aim, hit
anything more than 10 feet away.
Unless it's a barn.
But if he doesn't miss?
He'll kill you.
That's why there's so few
dangerous men around like Bob.
Like me.
It ain't so easy to shoot a man
if he's shooting back.
- That'll flat rattle some folks.
- Yeah.
- Let me show you something.
- Just a minute.
Look here.
- I know. Just...
Take that.
Go on, take it.
There's the key.
Just shoot me...
...and you and Bob can
ride on out of here free as birds.
- Is it loaded?
- Wouldn't do any good if it wasn't.
First, you got to cock it.
Go on, cock it.
Now you got to point it.
Go on. Point it.
Now all you got to do
is pull the trigger.
Hot, ain't it?
Didn't even put your finger
on the trigger.
What if...?
What if I gave it to him?
Give it to him.
- You don't really want me to...
- Give it to him.
I guess he don't want it.
You were right not to take it.
I'd have killed you.
We could use some rain.
You no-good, goddamn
pig-fucking whore!
Sorry, old horse.
I brung this
for when we kill them fellows.
Figured we could use some now.
Not me. I don't touch it no more.
- Come on, it's raining.
- I know it's raining!
Give some to the Kid.
You think that Kid
really killed five men?
No.
When he talked about the time
them deputies had the drop on you...
Yeah?
I remember
there was three men you shot, not two.
I ain't like that no more, Ned!
I ain't no crazy killing fool.
Still think it'll be easy
to kill them cowboys?
If we don't drown first.
Give these keys to the conductor.
He can loose Bob's cuffs
as soon as he's outside the county.
- Yeah.
- Got my pistols?
I guess you know, Bob...
...that if I see you again
I'll just shoot in self-defense.
I didn't steal your biographer!
He's staying on his own account!
He can go stuff himself
as well, can't he?!
The plague on the whole
stinking lot of you!
Without morals or laws!
And all you whores!
You got no laws and no honor!
It's no wonder you all
emigrated to America!
Because they wouldn't have you
in England!
You're a lot of savages!
You're all a bunch of bloody savages!
A curse on you!
I'll be back!
- Nobody's going to come...
- Huh?
...after what Little Bill done
to that Englishman.
Delilah, can't you
get them tables clean?
Cover your face, somebody might hump
you and you wouldn't have to clean.
- What do they call that face cover?
- A veil.
Yeah. Get a veil!
Rain's coming.
Thank God.
Will?
You sure?
You all right, Will?
Fellow asking for you.
Tonight?
You ain't joshing?
This way, mister.
Must be randy as hell
to come out in this shit.
"No, no!
You're wrong, Little Bill!" he said.
"That's not a Curly J.
That's a Bobbed J!"
He had changed it over.
And I said to him:
"Jim, you're a liar
and a horse thief!"
When he saw nobody would help him,
he started crying...
...and sobbing
and just carrying on.
He said, "God, please,
don't kill me, Bill!"
So I said, "Jim, it makes me sick..."
- Open the window, will you?
- Yeah.
"...to see a man carrying
two pistols and a Henry rifle...
...and crying like a damn baby."
So you killed him?
- No.
But I should have.
I can't abide them kind.
You see them in the taverns.
Tramps and drunk teamsters.
- Crazed miners.
- Yeah.
Sporting their pistols and
acting like they was bad men.
But without any sand or character.
Not even any bad character.
- I do not like assassins.
- Assassins.
Or men of low character.
- Like your friend, English Bob.
- Uh-huh.
- But, now Bob was no coward.
- No.
He wouldn't cry
and carry on like that...
Sheriff... I just...
I don't have any more receptacles.
Maybe you should hang the carpenter.
What?
Oh, uh...
I was just saying because of the...
You hang...
Doesn't matter.
What the hell?
On a night like this!
- Who the hell is it?
Deputy Charley Hecker, Bill.
What?
Three fellows just come into town.
They're down to Greely's.
At least two of them got guns.
What the hell's keeping that Kid?
You don't suppose he's up...
Jesus, Will!
You look like shit.
You remember Eagle Hendershot?
Yeah.
I saw him.
Will, he's dead.
No, I saw him, Ned.
His head was broke open.
You could see inside of it.
Jesus! You got a fever.
- Take a drink, will you?
- Worms were coming out.
Look, I'm going up
to see what's keeping the Kid.
Must be getting an advance
from one of the sporting ladies.
If I was to...
If it worked out that I could take
a little time for myself...
I mean you wouldn't...
I guess you wouldn't want to come.
Give me the pistol.
I says give me over your pistol.
I ain't drunk.
Ordinance says you got to turn in
your firearms to my office...
...day or night.
I guess you didn't see the sign,
because of the weather.
No.
But I ain't...
I ain't armed.
What about your friends upstairs?
They got any pistols?
They ain't armed either.
Spilled your whiskey.
- I said...
What's your name?
- William...
William?
...Hendershot.
Well, Mr. William Hendershot...
...what if I was to say you was
a no-good son of a bitch and a liar?
And if I was to say you shit in your
pants because of a cowardly soul...
...I bet you'd show me that pistol
quick and kill me. Isn't that so?
Maybe, yeah, I guess.
But the fact is...
...I ain't carrying no firearm.
Get up.
Come on.
What's this for,
snakes and such?
Yeah.
We don't have any snakes in here,
Mr. Hendershot.
Well...
It ain't loaded or...
Powder's wet.
You see, Mr. Beauchamp?
This is the trash
I was speaking of!
They're in all the saloons
in all your prosperous communities!
Wichita!
Over in Cheyenne!
Abilene!
But not in the town of Big Whiskey.
Hurry up!
You know what to tell Bill.
Look for that lone pine.
Miss the pine, you won't find it.
Forget the shirt!
Put the boots on!
What'll we do about Will?
Come on, Kid!
Let's hope them horses are still there!
Let the man out, W.W.
He's desiring to leave the hospitality
of Big Whiskey behind him.
Easy!
- She's got to turn a dollar a time.
- Why'd they lit out the back window?
They seen you beating on their friend.
- They come for the billiards, honest.
Billiards?!
- They were just passing through?
- They was going to Fort Buford.
You kicked the shit
out of an innocent man.
Innocent?
Innocent of what?
Ah, Jesus.
Jesus, Ned! You done this before?
Plenty of times.
His pistol must've jammed.
Here. Bring that candle in closer.
I can't see.
He wouldn't take no beating
if it hadn't jammed.
He wouldn't give it over
and not shoot.
He don't look so good.
He didn't even pull his pistol?
He ain't as tough as you, Kid.
I'd have pulled my pistol.
You did!
Out of the lady and out the window!
- That was your idea! I...
- We got to go.
What? I'm ready for another advance.
You'll use it all up.
No more advances.
Sweetheart, we're just waiting
on this weather to clear!
We're going to need more food!
About three days' worth.
Three days?
We can kill them tomorrow.
- I don't kill nobody without him.
- We don't need him! We can do it.
Besides...
...he ain't nothing
but a broken-down pig farmer.
We'll bring food in the morning,
and some whiskey too!
And some medicine if you got any!
Don't it make you sick hearing him?
Don't you ladies worry!
Me and Ned, we'll kill them two
sons of bitches for you!
Claudia.
Will?
- Claudia's not here.
- Is that you, Ned?
I seen him.
I seen the Angel of Death.
I seen a river, Ned.
- He's got snake eyes.
- Who's got snake eyes?
It's the Angel of Death.
Oh, Ned. Oh, Ned.
I'm scared of dying.
Easy, partner.
I seen Claudia too.
That's good you saw Claudia, ain't it?
Her face was all covered with worms.
Ned, I'm scared.
I'm dying.
You won't...
No, don't tell nobody.
Don't tell my kids...
...none of the things I done.
You hear me?
All right, Will.
He's gonna die, ain't he?
Maybe.
Supposing he does?
We'll bury him.
That ain't what I mean.
You mean, will I help
you kill them cowboys?
I can't spot them myself.
But you could.
That big bastard, you could spot him
a half-mile off, I bet.
And if I spot him?
Then I ride up close and shoot him.
Just like that?
I'm a damn killer.
I done it before.
I'm more of a killer than he is.
Yeah?
Yeah.
I thought you was an angel.
You ain't dead.
Some big fellow...
...kicked the hell out of me.
I must look like you now.
You don't look nothing like me.
No offense meant.
You got to be the one
those cowboys cut up.
My partners, Ned and that Kid...
...they around?
They went out scouting
when your fever broke.
Scouting?
Out to the Bar T...
...looking for them.
How long I been here?
Three days.
Are you hungry or...?
Three days?
I ought to be...
I thought I was gone.
I wouldn't normally pay no notice
to high country like this...
...trees,
but I'm sure noticing now.
Thought I was dying for sure.
I brought your hat.
You left it down at Greely's.
Thanks.
That sheriff...
- He still looking for me?
- Little Bill?
No, he thinks you went south.
Are you really gonna
kill them cowboys?
I guess.
Still a payment coming, isn't there?
Them other two, your friends...
...they been taking
advances on the payment.
Advances?
- Free ones.
- Free ones?
Alice and Silky been
giving them free ones.
I see.
Would you like a free one?
No. I guess not.
I didn't mean with me.
I meant...
...Alice and Silky would be happy
to give you a free one if you wanted.
That's all I meant.
I didn't mean...
...I didn't want a free one
because you been cut up and all.
What I said about you looking like me,
that ain't true.
You ain't ugly like me.
It's just that we both got scars.
You're a beautiful woman,
and if I wanted a free one...
...I'd want it with you
more than the other two.
It's just that...
...I can't on account of my wife.
Your wife?
Yeah. You see?
I admire you for that.
For being true to your wife.
I've known a lot of men...
...who weren't.
I suppose.
Is she back in Kansas?
Yeah.
She's watching over my young ones.
Hang on!
Get the damn iron!
Davey! Davey!
Jesus, fellas!
Jesus, boys, my leg's broke!
I'm pinned, boys!
Better finish him, Ned.
He ain't dead? You didn't get him?
He got the boy's horse.
Finish him before he gets clear.
Get behind them rocks.
Get over there!
- What happened? He ain't killed?!
Hurry up, Davey!
What's going on?
He gets in those rocks,
we won't get him.
- Unless we go down there.
What rocks?
Why don't you shoot?
What's going on?
Shoot!
- Will...
You backshooting bastards!
I ain't very good with one of these.
Keep going, Davey! The rocks!
Did you get him?
Where is he?
How many more shots do I have?
- Two.
Bastards!
- Go, Davey!
- Did you get him?
Here, reload this.
Slim.
- You missed him.
- I got him.
They shot me, boys.
- He ain't killed.
They shot me.
Maybe, maybe not.
Got him through the gut, I think.
Think he'll die?
You think we killed him?
They shot me, boys.
Yeah.
We killed him, I guess.
I'm dying, boys!
Then you shouldn't have out up
no woman, you asshole!
Jesus, I'm so thirsty!
Give me some water, please!
Please, Slim!
I'm bleeding, Slim!
Drink of water, please.
Give him a drink of water,
goddamn it!
Give me a drink of water, Slim!
Give him some water, for chrissake!
We ain't gonna shoot!
- You ain't gonna shoot?
- No.
Hold on, Davey-boy!
Here I come now!
Don't shoot me, you bastards!
Davey. Shit!
Davey!
They take him water?
Yeah.
Jesus, Johnny! They shot him!
Hold on now!
No!
You murdering bastards!
You killed our Davey-boy!
When will we double back?
After a ways.
Not me.
- I'm heading back down to Kansas.
- We got to kill the other one first.
With any luck, we'll find him
by nightfall or in the morning.
We'll shoot him
and head back with the money.
- Do you want the Spencer?
- It's no time to quit.
- You'll lose your share.
- Shut up!
I'll see you, Will.
So long, Kid.
Ned.
Here. I ain't no good
with that damn thing.
Me and the Kid'll head over
to that ranch and we'll shoot him.
We'll meet up with you,
get our money, and go back together.
Suppose he don't go back
to the ranch?
He ain't going into town
or stay out in the open country.
He'll hole up at that ranch.
I ain't waiting.
I'll look in on your young ones.
Hey, Ned.
Forget what the Kid said
about the money.
I'll bring your share.
Kid's full of shit.
Little Bill? Little Bill?
Just doing some repairs up here.
They killed one of them cowboys.
Shit!
Parson said he saw three men,
right after sunup, headed east.
One was on a dun and another
was on a flea-bitten gray.
He didn't know what the third one
was on, maybe an appaloosa.
Amos says to ask if the county
will pay for feed for all the horses.
Witherspoon won't sell us
no more shells without pay.
Hell, use my dogs!
Then the county's got
to be responsible.
Get on out there to the Bar T
and make sure that other cowboy...
...stays put
and don't expose himself.
All right.
I didn't think they'd really do it.
Think they come up
from Kansas to fuck us?
That Kid, he's just a boy
and the other one...
...Will, the nice one,
being so true to his wife...
Wife?
He ain't got no wife.
- Yes, he does. He...
- He ain't got no wife.
Not above ground, anyways.
Murdering whores!
He had it coming!
He had it coming for what he done!
And the other one too!
Both of them for what they done!
We got one!
They got one.
We got one, sheriff!
Out by Cow Creek!
- Is he alive?
- Hell, yeah!
Bunch of us from Bar T went looking
because they killed one of our own.
Come across the bastard
on a roan heading south.
He admit it?
No. But I guess he will soon enough.
Had a Spencer rifle on him.
They messing him up?
Little bit.
Clyde, Andy.
Get out there. Find out
what happened to those other two!
See anything out there, Buck?
Hell, yes!
Seen about 200 fellows packing rifles.
Got the place surrounded.
Say they want Quick Mike's ass.
I said, "How much?" They says, "Five."
I said, "Dollars?"
They said, "Cents."
I said, "Sold."
Well, I ain't worried!
Because I got me some protection.
Tell you where them is?
- Nope.
Any names?
- Only told us his name, Ned Roundtree.
Bring him in. So Ned...
...you'll want to tell me
and Mr. Beauchamp here...
...all about your two friends.
I'll want the names and
whereabouts of those son of a bitches.
Sure is ripe.
Yeah. Going to get a lot riper.
Think he's still in there?
He's in there.
He's holding on to his shit
like it was money.
He's in there.
- Tell me right off if you see him.
- Yeah.
You won't shoot him your own self?
You can shoot him.
Now you and Mr. Quincy and...
What was the young fellow's name?
Elroy Tate.
No, that's not what you said.
- Hell if it ain't!
- No, you said:
"Elroy Quincy out of Medicine Hat...
...and Henry Tate out of Cheyenne."
Hell if I did.
- Hell if I did.
- Charley?
Go get them whores that
pumped these boys that night.
Strawberry Alice and Silky?
Go on and get them!
Now, Ned.
Them whores are going to tell
different lies than you.
And when their lies
ain't the same as your lies...
Well, I ain't going to hurt no woman.
But I'm going to hurt you.
Not gentle like before...
...but bad.
Where you going?
- The shithouse.
- Let me finish.
To protect me while I take a dump?
- You'll get bushwhacked.
- I'll fart on them.
I'll go.
- Yeah, you can wipe my ass, Thirsty.
Hell with him. He ain't polite,
he should get shot.
Is that him?
Yeah, that's him.
All right, Kid. Go get him.
He's all yours.
Assassins!
Shoot him!
No.
No, no!
Come on, goddamn it!
- Did you get him?
- Yeah.
Cover me.
- I can't see them!
Just shoot!
Was it like that in the old days?
Everybody riding out, shooting...
...smoke all over, folks yelling,
bullets whizzing by?
I guess so.
Shit, I thought they'd get us.
I was even scared a little.
For a minute.
You ever scared in them days?
I can't remember.
I was drunk most of the time.
I shot that fucker three times!
He was taking a shit,
went for his pistol and I blazed away.
First shot...
...I got him right in the chest.
Say, Will?
- Yeah?
That was the first one.
First one what?
First one I ever killed.
Yeah?
You know how I said I shot five men?
It weren't true.
That Mexican with the knife?
I just busted his leg with a shovel.
I didn't kill him or nothing.
You sure killed
the hell out of that fellow today.
Hell, yeah!
Killed the hell out of him, didn't I?
Three shots and he was taking a shit.
Take a drink, Kid.
Jesus Christ!
It don't seem real.
How he ain't gonna
never breath again, ever.
How he's dead.
And the other one too.
On account of pulling a trigger.
It's a hell of a thing, killing a man.
You take away all he's got...
...and all he's ever gonna have.
I guess they had it coming.
We all have it coming, Kid.
I was watching
that you weren't followed.
Silky and Faith rode off to the east
and two deputies followed them.
You want to help me count this?
- I trust you.
Don't go trusting me too much.
In fact, we'll give Ned his share together.
You'll know I ain't holding out on you.
Ned's share?
He went south.
We'll catch up.
He's dead.
What do you mean, dead?
He went south yesterday.
He ain't dead.
They killed him.
I thought you knew.
Nobody killed Ned!
He didn't kill anyone.
He went south!
Why would anybody kill Ned?
Who killed him?
Little Bill.
The Bar T boys caught him...
...and Little Bill beat him up.
He was making him answer questions,
beating him up. Then Ned just died.
They got a sign on him
says he was a killer.
A sign on him?
In front of Greely's.
A sign on him in front of Greely's!
These questions he was asking...
...what kind were they?
About where you and him was.
Then what?
A cowboy come in saying
you killed Quick Mike in the shithouse.
So Little Bill killed him
for what we done?
Not on purpose.
But he started hurting him worse.
Making him tell stuff.
First, Ned wouldn't talk.
Then Little Bill hurt him so bad,
he said who you was.
He said how you was really
William Munny out of Missouri.
Little Bill said, "The one
who dynamited...
...the railroad in '69,
killing women and children?"
Ned said you done a lot worse.
Said you was...
...more cold-blooded than Will Bonney.
Said if he hurt Ned again...
...you'd come kill him
like you killed the U.S. marshal in '70.
That didn't scare him, did it?
No, sir.
Give me your Schofield.
What for, Will?
- Give it to me.
- Yeah. Sure.
You want it, keep it.
I won't use it.
I won't kill nobody no more.
I ain't like you, Will.
You better ride on back, miss.
Go on, keep all of it.
It's yours.
What about spectacles
and fancy clothes?
I'd rather be blind and ragged
than dead.
You don't have to worry, Kid.
I ain't going to kill you.
You're the only friend I got.
Take this money and give my half
and Ned's half to my kids.
Tell them if I ain't back in a week,
to give half to Sally.
You keep the rest.
Get them spectacles.
You'll go kill Little Bill?
Stay clear of folks you see.
There'll be a lot out to hang you.
Get going.
I'll say this just one more time,
so don't ask me again!
Those on today's posse got one drink
coming from the county budget!
And those who rode yesterday
get one for that too.
Hold it!
That's two! After that, it comes
out of your own pocket! You hear?
Yes, sir.
- We'll pull out early in the morning.
We'll chase them clear to Texas,
so don't spend too much money.
We'll divide up into four parties!
We'll hit all the farms and trails
in a big circle.
We're bound to find somebody
who's seen these skunks.
Who owns this shithole?
You, fat man. Speak up.
I own this establishment.
I bought it from Greely for $1000.
- Better clear out.
Yes, sir.
Hold it!
Sir, you are
a cowardly son of a bitch!
You just shot an unarmed man.
He should've armed himself...
...if he's going to decorate his saloon
with my friend.
You'd be William Munny
out of Missouri...
...killer of women and children.
That's right.
I killed women and children.
Killed just about everything
that walks or crawls.
And I'm here to kill you, Little Bill.
For what you did to Ned.
You boys better move away.
All right, gentlemen.
He's got one barrel left.
When he fires it,
use your pistols...
...and shoot him down
like the mangy scoundrel he is!
Misfire! Kill the son of a bitch!
Ah!
Any man don't want to get killed,
better clear on out the back.
I'm shot! I'm shot!
You ain't shot.
Please.
I don't have a gun.
I am not armed.
Pick up that rifle.
- Pick it up.
- I... I...
Shells too.
Oh, God.
You killed Little Bill.
Sure you ain't armed?
I'm not.
I don't have a gun.
I've never had a gun.
I'm a writer!
- A writer?
- Yeah.
- Letters and such?
- Books.
- Yeah.
I don't believe it, you killed
five men. Single-handed.
Yeah.
Uh...
- That's a Spencer rifle, right?
- Right.
Who'd you kill first?
Huh?
"When confronted by superior numbers...
...an experienced gunfighter will
fire on the best shot first."
- Is that so?
- Little Bill said that.
You probably killed him first.
I was lucky in the order.
I'm always lucky
when it comes to killing folks.
That so? Who was next?
Clyde, right?
You killed Clyde,
or it was Deputy Andy...
All I can tell you is,
who'll be last.
I don't deserve this.
To die like this.
I was building a house.
Deserve's got nothing to do with it.
I'll see you in hell, William Munny.
Yeah.
All right, I'm coming out!
Any man I see out there, I'll kill him!
Anyone takes a shot at me...
...I'm not only going to kill him,
but his wife and all his friends.
And burn his damn house down!
Nobody better shoot!
Charley, go ahead.
Shoot him!
I can't.
Hell, no!
I ain't no deputy!
You better bury Ned right!
You better not cut up
nor otherwise harm no whores!
Or I'll come back and kill every
one of you sons of bitches.